<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo812#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo812</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Sall_e_2010,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo812},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo812},
	year = 2010,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {4},
	pages = {273--279},
	author = {J. B. Sall{\'{e}}e and K. G. Speer and S. R. Rintoul},
	title = {Zonally asymmetric response of the Southern Ocean mixed-layer depth to the Southern Annular Mode},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Zonally asymmetric response of the Southern Ocean mixed-layer depth to the Southern Annular Mode
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>97</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>97</offset>
        <text>Interactions between the atmosphere and ocean are mediated by the mixed layer at the ocean surface.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>197</offset>
        <text>The depth of this layer is determined by wind forcing and heating from the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>284</offset>
        <text>Variations in mixed-layer depth affect the rate of exchange between the atmosphere and deeper ocean, the capacity of the ocean to store heat and carbon and the availability of light and nutrients to support the growth of phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>520</offset>
        <text>However, the response of the Southern Ocean mixed layer to changes in the atmosphere is not well known.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>624</offset>
        <text>Here we analyse temperature and salinity data from Argo profiling floats to show that the Southern Annular Mode (SAM), the dominant mode of atmospheric variability in the Southern Hemisphere, leads to large-scale anomalies in mixed-layer depth that are zonally asymmetric.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>897</offset>
        <text>From a simple heat budget of the mixed layer we conclude that meridional winds associated with departures of the SAM from zonal symmetry cause anomalies in heat flux that can, in turn, explain the observed changes of mixed-layer depth and sea surface temperature.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1161</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that changes in the SAM, including recent and projected trends attributed to human activity, drive variations in Southern Ocean mixed-layer depth, with consequences for air-sea exchange, ocean sequestration of heat and carbon, and biological productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
