<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1807#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1807</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Sluijs_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1807},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1807},
	year = 2013,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {6},
	number = {6},
	pages = {429--434},
	author = {Appy Sluijs and Richard E. Zeebe and Peter K. Bijl and Steven M. Bohaty},
	title = {A middle Eocene carbon cycle conundrum},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A middle Eocene carbon cycle conundrum
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>39</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>39</offset>
        <text>The Middle Eocene Climatic Optimum (MECO) was an approximately 500,000-year-long episode of widespread ocean-atmosphere warming about 40 million years ago, superimposed on a long-term middle Eocene cooling trend.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>252</offset>
        <text>It was marked by a rise in atmospheric CO2 concentrations, biotic changes and prolonged carbonate dissolution in the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>381</offset>
        <text>However, based on carbon cycle theory, a rise in atmospheric CO2 and warming should have enhanced continental weathering on timescales of the MECO.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>529</offset>
        <text>This should have in turn increased ocean carbonate mineral saturation state and carbonate burial in deep-sea sediments, rather than the recorded dissolution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>687</offset>
        <text>We explore several scenarios using a carbon cycle model in an attempt to reconcile the data with theory, but these simulations confirm the problem.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>835</offset>
        <text>The model only produces critical MECO features when we invoke a sea-level rise, which redistributes carbonate burial from deep oceans to continental shelves and decreases shelf sediment weathering.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1033</offset>
        <text>Sufficient field data to assess this scenario is currently lacking.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1101</offset>
        <text>We call for an integrated approach to unravel Earth system dynamics during carbon cycle variations that are of intermediate timescales (several hundreds of thousands of years), such as the MECO.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
