<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1273#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1273</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Gruber_2011,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1273},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1273},
	year = 2011,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {11},
	pages = {787--792},
	author = {Nicolas Gruber and Zouhair Lachkar and Hartmut Frenzel and Patrick Marchesiello and Matthias MĂźnnich and James C. McWilliams and Takeyoshi Nagai and Gian-Kasper Plattner},
	title = {Eddy-induced reduction of biological production in eastern boundary upwelling systems},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Eddy-induced reduction of biological production in eastern boundary upwelling systems
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>Eddies and other mesoscale oceanic processes, such as fronts, can enhance biological production in the ocean, according to several open-ocean studies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>237</offset>
        <text>The effect is thought to be particularly pronounced in low-nutrient environments, where mesoscale processes increase the net upward flux of limiting nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>397</offset>
        <text>However, eddies have been suggested to suppress production in the highly productive eastern boundary upwelling systems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>517</offset>
        <text>Here, we examine the relationship between satellite-derived estimates of net primary production, of upwelling strength, and of eddy-kinetic energy--a measure of the intensity of mesoscale activity--in the four most productive eastern boundary upwelling systems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>779</offset>
        <text>We show that high levels of eddy activity tend to be associated with low levels of biological production, indicative of a suppressive effect.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>921</offset>
        <text>Simulations using eddy-resolving models of two of these upwelling systems support the suggestion that eddies suppress production, and show that the downward export of organic matter is also reduced.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1120</offset>
        <text>According to these simulations, the reduction in production and export results from an eddy-induced transport of nutrients from the nearshore environment to the open ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1293</offset>
        <text>Eddies might have a similar effect on marine productivity in other oceanic systems that are characterized by intense eddy activity, such as the Southern Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
