<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1635#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1635</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bednar_ek_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1635},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1635},
	year = 2012,
	month = {nov},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	number = {12},
	pages = {881--885},
	author = {N. Bednar{\v{s}}ek and G. A. Tarling and D. C. E. Bakker and S. Fielding and E. M. Jones and H. J. Venables and P. Ward and A. Kuzirian and B. L{\'{e}}z{\'{e}} and R. A. Feely and E. J. Murphy},
	title = {Extensive dissolution of live pteropods in the Southern Ocean},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Extensive dissolution of live pteropods in the Southern Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>62</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>62</offset>
        <text>The carbonate chemistry of the surface ocean is rapidly changing with ocean acidification, a result of human activities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>183</offset>
        <text>In the upper layers of the Southern Ocean, aragonite--a metastable form of calcium carbonate with rapid dissolution kinetics--may become undersaturated by 2050 (ref. )
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>351</offset>
        <text>.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>353</offset>
        <text>Aragonite undersaturation is likely to affect aragonite-shelled organisms, which can dominate surface water communities in polar regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>491</offset>
        <text>Here we present analyses of specimens of the pteropod Limacina helicina antarctica that were extracted live from the Southern Ocean early in 2008.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>638</offset>
        <text>We sampled from the top 200 m of the water column, where aragonite saturation levels were around 1, as upwelled deep water is mixed with surface water containing anthropogenic CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>819</offset>
        <text>Comparing the shell structure with samples from aragonite-supersaturated regions elsewhere under a scanning electron microscope, we found severe levels of shell dissolution in the undersaturated region alone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1028</offset>
        <text>According to laboratory incubations of intact samples with a range of aragonite saturation levels, eight days of incubation in aragonite saturation levels of 0.94-1.12 produces equivalent levels of dissolution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1239</offset>
        <text>As deep-water upwelling and CO2 absorption by surface waters is likely to increase as a result of human activities, we conclude that upper ocean regions where aragonite-shelled organisms are affected by dissolution are likely to expand.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
