<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep01761#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep01761</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Hetzinger_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/srep01761},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep01761},
	year = 2013,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	author = {S. Hetzinger and J. Halfar and T. Zack and J. V. Mecking and B. E. Kunz and D. E. Jacob and W. H. Adey},
	title = {Coralline algal Barium as indicator for 20th century northwestern North Atlantic surface ocean freshwater variability},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Coralline algal Barium as indicator for 20th century northwestern North Atlantic surface ocean freshwater variability
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>118</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>118</offset>
        <text>During the past decades climate and freshwater dynamics in the northwestern North Atlantic have undergone major changes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>239</offset>
        <text>Large-scale freshening episodes, related to polar freshwater pulses, have had a strong influence on ocean variability in this climatically important region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>396</offset>
        <text>However, little is known about variability before 1950, mainly due to the lack of long-term high-resolution marine proxy archives.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>527</offset>
        <text>Here we present the first multidecadal-length records of annually resolved Ba/Ca variations from Northwest Atlantic coralline algae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>660</offset>
        <text>We observe positive relationships between algal Ba/Ca ratios from two Newfoundland sites and salinity observations back to 1950.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>789</offset>
        <text>Both records capture episodical multi-year freshening events during the 20th century.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>875</offset>
        <text>Variability in algal Ba/Ca is sensitive to freshwater-induced changes in upper ocean stratification, which affect the transport of cold, Ba-enriched deep waters onto the shelf (highly stratified equals less Ba/Ca).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1090</offset>
        <text>Algal Ba/Ca ratios therefore may serve as a new resource for reconstructing past surface ocean freshwater changes.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
