<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo472#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo472</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Sekula_Wood_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo472},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo472},
	year = 2009,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {4},
	pages = {272--275},
	author = {Emily Sekula-Wood and Astrid Schnetzer and Claudia R. Benitez-Nelson and Clarissa Anderson and William M. Berelson and Mark A. Brzezinski and Justina M. Burns and David A. Caron and Ivona Cetinic and John L. Ferry and Elizabeth Fitzpatrick and Burton H. Jones and Peter E. Miller and Steve L. Morton and Rebecca A. Schaffner and David A. Siegel and Robert Thunell},
	title = {Rapid downward transport of the neurotoxin domoic acid in coastal waters},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Rapid downward transport of the neurotoxin domoic acid in coastal waters
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>73</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>73</offset>
        <text>Toxic phytoplankton blooms threaten coastlines worldwide by diminishing beach quality and adversely affecting marine ecosystems and human health.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>219</offset>
        <text>The common diatom genus Pseudo-nitzschia consists of several species known to produce the neurotoxin domoic acid.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>333</offset>
        <text>Recent studies suggest that algal blooms dominated by Pseudo-nitzschia are increasing in frequency and duration owing to changes in coastal nutrient regimes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>491</offset>
        <text>However, few studies have examined the persistence or long-term biogeochemical cycling of domoic acid in marine waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>611</offset>
        <text>Here, we measure the concentration of domoic acid in surface waters and sediment traps--up to 800 m in depth--off the coast of Southern California.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>759</offset>
        <text>We show that peaks in Pseudo-nitzschia abundance and domoic acid concentrations in surface waters coincide with peaks in diatom and toxin abundance at depth, suggesting rapid downward transport of the toxin.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>967</offset>
        <text>In some cases, the sinking particles contain over five times the United States federal limit of domoic acid.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1076</offset>
        <text>Detection of domoic acid in bottom sediments indicates that the toxin may persist long after the Pseudo-nitzschia blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1198</offset>
        <text>Our results indicate that vertical fluxes of domoic acid are a substantial source of the toxin to deep-ocean food webs, and could explain high levels of domoic acid previously observed in benthic organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
