<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1753#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate1753</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Beaugrand_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate1753},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate1753},
	year = 2012,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {3},
	pages = {263--267},
	author = {Gregory Beaugrand and Abigail McQuatters-Gollop and Martin Edwards and Eric Goberville},
	title = {Long-term responses of North Atlantic calcifying plankton to climate change},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Long-term responses of North Atlantic calcifying plankton to climate change
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>76</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>76</offset>
        <text>The global increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration is potentially threatening marine biodiversity in two ways.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>200</offset>
        <text>First, carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases accumulating in the atmosphere are causing global warming.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>308</offset>
        <text>Second, carbon dioxide is altering sea water chemistry, making the ocean more acidic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>394</offset>
        <text>Although temperature has a cardinal influence on all biological processes from the molecular to the ecosystem level, acidification might impair the process of calcification or exacerbate dissolution of calcifying organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>618</offset>
        <text>Here, we show however that North Atlantic calcifying plankton primarily responded to climate-induced changes in temperatures during the period 1960-2009, overriding the signal from the effects of ocean acidification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>835</offset>
        <text>We provide evidence that foraminifers, coccolithophores, both pteropod and non-pteropod molluscs and echinoderms exhibited an abrupt shift circa 1996 at a time of a substantial increase in temperature and that some taxa exhibited a poleward movement in agreement with expected biogeographical changes under sea temperature warming.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1167</offset>
        <text>Although acidification may become a serious threat to marine calcifying organisms, our results suggest that over the study period the primary driver of North Atlantic calcifying plankton was oceanic temperature.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
