<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate2225#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate2225</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Williamson_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate2225},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate2225},
	year = 2014,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {6},
	pages = {434--441},
	author = {Craig E. Williamson and Richard G. Zepp and Robyn M. Lucas and Sasha Madronich and Amy T. Austin and Carlos L. Ballar{\'{e}} and Mary Norval and Barbara Sulzberger and Alkiviadis F. Bais and Richard L. McKenzie and Sharon A. Robinson and Donat-P. HĂ¤der and Nigel D. Paul and Janet F. Bornman},
	title = {Solar ultraviolet radiation in a changing climate},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Solar ultraviolet radiation in a changing climate
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>50</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>50</offset>
        <text>The projected large increases in damaging ultraviolet radiation as a result of global emissions of ozone-depleting substances have been forestalled by the success of the Montreal Protocol.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>239</offset>
        <text>New challenges are now arising in relation to climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>301</offset>
        <text>We highlight the complex interactions between the drivers of climate change and those of stratospheric ozone depletion, and the positive and negative feedbacks among climate, ozone and ultraviolet radiation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>509</offset>
        <text>These will result in both risks and benefits of exposure to ultraviolet radiation for the environment and human welfare.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>630</offset>
        <text>This Review synthesizes these new insights and their relevance in a world where changes in climate as well as in stratospheric ozone are altering exposure to ultraviolet radiation with largely unknown consequences for the biosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
