<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.116#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2009.116</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Malfatti_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2009.116},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2009.116},
	year = 2009,
	month = {nov},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {3},
	pages = {427--439},
	author = {Francesca Malfatti and Ty J Samo and Farooq Azam},
	title = {High-resolution imaging of pelagic bacteria by Atomic Force Microscopy and implications for carbon cycling},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>High-resolution imaging of pelagic bacteria by Atomic Force Microscopy and implications for carbon cycling
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>107</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>107</offset>
        <text>In microbial oceanography, cell size, volume and carbon (C) content of pelagic bacteria and archaea ('bacteria') are critical parameters in addressing the in situ physiology and functions of bacteria, and their role in the food web and C cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>352</offset>
        <text>However, because of the diminutive size of most pelagic bacteria and errors caused by sample fixation and processing, an accurate measurement of the size and volume has been challenging.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>539</offset>
        <text>We used atomic force microscopy (AFM) to obtain high-resolution images of pelagic bacteria and Synechococcus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>649</offset>
        <text>We measured the length, width and height of live and formalin-fixed pelagic bacteria, and computed individual cell volumes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>773</offset>
        <text>AFM-based measurements were compared with those by epifluorescence microscopy (EFM) using 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>901</offset>
        <text>The ability to measure cell height by AFM provides methodological advantage and ecophysiological insight.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1007</offset>
        <text>For the samples examined, EFM (DAPI)-based average cell volume was in good agreement (1.1-fold) with live sample AFM.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1125</offset>
        <text>However, the agreement may be a fortuitous balance between cell shrinkage due to fixation/drying (threefold) and Z-overestimation (as EFM does not account for cell flattening caused by sample processing and assumes that height=width).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1360</offset>
        <text>The two methods showed major differences in cell volume and cell C frequency distributions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1452</offset>
        <text>This study refines the methodology for quantifying bacteria-mediated C fluxes and the role of bacteria in marine ecosystems, and suggests the potential of AFM for individual cell physiological interrogations in natural marine assemblages.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
