<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#416629a#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/416629a</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Taylor_2002,
	doi = {10.1038/416629a},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F416629a},
	year = 2002,
	month = {apr},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {416},
	number = {6881},
	pages = {629--632},
	author = {Arnold H. Taylor and J. Icarus Allen and Paul A. Clark},
	title = {Extraction of a weak climatic signal by an ecosystem},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Extraction of a weak climatic signal by an ecosystem
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>53</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>53</offset>
        <text>The complexity of ecosystems can cause subtle and chaotic responses to changes in external forcing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>153</offset>
        <text>Although ecosystems may not normally behave chaotically, sensitivity to external influences associated with nonlinearity can lead to amplification of climatic signals.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>Strong correlations between an El Nino index and rainfall and maize yield in Zimbabwe have been demonstrated; the correlation with maize yield was stronger than that with rainfall.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>502</offset>
        <text>A second example is the 100,000-year ice-age cycle, which may arise from a weak cycle in radiation through its influence on the concentration of atmospheric CO2 (ref.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>669</offset>
        <text>5).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>673</offset>
        <text>Such integration of a weak climatic signal has yet to be demonstrated in a realistic theoretical system.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>778</offset>
        <text>Here we use a particular climatic phenomenon--the observed association between plankton populations around the UK and the position of the Gulf Stream--as a probe to demonstrate how a detailed marine ecosystem model extracts a weak signal that is spread across different meteorological variables.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1074</offset>
        <text>Biological systems may therefore respond to climatic signals other than those that dominate the driving variables.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
