<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature08141#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature08141</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Davies_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/nature08141},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature08141},
	year = 2009,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {460},
	number = {7252},
	pages = {254--258},
	author = {Andrew Davies and Alan E. S. Kemp and Jennifer Pike},
	title = {Late Cretaceous seasonal ocean variability from the Arctic},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Late Cretaceous seasonal ocean variability from the Arctic
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>59</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>59</offset>
        <text>The modern Arctic Ocean is regarded as a barometer of global change and amplifier of global warming and therefore records of past Arctic change are critical for palaeoclimate reconstruction.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>250</offset>
        <text>Little is known of the state of the Arctic Ocean in the greenhouse period of the Late Cretaceous epoch (65-99 million years ago), yet records from such times may yield important clues to Arctic Ocean behaviour in near-future warmer climates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>492</offset>
        <text>Here we present a seasonally resolved Cretaceous sedimentary record from the Alpha ridge of the Arctic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>602</offset>
        <text>This palaeo-sediment trap provides new insight into the workings of the Cretaceous marine biological carbon pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>716</offset>
        <text>Seasonal primary production was dominated by diatom algae but was not related to upwelling as was previously hypothesized.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>839</offset>
        <text>Rather, production occurred within a stratified water column, involving specially adapted species in blooms resembling those of the modern North Pacific subtropical gyre, or those indicated for the Mediterranean sapropels.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1062</offset>
        <text>With increased CO2 levels and warming currently driving increased stratification in the global ocean, this style of production that is adapted to stratification may become more widespread.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1251</offset>
        <text>Our evidence for seasonal diatom production and flux testify to an ice-free summer, but thin accumulations of terrigenous sediment within the diatom ooze are consistent with the presence of intermittent sea ice in the winter, supporting a wide body of evidence for low temperatures in the Late Cretaceous Arctic Ocean, rather than recent suggestions of a 15 degreesC mean annual temperature at this time.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
