<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature01253#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature01253</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bates_2002,
	doi = {10.1038/nature01253},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature01253},
	year = 2002,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {420},
	number = {6915},
	pages = {489--493},
	author = {Nicholas R. Bates and A. Christine Pequignet and Rodney J. Johnson and Nicolas Gruber},
	title = {A short-term sink for atmospheric {CO}2 in subtropical mode water of the North Atlantic Ocean},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A short-term sink for atmospheric CO2 in subtropical mode water of the North Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>92</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>92</offset>
        <text>Large-scale features of ocean circulation, such as deep water formation in the northern North Atlantic Ocean, are known to regulate the long-term physical uptake of CO2 from the atmosphere by moving CO2-laden surface waters into the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>337</offset>
        <text>But the importance of CO2 uptake into water masses that ventilate shallower ocean depths, such as subtropical mode waters of the subtropical gyres, are poorly quantified.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>508</offset>
        <text>Here we report that, between 1988 and 2001, dissolved CO2 concentrations in subtropical mode waters of the North Atlantic have increased at a rate twice that expected from these waters keeping in equilibrium with increasing atmospheric CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>749</offset>
        <text>This accounts for an extra ~0.4-2.8 Pg C (1 Pg = 1015 g) over this period (that is, about 0.03-0.24 Pg C yr-1), equivalent to ~3-10% of the current net annual ocean uptake of CO2 (ref.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>934</offset>
        <text>3).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>938</offset>
        <text>We suggest that the lack of strong winter mixing events, to greater than 300 m in depth, in recent decades is responsible for this accumulation, which would otherwise disturb the mode water layer and liberate accumulated CO2 back to the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1187</offset>
        <text>However, future climate variability (which influences subtropical mode water formation) and changes in the North Atlantic Oscillation (leading to a return of deep winter mixing events) may reduce CO2 accumulation in subtropical mode waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1428</offset>
        <text>We therefore conclude that, although CO2 uptake by subtropical mode waters in the North Atlantic--and possibly elsewhere--does not always represent a long-term CO2 sink, the phenomenon is likely to contribute substantially to interannual variability in oceanic CO2 uptake.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
