<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep07265#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep07265</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Yuan_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/srep07265},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep07265},
	year = 2014,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	pages = {7265},
	author = {Fasong Yuan and Richard Depew and Cheryl Soltis-Muth},
	title = {Ecosystem regime change inferred from the distribution of trace metals in Lake Erie sediments},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Ecosystem regime change inferred from the distribution of trace metals in Lake Erie sediments
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>94</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>94</offset>
        <text>Many freshwater and coastal marine ecosystems across the world may have undergone an ecosystem regime change due to a combination of rising anthropogenic disturbances and regional climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>290</offset>
        <text>Such a change in aquatic ecosystems is commonly seen as shifts in algal species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>371</offset>
        <text>But considerably less detail is known about the eutrophication history in terms of changes in algal productivity, particularly for a large lake with a great deal of spatial variability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>557</offset>
        <text>Here we present an analysis of trace metals (Cu, Ni, Cd, and Pb) on a sediment core recovered from Lake Erie, off the Vermilion coast of northern Ohio, USA, to reconstruct the eutrophication history of the lake over the past 210 years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>793</offset>
        <text>Following a slow eutrophication during European settlement, Lake Erie experienced a period of accelerated eutrophication, leading to an ecosystem regime transition into a eutrophic lake state in 1950.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>994</offset>
        <text>Our results suggested that the lake's biological productivity has ever since maintained fairly high even though a significant input reduction was realized from rigorous nutrient abatements that began as early as in 1969.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1215</offset>
        <text>This work underscored the role of in-lake biogeochemical cycling in nutrient dynamics of this already eutrophic lake.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
