<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo460#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo460</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Moy_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo460},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo460},
	year = 2009,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {4},
	pages = {276--280},
	author = {Andrew D. Moy and William R. Howard and Stephen G. Bray and Thomas W. Trull},
	title = {Reduced calcification in modern Southern Ocean planktonic foraminifera},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Reduced calcification in modern Southern Ocean planktonic foraminifera
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>71</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>71</offset>
        <text>Anthropogenic carbon dioxide has been accumulating in the oceans, lowering both the concentration of carbonate ions and the pH (ref.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>204</offset>
        <text>1), resulting in the acidification of sea water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>253</offset>
        <text>Previous laboratory experiments have shown that decreased carbonate ion concentrations cause many marine calcareous organisms to show reduced calcification rates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>416</offset>
        <text>If these results are widely applicable to ocean settings, ocean acidification could lead to ecosystem shifts.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>526</offset>
        <text>Planktonic foraminifera are single-celled calcite-secreting organisms that represent between 25 and 50% of the total open-ocean marine carbonate flux and influence the transport of organic carbon to the ocean interior.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>745</offset>
        <text>Here we compare the shell weights of the modern foraminifer Globigerina bulloides collected from sediment traps in the Southern Ocean with the weights of shells preserved in the underlying Holocene-aged sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>959</offset>
        <text>We find that modern shell weights are 30-35% lower than those from the sediments, consistent with reduced calcification today induced by ocean acidification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1117</offset>
        <text>We also find a link between higher atmospheric carbon dioxide and low shell weights in a 50,000-year-long record obtained from a Southern Ocean marine sediment core.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1283</offset>
        <text>It is unclear whether reduced calcification will affect the survival of this and other species, but a decline in the abundance of foraminifera caused by acidification could affect both marine ecosystems and the oceanic uptake of atmospheric carbon dioxide.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
