<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms5299#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms5299</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Vallina_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms5299},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms5299},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	author = {S. M. Vallina and M. J. Follows and S. Dutkiewicz and J. M. Montoya and P. Cermeno and M. Loreau},
	title = {Global relationship between phytoplankton diversity and productivity in the ocean},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Global relationship between phytoplankton diversity and productivity in the ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>82</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>82</offset>
        <text>The shape of the productivity-diversity relationship (PDR) for marine phytoplankton has been suggested to be unimodal, that is, diversity peaking at intermediate levels of productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>268</offset>
        <text>However, there are few observations and there has been little attempt to understand the mechanisms that would lead to such a shape for planktonic organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>425</offset>
        <text>Here we use a marine ecosystem model together with the community assembly theory to explain the shape of the unimodal PDR we obtain at the global scale.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>578</offset>
        <text>The positive slope from low to intermediate productivity is due to grazer control with selective feeding, which leads to the predator-mediated coexistence of prey.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>742</offset>
        <text>The negative slope at high productivity is due to seasonal blooms of opportunist species that occur before they are regulated by grazers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>880</offset>
        <text>The negative side is only unveiled when the temporal scale of the observation captures the transient dynamics, which are especially relevant at highly seasonal latitudes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1051</offset>
        <text>Thus selective predation explains the positive side while transient competitive exclusion explains the negative side of the unimodal PDR curve.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1195</offset>
        <text>The phytoplankton community composition of the positive and negative sides is mostly dominated by slow-growing nutrient specialists and fast-growing nutrient opportunist species, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
