<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo307#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo307</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Algeo_2008,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo307},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo307},
	year = 2008,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {1},
	number = {10},
	pages = {709--714},
	author = {Thomas Algeo and Harry Rowe and James C. Hower and Lorenz Schwark and Achim Herrmann and Phil Heckel},
	title = {Changes in ocean denitrification during~Late Carboniferous glacial{\textendash}interglacial~cycles},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Changes in ocean denitrification during Late Carboniferous glacial-interglacial cycles
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>87</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>87</offset>
        <text>Denitrification (the process by which nitrate and nitrite are reduced to nitrogen gas) in the oxygen-minimum zones of modern oceans is an important part of the global nitrogen cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>270</offset>
        <text>Variations in rates of denitrification over Quaternary glacial-interglacial timescales may have affected global climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>391</offset>
        <text>Evidence of denitrification has been reported from some older marine systems, but it is unclear whether denitrification rates varied during pre-Quaternary glacial cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>562</offset>
        <text>Here we present ratios of organic carbon to nitrogen and nitrogen isotope data from the Upper Carboniferous black shales of the North American mid-continent.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>720</offset>
        <text>In these cyclic deposits, we find evidence of variations in the intensity of denitrification in the eastern tropical Panthalassic Ocean associated with glacially driven sea-level changes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>908</offset>
        <text>Sedimentary delta15N increases during the interval of rapid sea-level rise in each cycle, indicative of intensified denitrification, before returning to background levels as sea level stabilized during the interglacial phase.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1134</offset>
        <text>Nearly identical patterns of denitrification have been observed in the eastern tropical Pacific during the Quaternary period.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1260</offset>
        <text>We therefore conclude that ice ages have produced similar oceanographic conditions and nitrogen cycle dynamics in these regions over the past 300 million years.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
