<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.220#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.220</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Weitz_2015,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.220},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.220},
	year = 2015,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {6},
	pages = {1352--1364},
	author = {Joshua S Weitz and Charles A Stock and Steven W Wilhelm and Lydia Bourouiba and Maureen L Coleman and Alison Buchan and Michael J Follows and Jed A Fuhrman and Luis F Jover and Jay T Lennon and Mathias Middelboe and Derek L Sonderegger and Curtis A Suttle and Bradford P Taylor and T Frede Thingstad and William H Wilson and K Eric Wommack},
	title = {A multitrophic model to quantify the effects of marine viruses on microbial food webs and ecosystem processes},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A multitrophic model to quantify the effects of marine viruses on microbial food webs and ecosystem processes
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>110</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>110</offset>
        <text>Viral lysis of microbial hosts releases organic matter that can then be assimilated by nontargeted microorganisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>225</offset>
        <text>Quantitative estimates of virus-mediated recycling of carbon in marine waters, first established in the late 1990s, were originally extrapolated from marine host and virus densities, host carbon content and inferred viral lysis rates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>460</offset>
        <text>Yet, these estimates did not explicitly incorporate the cascade of complex feedbacks associated with virus-mediated lysis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>583</offset>
        <text>To evaluate the role of viruses in shaping community structure and ecosystem functioning, we extend dynamic multitrophic ecosystem models to include a virus component, specifically parameterized for processes taking place in the ocean euphotic zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>833</offset>
        <text>Crucially, we are able to solve this model analytically, facilitating evaluation of model behavior under many alternative parameterizations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>974</offset>
        <text>Analyses reveal that the addition of a virus component promotes the emergence of complex communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1076</offset>
        <text>In addition, biomass partitioning of the emergent multitrophic community is consistent with well-established empirical norms in the surface oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1224</offset>
        <text>At steady state, ecosystem fluxes can be probed to characterize the effects that viruses have when compared with putative marine surface ecosystems without viruses.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1389</offset>
        <text>The model suggests that ecosystems with viruses will have (1) increased organic matter recycling, (2) reduced transfer to higher trophic levels and (3) increased net primary productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1577</offset>
        <text>These model findings support hypotheses that viruses can have significant stimulatory effects across whole-ecosystem scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1702</offset>
        <text>We suggest that existing efforts to predict carbon and nutrient cycling without considering virus effects are likely to miss essential features of marine food webs that regulate global biogeochemical cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
