<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#35020041#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/35020041</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Loubere_2000,
	doi = {10.1038/35020041},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F35020041},
	year = 2000,
	month = {aug},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {406},
	number = {6795},
	pages = {497--500},
	author = {Paul Loubere},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Marine control of biological production in the eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>80</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>80</offset>
        <text>The eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean is the site of approximately 20-50% of new biological production in the global oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>204</offset>
        <text>This region is also responsible for the greatest efflux of CO2 from oceans to the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>298</offset>
        <text>New production, which fixes carbon in response to external inputs of nutrients as opposed to supply from local nutrient recycling, is thought to modulate the CO2 release.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>469</offset>
        <text>But what controls new production in this region is less clear.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>532</offset>
        <text>Here we present a quantitative reconstruction of biological production in the surface ocean for this region over the past 130,000 years, which shows that the equatorial Pacific Ocean exhibits higher-frequency variations than the South Equatorial Current.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>787</offset>
        <text>Comparison of these records with palaeotemperature reconstructions indicates that atmospherically driven mechanisms--such as aeolian flux of iron or wind-driven changes in upwelling rate of nutrient-rich waters--are unlikely to have influenced longer-term rates of production in this region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1079</offset>
        <text>Instead, biological production appears to be governed by changes in ocean circulation and the chemical composition of upwelled water.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
