<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate2379#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate2379</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Schl_ter_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate2379},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate2379},
	year = 2014,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {11},
	pages = {1024--1030},
	author = {Lothar SchlĂźter and Kai T. Lohbeck and Magdalena A. Gutowska and Joachim P. GrĂśger and Ulf Riebesell and Thorsten B. H. Reusch},
	title = {Adaptation of a globally important coccolithophore to ocean warming and~acidification},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Adaptation of a globally important coccolithophore to ocean warming and acidification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>Although ocean warming and acidification are recognized as two major anthropogenic perturbations of today's oceans we know very little about how marine phytoplankton may respond via evolutionary change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>289</offset>
        <text>We tested for adaptation to ocean warming in combination with ocean acidification in the globally important phytoplankton species Emiliania huxleyi.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>438</offset>
        <text>Temperature adaptation occurred independently of ocean acidification levels.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>515</offset>
        <text>Growth rates were up to 16% higher in populations adapted for one year to warming when assayed at their upper thermal tolerance limit.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>650</offset>
        <text>Particulate inorganic (PIC) and organic (POC) carbon production was restored to values under present-day ocean conditions, owing to adaptive evolution, and were 101% and 55% higher under combined warming and acidification, respectively, than in non-adapted controls.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>917</offset>
        <text>Cells also evolved to a smaller size while they recovered their initial PIC:POC ratio even under elevated CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1028</offset>
        <text>The observed changes in coccolithophore growth, calcite and biomass production, cell size and elemental composition demonstrate the importance of evolutionary processes for phytoplankton performance in a future ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
