<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.205#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2010.205</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{A_Turk_2011,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2010.205},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2010.205},
	year = 2011,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	number = {7},
	pages = {1201--1212},
	author = {Kendra A Turk and Andrew P Rees and Jonathan P Zehr and Nicole Pereira and Paul Swift and Rachel Shelley and Maeve Lohan and E Malcolm S Woodward and Jack Gilbert},
	title = {Nitrogen fixation and nitrogenase ({nifH}) expression in tropical waters of the eastern North Atlantic},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen fixation and nitrogenase (nifH) expression in tropical waters of the eastern North Atlantic
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>101</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>101</offset>
        <text>Expression of nifH in 28 surface water samples collected during fall 2007 from six stations in the vicinity of the Cape Verde Islands (north-east Atlantic) was examined using reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR)-based clone libraries and quantitative RT-PCR (RT-qPCR) analysis of seven diazotrophic phylotypes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>432</offset>
        <text>Biological nitrogen fixation (BNF) rates and nutrient concentrations were determined for these stations, which were selected based on a range in surface chlorophyll concentrations to target a gradient of primary productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>658</offset>
        <text>BNF rates greater than 6 nmolN l-1 h-1 were measured at two of the near-shore stations where high concentrations of Fe and PO43- were also measured.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>807</offset>
        <text>Six hundred and five nifH transcripts were amplified by RT-PCR, of which 76% are described by six operational taxonomic units, including Trichodesmium and the uncultivated UCYN-A, and four non-cyanobacterial diazotrophs that clustered with uncultivated Proteobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1076</offset>
        <text>Although all five cyanobacterial phylotypes quantified in RT-qPCR assays were detected at different stations in this study, UCYN-A contributed most significantly to the pool of nifH transcripts in both coastal and oligotrophic waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1311</offset>
        <text>A comparison of results from RT-PCR clone libraries and RT-qPCR indicated that a gamma-proteobacterial phylotype was preferentially amplified in clone libraries, which underscores the need to use caution interpreting clone-library-based nifH studies, especially when considering the importance of uncultivated proteobacterial diazotrophs.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
