<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.119#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.119</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bentzon_Tilia_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.119},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.119},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {2},
	pages = {273--285},
	author = {Mikkel Bentzon-Tilia and Sachia J Traving and Mustafa Mantikci and Helle Knudsen-Leerbeck and J{\o}rgen LS Hansen and Stiig Markager and Lasse Riemann},
	title = {Significant N2 fixation by heterotrophs, photoheterotrophs and heterocystous cyanobacteria in two temperate estuaries},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Significant N2 fixation by heterotrophs, photoheterotrophs and heterocystous cyanobacteria in two temperate estuaries
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>118</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>118</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen (N) fixation is fueling planktonic production in a multitude of aquatic environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>213</offset>
        <text>In meso- and poly-haline estuaries, however, the contribution of N by pelagic N2 fixation is believed to be insignificant due to the high input of N from land and the presumed absence of active N2-fixing organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>428</offset>
        <text>Here we report N2 fixation rates, nifH gene composition and nifH gene transcript abundance for key diazotrophic groups over 1 year in two contrasting, temperate, estuarine systems: Roskilde Fjord (RF) and the Great Belt (GB) strait.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>661</offset>
        <text>Annual pelagic N2 fixation rates averaged 17 and 61 mmol N m-2 per year at the two sites, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>765</offset>
        <text>In RF, N2 fixation was mainly accompanied by transcripts related to heterotrophic (for example, Pseudomonas sp.)
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>878</offset>
        <text>and photoheterotrophic bacteria (for example, unicellular diazotrophic cyanobacteria group A).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>973</offset>
        <text>In the GB, the first of two N2 fixation peaks coincided with a similar nifH-expressing community as in RF, whereas the second peak was synchronous with increased nifH expression by an array of diazotrophs, including heterotrophic organisms as well as the heterocystous cyanobacterium Anabaena.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1267</offset>
        <text>Thus, we show for the first time that significant planktonic N2 fixation takes place in mesohaline, temperate estuaries and that the importance of heterotrophic, photoheterotrophic and photosynthetic diazotrophs is clearly variable in space and time.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
