<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2008.56#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2008.56</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Zeev_2008,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2008.56},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2008.56},
	year = 2008,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {9},
	pages = {911--923},
	author = {Edo Bar Zeev and Tali Yogev and Dikla Man-Aharonovich and Nurit Kress and Barak Herut and Oded B{\'{e}}j{\`{a}} and Ilana Berman-Frank},
	title = {Seasonal dynamics of the endosymbiotic, nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium Richelia intracellularis in the eastern Mediterranean Sea},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Seasonal dynamics of the endosymbiotic, nitrogen-fixing cyanobacterium Richelia intracellularis in the eastern Mediterranean Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>129</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>129</offset>
        <text>Biological nitrogen fixation has been suggested as an important source of nitrogen for the ultra-oligotrophic waters of the Levantine Basin of the Mediterranean Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>295</offset>
        <text>In this study, we identify and characterize the spatial and temporal distribution of the N-fixing (diazotrophic) cyanobacterium Richelia intracellularis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>449</offset>
        <text>R. intracellularis is usually found as an endosymbiont within diatoms such as Rhizosolenia spp and Hemiaulus spp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>563</offset>
        <text>and is an important diazotroph in marine tropical oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>621</offset>
        <text>In this study, two stations off the Mediterranean coast of Israel were sampled monthly during 2005-2007.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>726</offset>
        <text>R. intracellularis was identified by microscopy and by reverse transcribed-PCR which confirmed a 98.8% identity with known nifH sequences of R. intracellularis from around the world.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>909</offset>
        <text>The diatom-diazotroph associations were found throughout the year peaking during autumn (October-November) at both stations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1034</offset>
        <text>Abundance of R. intracellularis ranged from 10 to 55 heterocysts l-1 and correlated positively with the dissolved Si(OH)4/(NO3+NO2) ratio in surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1191</offset>
        <text>Although the rates of nitrogen fixation were very low, averaging ~1.1 nmol N l-1 day-1 for the R. intracellularis size fraction (&gt;10 mum) from surface waters, they correlated positively with heterocyst counts during thermal stratification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1431</offset>
        <text>The lack of large-scale diatom-diazotroph blooms and the low rates of nitrogen fixation by these diazotrophs may result from the P-starved conditions affecting the Levantine basin.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
