<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.75#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.75</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Stegman_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.75},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.75},
	year = 2014,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {8},
	number = {11},
	pages = {2339--2348},
	author = {Monica R Stegman and Matthew T Cottrell and David L Kirchman},
	title = {Leucine incorporation by aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria in the Delaware estuary},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Leucine incorporation by aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic bacteria in the Delaware estuary
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Aerobic anoxygenic phototrophic (AAP) bacteria are well known to be abundant in estuaries, coastal regions and in the open ocean, but little is known about their activity in any aquatic ecosystem.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>287</offset>
        <text>To explore the activity of AAP bacteria in the Delaware estuary and coastal waters, single-cell 3H-leucine incorporation by these bacteria was examined with a new approach that combines infrared epifluorescence microscopy and microautoradiography.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>535</offset>
        <text>The approach was used on samples from the Delaware coast from August through December and on transects through the Delaware estuary in August and November 2011.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>696</offset>
        <text>The percent of active AAP bacteria was up to twofold higher than the percentage of active cells in the rest of the bacterial community in the estuary.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>847</offset>
        <text>Likewise, the silver grain area around active AAP bacteria in microautoradiography preparations was larger than the area around cells in the rest of the bacterial community, indicating higher rates of leucine consumption by AAP bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1085</offset>
        <text>The cell size of AAP bacteria was 50% bigger than the size of other bacteria, about the same difference on average as measured for activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1226</offset>
        <text>The abundance of AAP bacteria was negatively correlated and their activity positively correlated with light availability in the water column, although light did not affect 3H-leucine incorporation in light-dark experiments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1450</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that AAP bacteria are bigger and more active than other bacteria, and likely contribute more to organic carbon fluxes than indicated by their abundance.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
