<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo2300#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo2300</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{DeVries_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo2300},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo2300},
	year = 2014,
	month = {nov},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {7},
	number = {12},
	pages = {890--894},
	author = {Tim DeVries and Curtis Deutsch},
	title = {Large-scale variations in the stoichiometry of marine organic matter respiration},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Large-scale variations in the stoichiometry of marine organic matter respiration
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>81</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>81</offset>
        <text>The elemental composition of marine organic matter governs resource competition among plankton, and couples the global cycles of carbon, nutrients and oxygen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>240</offset>
        <text>Observations have revealed systematic large-scale variation in the ratios of these essential elements removed from surface waters by phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>388</offset>
        <text>However, an impact of this variability on deep ocean properties has not been detected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>475</offset>
        <text>Here we use a data-constrained ocean circulation model and observed long-term mean distributions of dissolved oxygen and the nutrient phosphate to show that there is a threefold variation across latitudes in the amount of dissolved oxygen consumed per unit of phosphate released during organic matter respiration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>789</offset>
        <text>This pattern of remineralization ratios is shown to significantly modify the extent and distribution of low-oxygen water masses in the interior ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>940</offset>
        <text>We also find that ocean biomes with distinct light and nutrient availability are characterized by different regional stoichiometries.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1074</offset>
        <text>These findings suggest that in a more stratified ocean, an increase in light exposure and decrease in nutrient concentration could raise the C:P ratio of phytoplankton, and the associated carbon storage by the ocean's biological pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
