<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.168#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.168</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Pernice_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.168},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.168},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {3},
	pages = {782--792},
	author = {Massimo C Pernice and Irene Forn and Ana Gomes and Elena Lara and Laura Alonso-S{\'{a}}ez and Jesus M Arrieta and Francisca del Carmen Garcia and Victor Hernando-Morales and Roy MacKenzie and Mireia Mestre and Eva Sintes and Eva Teira and Joaquin Valencia and Marta M Varela and Dolors Vaqu{\'{e}} and Carlos M Duarte and Josep M Gasol and Ramon Massana},
	title = {Global abundance of planktonic heterotrophic protists in the deep ocean},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Global abundance of planktonic heterotrophic protists in the deep ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>72</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>72</offset>
        <text>The dark ocean is one of the largest biomes on Earth, with critical roles in organic matter remineralization and global carbon sequestration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>214</offset>
        <text>Despite its recognized importance, little is known about some key microbial players, such as the community of heterotrophic protists (HP), which are likely the main consumers of prokaryotic biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>413</offset>
        <text>To investigate this microbial component at a global scale, we determined their abundance and biomass in deepwater column samples from the Malaspina 2010 circumnavigation using a combination of epifluorescence microscopy and flow cytometry.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>653</offset>
        <text>HP were ubiquitously found at all depths investigated down to 4000 m. HP abundances decreased with depth, from an average of 72+/-19 cells ml-1 in mesopelagic waters down to 11+/-1 cells ml-1 in bathypelagic waters, whereas their total biomass decreased from 280+/-46 to 50+/-14 pg C ml-1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>943</offset>
        <text>The parameters that better explained the variance of HP abundance were depth and prokaryote abundance, and to lesser extent oxygen concentration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1089</offset>
        <text>The generally good correlation with prokaryotic abundance suggested active grazing of HP on prokaryotes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1194</offset>
        <text>On a finer scale, the prokaryote:HP abundance ratio varied at a regional scale, and sites with the highest ratios exhibited a larger contribution of fungi molecular signal.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1367</offset>
        <text>Our study is a step forward towards determining the relationship between HP and their environment, unveiling their importance as players in the dark ocean's microbial food web.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
