<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1981#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate1981</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Six_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate1981},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate1981},
	year = 2013,
	month = {aug},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {11},
	pages = {975--978},
	author = {Katharina D. Six and Silvia Kloster and Tatiana Ilyina and Stephen D. Archer and Kai Zhang and Ernst Maier-Reimer},
	title = {Global warming amplified by reduced sulphur fluxes as a result of ocean acidification},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Global warming amplified by reduced sulphur fluxes as a result of ocean acidification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>Climate change and decreasing seawater pH (ocean acidification) have widely been considered as uncoupled consequences of the anthropogenic CO2 perturbation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>243</offset>
        <text>Recently, experiments in seawater enclosures (mesocosms) showed that concentrations of dimethylsulphide (DMS), a biogenic sulphur compound, were markedly lower in a low-pH environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>428</offset>
        <text>Marine DMS emissions are the largest natural source of atmospheric sulphur and changes in their strength have the potential to alter the Earth's radiation budget.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>591</offset>
        <text>Here we establish observational-based relationships between pH changes and DMS concentrations to estimate changes in future DMS emissions with Earth system model climate simulations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>774</offset>
        <text>Global DMS emissions decrease by about 18(+/-3)% in 2100 compared with pre-industrial times as a result of the combined effects of ocean acidification and climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>945</offset>
        <text>The reduced DMS emissions induce a significant additional radiative forcing, of which 83% is attributed to the impact of ocean acidification, tantamount to an equilibrium temperature response between 0.23 and 0.48 K.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1162</offset>
        <text>Our results indicate that ocean acidification has the potential to exacerbate anthropogenic warming through a mechanism that is not considered at present in projections of future climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
