<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo2181#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo2181</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Pichevin_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo2181},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo2181},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {7},
	number = {7},
	pages = {541--546},
	author = {L. E. Pichevin and R. S. Ganeshram and W. Geibert and R. Thunell and R. Hinton},
	title = {Silica burial enhanced by iron limitation in oceanic upwelling margins},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Silica burial enhanced by iron limitation in oceanic upwelling margins
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>71</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>71</offset>
        <text>In large swaths of the ocean, primary production by diatoms may be limited by the availability of silica, which in turn limits the biological uptake of carbon dioxide.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>239</offset>
        <text>The burial of biogenic silica in the form of opal is the main sink of marine silicon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>325</offset>
        <text>Opal burial occurs in equal parts in iron-limited open-ocean provinces and upwelling margins, especially the eastern Pacific upwelling zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>466</offset>
        <text>However, it is unclear why opal burial is so efficient in this margin.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>537</offset>
        <text>Here we measure fluxes of biogenic material, concentrations of diatom-bound iron and silicon isotope ratios using sediment traps and a sediment core from the Gulf of California upwelling margin.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>732</offset>
        <text>In the sediment trap material, we find that periods of intense upwelling are associated with transient iron limitation that results in a high export of silica relative to organic carbon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>919</offset>
        <text>A similar correlation between enhanced silica burial and iron limitation is evident in the sediment core, which spans the past 26,000 years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1060</offset>
        <text>A global compilation also indicates that hotspots of silicon burial in the ocean are all characterized by high silica to organic carbon export ratios, a diagnostic trait for diatoms growing under iron stress.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1269</offset>
        <text>We therefore propose that prevailing conditions of silica limitation in the ocean are largely caused by iron deficiency imposing an indirect constraint on oceanic carbon uptake.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
