<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.86#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2009.86</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Brown_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2009.86},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2009.86},
	year = 2009,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {12},
	pages = {1374--1386},
	author = {Mark V Brown and Gayle K Philip and John A Bunge and Matthew C Smith and Andrew Bissett and Federico M Lauro and Jed A Fuhrman and Stuart P Donachie},
	title = {Microbial community structure in the North Pacific ocean},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Microbial community structure in the North Pacific ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>57</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>57</offset>
        <text>We report a ribosomal tag pyrosequencing study of the phylogenetic diversity of Archaea, Bacteria and Eucarya over a depth profile at the Hawaii Ocean Time-Series Station, ALOHA.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>236</offset>
        <text>The V9 region of the SSU rRNA gene was amplified from samples representing the epi- (10 m), meso- (800 m) and bathy- (4400 m) pelagia.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>371</offset>
        <text>The primers used are expected to amplify representatives of ~80% of known phylogenetic diversity across all three domains.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>494</offset>
        <text>Comparisons of unique sequences revealed a remarkably low degree of overlap between communities at each depth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>605</offset>
        <text>The 444 147 sequence tags analyzed represented 62 975 unique sequences.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>677</offset>
        <text>Of these, 3707 (5.9%) occurred at two depths, and only 298 (0.5%) were observed at all three depths.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>778</offset>
        <text>At this level of phylogenetic resolution, Bacteria diversity decreased with depth but was still equivalent to that reported elsewhere for different soil types.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>938</offset>
        <text>Archaea diversity was highest in the two deeper samples.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>995</offset>
        <text>Eucarya observations and richness estimates are almost one order of magnitude higher than any previous marine microbial Eucarya richness estimates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1143</offset>
        <text>The associations of many Eucarya sequences with putative parasitic organisms may have significant impacts on our understanding of the mechanisms controlling host population density and diversity, and point to a more significant role for microbial Eucarya in carbon flux through the microbial loop.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1441</offset>
        <text>We posit that the majority of sequences detected from the deep sea that have closest matches to sequences from non-pelagic sources are indeed native to the marine environment, and are possibly responsible for key metabolic processes in global biogeochemical cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
