<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.186#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.186</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Momper_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.186},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.186},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {4},
	pages = {882--893},
	author = {Lily M Momper and Brandi Kiel Reese and Gustavo Carvalho and Patrick Lee and Eric A Webb},
	title = {A novel cohabitation between two diazotrophic cyanobacteria in the oligotrophic ocean},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A novel cohabitation between two diazotrophic cyanobacteria in the oligotrophic ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>The cyanobacterial genus Trichodesmium is biogeochemically significant because of its dual role in nitrogen and carbon fixation in the oligotrophic ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>241</offset>
        <text>Trichodesmium species form colonies that can be easily enriched from the water column and used for shipboard rate measurements to estimate their contribution to oceanic carbon and nitrogen budgets.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>439</offset>
        <text>During a July 2010 cruise near the Hawaiian Islands in the oligotrophic North Pacific Subtropical Gyre, a specific morphology of Trichodesmium puff-form colonies were examined under epifluorescent microscopy and found to harbor a colonial endobiont, morphologically identified as the heterocystous diazotrophic cyanobacterium Calothrix.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>776</offset>
        <text>Using unialgal enrichments obtained from this cruise, we show that these Calothrix-like heterocystous cyanobionts (hetDA for 'Trichodesmium-associated heterocystous diazotroph') fix nitrogen on a diurnal cycle (maximally in the middle of the light cycle with a detectable minimum in the dark).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1070</offset>
        <text>Gene sequencing of nifH from the enrichments revealed that this genus was likely not quantified using currently described quantitative PCR (qPCR) primers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1225</offset>
        <text>Guided by the sequence from the isolate, new hetDA-specific primers were designed and subsequent qPCR of environmental samples detected this diazotroph from surface water to a depth of 150 m, reaching densities up to ~9 x 103 l-1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1456</offset>
        <text>Based on phylogenetic relatedness of nifH and 16S rRNA gene sequences, it is predicted that the distribution of this cyanobiont is not limited to subtropical North Pacific but likely reaches to the South Pacific and Atlantic Oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1689</offset>
        <text>Therefore, this previously unrecognized cohabitation, if it reaches beyond the oligotrophic North Pacific, could potentially influence Trichodesmium-derived nitrogen fixation budgets in the world ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
