<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature04245#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature04245</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Huisman_2006,
	doi = {10.1038/nature04245},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature04245},
	year = 2006,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {439},
	number = {7074},
	pages = {322--325},
	author = {Jef Huisman and Nga N. Pham Thi and David M. Karl and Ben Sommeijer},
	title = {Reduced mixing generates oscillations and chaos in the oceanic deep chlorophyll maximum},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Reduced mixing generates oscillations and chaos in the oceanic deep chlorophyll maximum
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>88</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>88</offset>
        <text>Deep chlorophyll maxima (DCMs) are widespread in large parts of the world's oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>172</offset>
        <text>These deep layers of high chlorophyll concentration reflect a compromise of phytoplankton growth exposed to two opposing resource gradients: light supplied from above and nutrients supplied from below.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>374</offset>
        <text>It is often argued that DCMs are stable features.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>424</offset>
        <text>Here we show, however, that reduced vertical mixing can generate oscillations and chaos in phytoplankton biomass and species composition of DCMs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>570</offset>
        <text>These fluctuations are caused by a difference in the timescales of two processes: (1) rapid export of sinking plankton, withdrawing nutrients from the euphotic zone and (2) a slow upward flux of nutrients fuelling new phytoplankton production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>814</offset>
        <text>Climate models predict that global warming will reduce vertical mixing in the oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>900</offset>
        <text>Our model indicates that reduced mixing will generate more variability in DCMs, thereby enhancing variability in oceanic primary production and in carbon export into the ocean interior.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
