<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature09268#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature09268</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Boyce_2010,
	doi = {10.1038/nature09268},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature09268},
	year = 2010,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {466},
	number = {7306},
	pages = {591--596},
	author = {Daniel G. Boyce and Marlon R. Lewis and Boris Worm},
	title = {Global phytoplankton decline over the past century},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Global phytoplankton decline over the past century
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>51</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>51</offset>
        <text>In the oceans, ubiquitous microscopic phototrophs (phytoplankton) account for approximately half the production of organic matter on Earth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>191</offset>
        <text>Analyses of satellite-derived phytoplankton concentration (available since 1979) have suggested decadal-scale fluctuations linked to climate forcing, but the length of this record is insufficient to resolve longer-term trends.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>418</offset>
        <text>Here we combine available ocean transparency measurements and in situ chlorophyll observations to estimate the time dependence of phytoplankton biomass at local, regional and global scales since 1899.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>619</offset>
        <text>We observe declines in eight out of ten ocean regions, and estimate a global rate of decline of ~1% of the global median per year.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>750</offset>
        <text>Our analyses further reveal interannual to decadal phytoplankton fluctuations superimposed on long-term trends.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>862</offset>
        <text>These fluctuations are strongly correlated with basin-scale climate indices, whereas long-term declining trends are related to increasing sea surface temperatures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1026</offset>
        <text>We conclude that global phytoplankton concentration has declined over the past century; this decline will need to be considered in future studies of marine ecosystems, geochemical cycling, ocean circulation and fisheries.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
