<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#35075041#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/35075041</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Sa_udo_Wilhelmy_2001,
	doi = {10.1038/35075041},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F35075041},
	year = 2001,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {411},
	number = {6833},
	pages = {66--69},
	author = {Sergio A. Sa{\~{n}}udo-Wilhelmy and Adam B. Kustka and Christopher J. Gobler and David A. Hutchins and Min Yang and Kamazima Lwiza and James Burns and Douglas G. Capone and John A. Raven and Edward J. Carpenter},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Phosphorus limitation of nitrogen fixation by Trichodesmium in the central Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Marine fixation of atmospheric nitrogen is believed to be an important source of biologically useful nitrogen to ocean surface waters, stimulating productivity of phytoplankton and so influencing the global carbon cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>311</offset>
        <text>The majority of nitrogen fixation in tropical waters is carried out by the marine cyanobacterium Trichodesmium, which supplies more than half of the new nitrogen used for primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>502</offset>
        <text>Although the factors controlling marine nitrogen fixation remain poorly understood, it has been thought that nitrogen fixation is limited by iron availability in the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>675</offset>
        <text>This was inferred from the high iron requirement estimated for growth of nitrogen fixing organisms and the higher apparent densities of Trichodesmium where aeolian iron inputs are plentiful.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>866</offset>
        <text>Here we report that nitrogen fixation rates in the central Atlantic appear to be independent of both dissolved iron levels in sea water and iron content in Trichodesmium colonies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1046</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen fixation was, instead, highly correlated to the phosphorus content of Trichodesmium and was enhanced at higher irradiance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1178</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, our calculations suggest that the structural iron requirement for the growth of nitrogen-fixing organisms is much lower than previously calculated.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1339</offset>
        <text>Although iron deficiency could still potentially limit growth of nitrogen-fixing organisms in regions of low iron availability--for example, in the subtropical North Pacific Ocean--our observations suggest that marine nitrogen fixation is not solely regulated by iron supply.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
