<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.221#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.221</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{von_Dassow_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.221},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.221},
	year = 2014,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {6},
	pages = {1365--1377},
	author = {Peter von Dassow and Uwe John and Hiroyuki Ogata and Ian Probert and El Mahdi Bendif and Jessica U Kegel and St{\'{e}}phane Audic and Patrick Wincker and Corinne Da Silva and Jean-Michel Claverie and Scott Doney and David M Glover and Daniella Mella Flores and Yeritza Herrera and Magali Lescot and Marie-Jos{\'{e}} Garet-Delmas and Colomban de Vargas},
	title = {Life-cycle modification in open oceans accounts for genome variability in a cosmopolitan phytoplankton},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Life-cycle modification in open oceans accounts for genome variability in a cosmopolitan phytoplankton
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>103</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>103</offset>
        <text>Emiliania huxleyi is the most abundant calcifying plankton in modern oceans with substantial intraspecific genome variability and a biphasic life cycle involving sexual alternation between calcified 2N and flagellated 1N cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>331</offset>
        <text>We show that high genome content variability in Emiliania relates to erosion of 1N-specific genes and loss of the ability to form flagellated cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>480</offset>
        <text>Analysis of 185 E. huxleyi strains isolated from world oceans suggests that loss of flagella occurred independently in lineages inhabiting oligotrophic open oceans over short evolutionary timescales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>680</offset>
        <text>This environmentally linked physiogenomic change suggests life cycling is not advantageous in very large/diluted populations experiencing low biotic pressure and low ecological variability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>870</offset>
        <text>Gene loss did not appear to reflect pressure for genome streamlining in oligotrophic oceans as previously observed in picoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1002</offset>
        <text>Life-cycle modifications might be common in plankton and cause major functional variability to be hidden from traditional taxonomic or molecular markers.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
