<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1595#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate1595</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Kabel_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate1595},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate1595},
	year = 2012,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {12},
	pages = {871--874},
	author = {Karoline Kabel and Matthias Moros and Christian Porsche and Thomas Neumann and Florian Adolphi and Thorbj{\o}rn Joest Andersen and Herbert Siegel and Monika Gerth and Thomas Leipe and Eystein Jansen and Jaap S. Sinninghe Damst{\'{e}}},
	title = {Impact of climate change on the Baltic Sea ecosystem over the past 1,000 years},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Impact of climate change on the Baltic Sea ecosystem over the past 1,000 years
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>79</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>79</offset>
        <text>Climate change has a strong impact on ecosystem health, particularly in marginal seas such as the Baltic, for example causing the spreading of anoxic areas (oxygen-free areas, the so-called dead zones) through strong feedbacks.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>307</offset>
        <text>Marked ecosystem changes in the Baltic Sea have been recorded in the sedimentary archive, but the reasons are not fully understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>439</offset>
        <text>Here we report an integrated study of high-resolution sediment records (past 1,000 years) in combination with an ecosystem modelling approach, providing new insights into the functioning of the Baltic Sea ecosystem under natural and human-influenced climatic changes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>707</offset>
        <text>Between the Little Ice Age and the Modern Warm Period the surface water temperatures reconstructed using TEX86 palaeothermometry increased by ~2 degreesC.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>862</offset>
        <text>Simultaneously, the anoxic areas in the Baltic Sea began to expand significantly as evident from the accumulation of laminated sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1000</offset>
        <text>Ecosystem model simulations support our findings of widespread oxic areas during the Little Ice Age.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1101</offset>
        <text>Backed up by the modelling results that take into account anthropogenic-influenced nutrient load scenarios, our results provide evidence that surface temperature changes strongly influence deepwater oxygenation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1313</offset>
        <text>This highlights the risk of a continued spreading of anoxic areas during scenarios of continued climate warming in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
