<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.22#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2011.22</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bowen_2011,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2011.22},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2011.22},
	year = 2011,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	number = {9},
	pages = {1540--1548},
	author = {Jennifer L Bowen and Bess B Ward and Hilary G Morrison and John E Hobbie and Ivan Valiela and Linda A Deegan and Mitchell L Sogin},
	title = {Microbial community composition in sediments resists perturbation by nutrient enrichment},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Microbial community composition in sediments resists perturbation by nutrient enrichment
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>Functional redundancy in bacterial communities is expected to allow microbial assemblages to survive perturbation by allowing continuity in function despite compositional changes in communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>284</offset>
        <text>Recent evidence suggests, however, that microbial communities change both composition and function as a result of disturbance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>411</offset>
        <text>We present evidence for a third response: resistance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>465</offset>
        <text>We examined microbial community response to perturbation caused by nutrient enrichment in salt marsh sediments using deep pyrosequencing of 16S rRNA and functional gene microarrays targeting the nirS gene.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>671</offset>
        <text>Composition of the microbial community, as demonstrated by both genes, was unaffected by significant variations in external nutrient supply in our sampling locations, despite demonstrable and diverse nutrient-induced changes in many aspects of marsh ecology.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>930</offset>
        <text>The lack of response to external forcing demonstrates a remarkable uncoupling between microbial composition and ecosystem-level biogeochemical processes and suggests that sediment microbial communities are able to resist some forms of perturbation.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
