<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.198#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.198</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Dupont_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.198},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.198},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {5},
	pages = {1076--1092},
	author = {Chris L Dupont and John P McCrow and Ruben Valas and Ahmed Moustafa and Nathan Walworth and Ursula Goodenough and Robyn Roth and Shane L Hogle and Jing Bai and Zackary I Johnson and Elizabeth Mann and Brian Palenik and Katherine A Barbeau and J Craig Venter and Andrew E Allen},
	title = {Genomes and gene expression across light and productivity gradients in eastern subtropical Pacific microbial communities},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Genomes and gene expression across light and productivity gradients in eastern subtropical Pacific microbial communities
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>121</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>121</offset>
        <text>Transitions in community genomic features and biogeochemical processes were examined in surface and subsurface chlorophyll maximum (SCM) microbial communities across a trophic gradient from mesotrophic waters near San Diego, California to the oligotrophic Pacific.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>386</offset>
        <text>Transect end points contrasted in thermocline depth, rates of nitrogen and CO2 uptake, new production and SCM light intensity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>513</offset>
        <text>Relative to surface waters, bacterial SCM communities displayed greater genetic diversity and enrichment in putative sulfur oxidizers, multiple actinomycetes, low-light-adapted Prochlorococcus and cell-associated viruses.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>735</offset>
        <text>Metagenomic coverage was not correlated with transcriptional activity for several key taxa within Bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>843</offset>
        <text>Low-light-adapted Prochlorococcus, Synechococcus, and low abundance gamma-proteobacteria enriched in the&gt;3.0-mum size fraction contributed disproportionally to global transcription.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1025</offset>
        <text>The abundance of these groups also correlated with community functions, such as primary production or nitrate uptake.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1143</offset>
        <text>In contrast, many of the most abundant bacterioplankton, including SAR11, SAR86, SAR112 and high-light-adapted Prochlorococcus, exhibited low levels of transcriptional activity and were uncorrelated with rate processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1363</offset>
        <text>Eukaryotes such as Haptophytes and non-photosynthetic Aveolates were prevalent in surface samples while Mamielles and Pelagophytes dominated the SCM.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1513</offset>
        <text>Metatranscriptomes generated with ribosomal RNA-depleted mRNA (total mRNA) coupled to in vitro polyadenylation compared with polyA-enriched mRNA revealed a trade-off in detection eukaryotic organelle and eukaryotic nuclear origin transcripts, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1770</offset>
        <text>Gene expression profiles of SCM eukaryote populations, highly similar in sequence identity to the model pelagophyte Pelagomonas sp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1902</offset>
        <text>CCMP1756, suggest that pelagophytes are responsible for a majority of nitrate assimilation within the SCM.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
