<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep06775#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep06775</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Hioki_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/srep06775},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep06775},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	pages = {6775},
	author = {Nanako Hioki and Kenshi Kuma and Yuichirou Morita and Ryouhei Sasayama and Atsushi Ooki and Yoshiko Kondo and Hajime Obata and Jun Nishioka and Youhei Yamashita and Shigeto Nishino and Takashi Kikuchi and Michio Aoyama},
	title = {Laterally spreading iron, humic-like dissolved organic matter and nutrients in cold, dense subsurface water of the Arctic Ocean},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Laterally spreading iron, humic-like dissolved organic matter and nutrients in cold, dense subsurface water of the Arctic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>128</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>128</offset>
        <text>The location and magnitude of oceanic iron sources remain uncertain owing to a scarcity of data, particularly in the Arctic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>259</offset>
        <text>The formation of cold, dense water in the subsurface layer of the western Arctic Ocean is a key process in the lateral transport of iron, macronutrients, and other chemical constituents.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>446</offset>
        <text>Here, we present iron, humic-like fluorescent dissolved organic matter, and nutrient concentration data in waters above the continental slope and shelf and along two transects across the shelf-basin interface in the western Arctic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>684</offset>
        <text>We detected high concentrations in shelf bottom waters and in a plume that extended in the subsurface cold dense water of the halocline layer in slope and basin regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>854</offset>
        <text>At sigmatheta = 26.5, dissolved Fe, humic-like fluorescence intensity, and nutrient maxima coincided with N* minima (large negative values of N* indicate significant denitrification within shelf sediments).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1061</offset>
        <text>These results suggest that these constituents are supplied from the shelf sediments and then transported laterally to basin regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1194</offset>
        <text>Humic dissolved organic matter probably plays the most important role in the subsurface maxima and lateral transport of dissolved Fe in the halocline layer as natural Fe-binding organic ligand.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
