<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep02802#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep02802</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Roder_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/srep02802},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep02802},
	year = 2013,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	author = {C. Roder and M. L. Berumen and J. Bouwmeester and E. Papathanassiou and A. Al-Suwailem and C. R. Voolstra},
	title = {First biological measurements of deep-sea corals from the Red Sea},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>First biological measurements of deep-sea corals from the Red Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>66</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>66</offset>
        <text>It is usually assumed that metabolic constraints restrict deep-sea corals to cold-water habitats, with 'deep-sea' and 'cold-water' corals often used as synonymous.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>230</offset>
        <text>Here we report on the first measurements of biological characters of deep-sea corals from the central Red Sea, where they occur at temperatures exceeding 20degreesC in highly oligotrophic and oxygen-limited waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>445</offset>
        <text>Low respiration rates, low calcification rates, and minimized tissue cover indicate that a reduced metabolism is one of the key adaptations to prevailing environmental conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>625</offset>
        <text>We investigated four sites and encountered six species of which at least two appear to be undescribed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>728</offset>
        <text>One species is previously reported from the Red Sea but occurs in deep cold waters outside the Red Sea raising interesting questions about presumed environmental constraints for other deep-sea corals.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>929</offset>
        <text>Our findings suggest that the present understanding of deep-sea coral persistence and resilience needs to be revisited.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
