<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.172#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.172</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Forth_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.172},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.172},
	year = 2014,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {3},
	pages = {656--669},
	author = {Michael Forth and Bengt Liljebladh and Anders Stigebrandt and Per O J Hall and Alexander H Treusch},
	title = {Effects of ecological engineered oxygenation on the bacterial community structure in an anoxic fjord in western Sweden},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Effects of ecological engineered oxygenation on the bacterial community structure in an anoxic fjord in western Sweden
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>119</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>119</offset>
        <text>Oxygen-depleted bodies of water are becoming increasingly common in marine ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>206</offset>
        <text>Solutions to reverse this trend are needed and under development, for example, by the Baltic deep-water OXygenation (BOX) project.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>337</offset>
        <text>In the framework of this project, the Swedish Byfjord was chosen for a pilot study, investigating the effects of an engineered oxygenation on long-term anoxic bottom waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>511</offset>
        <text>The strong stratification of the water column of the Byfjord was broken up by pumping surface water into the deeper layers, triggering several inflows of oxygen-rich water and increasing oxygen levels in the lower water column and the benthic zone up to 110 mumol l-1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>780</offset>
        <text>We used molecular ecologic methods to study changes in bacterial community structure in response to the oxygenation in the Byfjord.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>912</offset>
        <text>Water column samples from before, during and after the oxygenation as well as from two nearby control fjords were analyzed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1036</offset>
        <text>Our results showed a strong shift in bacterial community composition when the bottom water in the Byfjord became oxic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1155</offset>
        <text>Initially dominant indicator species for oxygen minimum zones such as members of the SUP05 clade declined in abundance during the oxygenation event and nearly vanished after the oxygenation was accomplished.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1363</offset>
        <text>In contrast, aerobic species like SAR11 that initially were restricted to surface waters could later be detected deep into the water column.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1504</offset>
        <text>Overall, the bacterial community in the formerly anoxic bottom waters changed to a community structure similar to those found in oxic waters, showing that an engineered oxygenation of a large body of anoxic marine water is possible and emulates that of a natural oxygenation event.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
