<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature02631#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature02631</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Schulz_2004,
	doi = {10.1038/nature02631},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature02631},
	year = 2004,
	month = {aug},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {430},
	number = {7000},
	pages = {673--676},
	author = {K. G. Schulz and I. Zondervan and L. J. A. Gerringa and K. R. Timmermans and M. J. W. Veldhuis and U. Riebesell},
	title = {Effect of trace metal availability on coccolithophorid calcification},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Effect of trace metal availability on coccolithophorid calcification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>69</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>69</offset>
        <text>The deposition of atmospheric dust into the ocean has varied considerably over geological time.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>165</offset>
        <text>Because some of the trace metals contained in dust are essential plant nutrients which can limit phytoplankton growth in parts of the ocean, it has been suggested that variations in dust supply to the surface ocean might influence primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>416</offset>
        <text>Whereas the role of trace metal availability in photosynthetic carbon fixation has received considerable attention, its effect on biogenic calcification is virtually unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>591</offset>
        <text>The production of both particulate organic carbon and calcium carbonate (CaCO3) drives the ocean's biological carbon pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>714</offset>
        <text>The ratio of particulate organic carbon to CaCO3 export, the so-called rain ratio, is one of the factors determining CO2 sequestration in the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>868</offset>
        <text>Here we investigate the influence of the essential trace metals iron and zinc on the prominent CaCO3-producing microalga Emiliania huxleyi.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1008</offset>
        <text>We show that whereas at low iron concentrations growth and calcification are equally reduced, low zinc concentrations result in a de-coupling of the two processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1172</offset>
        <text>Despite the reduced growth rate of zinc-limited cells, CaCO3 production rates per cell remain unaffected, thus leading to highly calcified cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1318</offset>
        <text>These results suggest that changes in dust deposition can affect biogenic calcification in oceanic regions characterized by trace metal limitation, with possible consequences for CO2 partitioning between the atmosphere and the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
