<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.104#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.104</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Garcia_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.104},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.104},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {1},
	pages = {238--245},
	author = {Nathan S Garcia and Feixue Fu and Peter N Sedwick and David A Hutchins},
	title = {Iron deficiency increases growth and nitrogen-fixation rates of phosphorus-deficient marine cyanobacteria},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Iron deficiency increases growth and nitrogen-fixation rates of phosphorus-deficient marine cyanobacteria
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>106</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>106</offset>
        <text>Marine dinitrogen (N2)-fixing cyanobacteria have large impacts on global biogeochemistry as they fix carbon dioxide (CO2) and fertilize oligotrophic ocean waters with new nitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>287</offset>
        <text>Iron (Fe) and phosphorus (P) are the two most important limiting nutrients for marine biological N2 fixation, and their availabilities vary between major ocean basins and regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>467</offset>
        <text>A long-standing question concerns the ability of two globally dominant N2-fixing cyanobacteria, unicellular Crocosphaera and filamentous Trichodesmium, to maintain relatively high N2-fixation rates in these regimes where both Fe and P are typically scarce.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>724</offset>
        <text>We show that under P-deficient conditions, cultures of these two cyanobacteria are able to grow and fix N2 faster when Fe deficient than when Fe replete.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>878</offset>
        <text>In addition, growth affinities relative to P increase while minimum concentrations of P that support growth decrease at low Fe concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1021</offset>
        <text>In Crocosphaera, this effect is accompanied by a reduction in cell sizes and elemental quotas.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1116</offset>
        <text>Relatively high growth rates of these two biogeochemically critical cyanobacteria in low-P, low-Fe environments such as those that characterize much of the oligotrophic ocean challenge the common assumption that low Fe levels can have only negative effects on marine primary producers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1402</offset>
        <text>The closely interdependent influence of Fe and P on N2-fixing cyanobacteria suggests that even subtle shifts in their supply ratio in the past, present and future oceans could have large consequences for global carbon and nitrogen cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
