<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1441#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1441</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Lohbeck_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1441},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1441},
	year = 2012,
	month = {apr},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	number = {5},
	pages = {346--351},
	author = {Kai T. Lohbeck and Ulf Riebesell and Thorsten B. H. Reusch},
	title = {Adaptive evolution of a key phytoplankton species to ocean acidification},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Adaptive evolution of a key phytoplankton species to ocean acidification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>73</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>73</offset>
        <text>Ocean acidification, the drop in seawater pH associated with the ongoing enrichment of marine waters with carbon dioxide from fossil fuel burning, may seriously impair marine calcifying organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>270</offset>
        <text>Our present understanding of the sensitivity of marine life to ocean acidification is based primarily on short-term experiments, in which organisms are exposed to increased concentrations of CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>466</offset>
        <text>However, phytoplankton species with short generation times, in particular, may be able to respond to environmental alterations through adaptive evolution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>621</offset>
        <text>Here, we examine the ability of the world's single most important calcifying organism, the coccolithophore Emiliania huxleyi, to evolve in response to ocean acidification in two 500-generation selection experiments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>837</offset>
        <text>Specifically, we exposed E. huxleyi populations founded by single or multiple clones to increased concentrations of CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>958</offset>
        <text>Around 500 asexual generations later we assessed their fitness.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1022</offset>
        <text>Compared with populations kept at ambient CO2 partial pressure, those selected at increased partial pressure exhibited higher growth rates, in both the single- and multiclone experiment, when tested under ocean acidification conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1259</offset>
        <text>Calcification was partly restored: rates were lower under increased CO2 conditions in all cultures, but were up to 50% higher in adapted compared with non-adapted cultures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1432</offset>
        <text>We suggest that contemporary evolution could help to maintain the functionality of microbial processes at the base of marine food webs in the face of global change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
