<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature03948#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature03948</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Allen_2005,
	doi = {10.1038/nature03948},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature03948},
	year = 2005,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {437},
	number = {7059},
	pages = {728--732},
	author = {John T. Allen and Louise Brown and Richard Sanders and C. Mark Moore and Alexander Mustard and Sophie Fielding and Mike Lucas and Michel Rixen and Graham Savidge and Stephanie Henson and Dan Mayor},
	title = {Diatom carbon export enhanced by silicate upwelling in the northeast Atlantic},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Diatom carbon export enhanced by silicate upwelling in the northeast Atlantic
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>78</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>78</offset>
        <text>Diatoms are unicellular or chain-forming phytoplankton that use silicon (Si) in cell wall construction.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>182</offset>
        <text>Their survival during periods of apparent nutrient exhaustion enhances carbon sequestration in frontal regions of the northern North Atlantic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>325</offset>
        <text>These regions may therefore have a more important role in the 'biological pump' than they have previously been attributed, but how this is achieved is unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>485</offset>
        <text>Diatom growth depends on silicate availability, in addition to nitrate and phosphate, but northern Atlantic waters are richer in nitrate than silicate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>637</offset>
        <text>Following the spring stratification, diatoms are the first phytoplankton to bloom.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>720</offset>
        <text>Once silicate is exhausted, diatom blooms subside in a major export event.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>795</offset>
        <text>Here we show that, with nitrate still available for new production, the diatom bloom is prolonged where there is a periodic supply of new silicate: specifically, diatoms thrive by 'mining' deep-water silicate brought to the surface by an unstable ocean front.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1055</offset>
        <text>The mechanism we present here is not limited to silicate fertilization; similar mechanisms could support nitrate-, phosphate- or iron-limited frontal regions in oceans elsewhere.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
