<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo905#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo905</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Arneth_2010,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo905},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo905},
	year = 2010,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {8},
	pages = {525--532},
	author = {A. Arneth and S. P. Harrison and S. Zaehle and K. Tsigaridis and S. Menon and P. J. Bartlein and J. Feichter and A. Korhola and M. Kulmala and D. O{\textquotesingle}Donnell and G. Schurgers and S. Sorvari and T. Vesala},
	title = {Terrestrial biogeochemical feedbacks in the climate system},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Terrestrial biogeochemical feedbacks in the climate system
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>59</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>59</offset>
        <text>The terrestrial biosphere is a key regulator of atmospheric chemistry and climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>142</offset>
        <text>During past periods of climate change, vegetation cover and interactions between the terrestrial biosphere and atmosphere changed within decades.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>288</offset>
        <text>Modern observations show a similar responsiveness of terrestrial biogeochemistry to anthropogenically forced climate change and air pollution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>431</offset>
        <text>Although interactions between the carbon cycle and climate have been a central focus, other biogeochemical feedbacks could be as important in modulating future climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>607</offset>
        <text>Total positive radiative forcings resulting from feedbacks between the terrestrial biosphere and the atmosphere are estimated to reach up to 0.9 or 1.5 W m-2 K-1 towards the end of the twenty-first century, depending on the extent to which interactions with the nitrogen cycle stimulate or limit carbon sequestration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>925</offset>
        <text>This substantially reduces and potentially even eliminates the cooling effect owing to carbon dioxide fertilization of the terrestrial biota.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1067</offset>
        <text>The overall magnitude of the biogeochemical feedbacks could potentially be similar to that of feedbacks in the physical climate system, but there are large uncertainties in the magnitude of individual estimates and in accounting for synergies between these effects.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
