<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms1222#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms1222</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Helmle_2011,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms1222},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms1222},
	year = 2011,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	pages = {215},
	author = {Kevin P. Helmle and Richard E. Dodge and Peter K. Swart and Dwight K. Gledhill and C. Mark Eakin},
	title = {Growth rates of Florida corals from 1937 to 1996 and their response to climate change},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Growth rates of Florida corals from 1937 to 1996 and their response to climate change
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>Ocean acidification causes declines in calcification rates of corals because of decreasing aragonite saturation states (Omegaarag).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>218</offset>
        <text>Recent evidence also indicates that increasing sea surface temperatures may have already reduced growth and calcification rates because of the stenothermic threshold of localized coral populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>416</offset>
        <text>Density banding in coral skeletons provides a record of growth over the coral's lifespan.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>506</offset>
        <text>Here we present coral extension, bulk density and calcification master chronologies from seven subtropical corals (Montastraea faveolata) located in the Florida Keys, USA with a 60-year common period, 1937-1996.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>718</offset>
        <text>Linear trends indicate that extension increased, density decreased and calcification remained stable while the most recent decade was not significantly different than decadal averages over the preceding 50 years for extension and calcification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>963</offset>
        <text>The results suggest that growth rates in this species of subtropical coral have been tolerant to recent climatic changes up to the time of collection (1996).
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
