<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.216#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2013.216</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Ankrah_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2013.216},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2013.216},
	year = 2013,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {8},
	number = {5},
	pages = {1089--1100},
	author = {Nana Yaw D Ankrah and Amanda L May and Jesse L Middleton and Daniel R Jones and Mary K Hadden and Jessica R Gooding and Gary R LeCleir and Steven W Wilhelm and Shawn R Campagna and Alison Buchan},
	title = {Phage infection of an environmentally relevant marine bacterium alters host metabolism and lysate composition},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Phage infection of an environmentally relevant marine bacterium alters host metabolism and lysate composition
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>110</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>110</offset>
        <text>Viruses contribute to the mortality of marine microbes, consequentially altering biological species composition and system biogeochemistry.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>250</offset>
        <text>Although it is well established that host cells provide metabolic resources for virus replication, the extent to which infection reshapes host metabolism at a global level and the effect of this alteration on the cellular material released following viral lysis is less understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>532</offset>
        <text>To address this knowledge gap, the growth dynamics, metabolism and extracellular lysate of roseophage-infected Sulfitobacter sp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>661</offset>
        <text>2047 was studied using a variety of techniques, including liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS)-based metabolomics.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>797</offset>
        <text>Quantitative estimates of the total amount of carbon and nitrogen sequestered into particulate biomass indicate that phage infection redirects ~75% of nutrients into virions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>972</offset>
        <text>Intracellular concentrations for 82 metabolites were measured at seven time points over the infection cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1081</offset>
        <text>By the end of this period, 71% of the detected metabolites were significantly elevated in infected populations, and stable isotope-based flux measurements showed that these cells had elevated metabolic activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1293</offset>
        <text>In contrast to simple hypothetical models that assume that extracellular compounds increase because of lysis, a profile of metabolites from infected cultures showed that &gt;70% of the 56 quantified compounds had decreased concentrations in the lysate relative to uninfected controls, suggesting that these small, labile nutrients were being utilized by surviving cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1661</offset>
        <text>These results indicate that virus-infected cells are physiologically distinct from their uninfected counterparts, which has implications for microbial community ecology and biogeochemistry.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
