<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms6239#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms6239</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bertrand_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms6239},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms6239},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	pages = {5239},
	author = {Arnaud Bertrand and Daniel Grados and Fran{\c{c}}ois Colas and Sophie Bertrand and Xavier Capet and Alexis Chaigneau and Gary Vargas and Alexandre Mousseigne and Ronan Fablet},
	title = {Broad impacts of fine-scale dynamics on seascape structure from zooplankton to seabirds},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Broad impacts of fine-scale dynamics on seascape structure from zooplankton to seabirds
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>88</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>88</offset>
        <text>In marine ecosystems, like most natural systems, patchiness is the rule.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>161</offset>
        <text>A characteristic of pelagic ecosystems is that their 'substrate' consists of constantly moving water masses, where ocean surface turbulence creates ephemeral oases.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>326</offset>
        <text>Identifying where and when hotspots occur and how predators manage those vagaries in their preyscape is challenging because wide-ranging observations are lacking.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>489</offset>
        <text>Here we use a unique data set, gathering high-resolution and wide-range acoustic and GPS-tracking data.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>593</offset>
        <text>We show that the upper ocean dynamics at scales less than 10 km play the foremost role in shaping the seascape from zooplankton to seabirds.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>734</offset>
        <text>Short internal waves (100 m-1 km) play a major role, while submesoscale (~1-20 km) and mesoscale (~20-100 km) turbulence have a comparatively modest effect.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>891</offset>
        <text>Predicted changes in surface stratification due to global change are expected to have an impact on the number and intensity of physical structures and thus biological interactions from plankton to top predators.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
