<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1832#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1832</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Galbraith_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1832},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1832},
	year = 2013,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {6},
	number = {7},
	pages = {579--584},
	author = {Eric D. Galbraith and Markus Kienast and Eric D. Galbraith and Markus Kienast and Ana Luiza Albuquerque and Mark A. Altabet and Fabian Batista and Daniele Bianchi and Stephen E. Calvert and Sergio Contreras and Xavier Crosta and Ricardo De Pol-Holz and Nathalie Dubois and Johan Etourneau and Roger Francois and Ting-Chang Hsu and Tara Ivanochko and Samuel L. Jaccard and Shuh-Ji Kao and Thorsten Kiefer and Stephanie Kienast and Moritz F. Lehmann and Philippe Martinez and Matthew McCarthy and Anna Nele Meckler and Alan Mix and JĂźrgen MĂśbius and Tom F. Pedersen and Laetitia Pichevin and Tracy M. Quan and Rebecca S. Robinson and Evgeniya Ryabenko and Andreas Schmittner and Ralph Schneider and Aya Schneider-Mor and Masahito Shigemitsu and Dan Sinclair and Christopher Somes and Anja S. Studer and Jan-Erik Tesdal and Robert Thunell and Jin-Yu Terence Yang},
	title = {The acceleration of oceanic denitrification during deglacial warming},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The acceleration of oceanic denitrification during deglacial warming
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>69</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>69</offset>
        <text>Over much of the ocean's surface, productivity and growth are limited by a scarcity of bioavailable nitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>179</offset>
        <text>Sedimentary delta15N records spanning the last deglaciation suggest marked shifts in the nitrogen cycle during this time, but the quantification of these changes has been hindered by the complexity of nitrogen isotope cycling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>406</offset>
        <text>Here we present a database of delta15N in sediments throughout the world's oceans, including 2,329 modern seafloor samples, and 76 timeseries spanning the past 30,000 years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>580</offset>
        <text>We show that the delta15N values of modern seafloor sediments are consistent with values predicted by our knowledge of nitrogen cycling in the water column.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>737</offset>
        <text>Despite many local deglacial changes, the globally averaged delta15N values of sinking organic matter were similar during the Last Glacial Maximum and Early Holocene.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>904</offset>
        <text>Considering the global isotopic mass balance, we explain these observations with the following deglacial history of nitrogen inventory processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1050</offset>
        <text>During the Last Glacial Maximum, the nitrogen cycle was near steady state.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1125</offset>
        <text>During the deglaciation, denitrification in the pelagic water column accelerated.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1207</offset>
        <text>The flooding of continental shelves subsequently increased denitrification at the seafloor, and denitrification reached near steady-state conditions again in the Early Holocene.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1385</offset>
        <text>We use a recent parameterization of seafloor denitrification to estimate a 30-120% increase in benthic denitrification between 15,000 and 8,000 years ago.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1540</offset>
        <text>Based on the similarity of globally averaged delta15N values during the Last Glacial Maximum and Early Holocene, we infer that pelagic denitrification must have increased by a similar amount between the two steady states.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
