<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.253#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.253</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Krupke_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.253},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.253},
	year = 2014,
	month = {dec},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {7},
	pages = {1635--1647},
	author = {Andreas Krupke and Wiebke Mohr and Julie LaRoche and Bernhard M Fuchs and Rudolf I Amann and Marcel MM Kuypers},
	title = {The effect of nutrients on carbon and nitrogen fixation by the {UCYN}-A{\textendash}haptophyte symbiosis},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The effect of nutrients on carbon and nitrogen fixation by the UCYN-A-haptophyte symbiosis
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>91</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>91</offset>
        <text>Symbiotic relationships between phytoplankton and N2-fixing microorganisms play a crucial role in marine ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>208</offset>
        <text>The abundant and widespread unicellular cyanobacteria group A (UCYN-A) has recently been found to live symbiotically with a haptophyte.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>344</offset>
        <text>Here, we investigated the effect of nitrogen (N), phosphorus (P), iron (Fe) and Saharan dust additions on nitrogen (N2) fixation and primary production by the UCYN-A-haptophyte association in the subtropical eastern North Atlantic Ocean using nifH expression analysis and stable isotope incubations combined with single-cell measurements.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>683</offset>
        <text>N2 fixation by UCYN-A was stimulated by the addition of Fe and Saharan dust, although this was not reflected in the nifH expression.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>816</offset>
        <text>CO2 fixation by the haptophyte was stimulated by the addition of ammonium nitrate as well as Fe and Saharan dust.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>930</offset>
        <text>Intriguingly, the single-cell analysis using nanometer scale secondary ion mass spectrometry indicates that the increased CO2 fixation by the haptophyte in treatments without added fixed N is likely an indirect result of the positive effect of Fe and/or P on UCYN-A N2 fixation and the transfer of N2-derived N to the haptophyte.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1260</offset>
        <text>Our results reveal a direct linkage between the marine carbon and nitrogen cycles that is fuelled by the atmospheric deposition of dust.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1397</offset>
        <text>The comparison of single-cell rates suggests a tight coupling of nitrogen and carbon transfer that stays balanced even under changing nutrient regimes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1549</offset>
        <text>However, it appears that the transfer of carbon from the haptophyte to UCYN-A requires a transfer of nitrogen from UCYN-A.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1672</offset>
        <text>This tight coupling indicates an obligate symbiosis of this globally important diazotrophic association.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
