<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2015.1#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2015.1</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Nguyen_2015,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2015.1},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2015.1},
	year = 2015,
	month = {feb},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {8},
	pages = {1835--1845},
	author = {Dan Nguyen and Roxane Maranger and Vanessa Balagu{\'{e}} and Montserrat Coll-Llad{\'{o}} and Connie Lovejoy and Carlos Pedr{\'{o}}s-Ali{\'{o}}},
	title = {Winter diversity and expression of proteorhodopsin genes in a polar ocean},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Winter diversity and expression of proteorhodopsin genes in a polar ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>74</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>74</offset>
        <text>Mixotrophy is a valuable functional trait used by microbes when environmental conditions vary broadly or resources are limited.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>202</offset>
        <text>In the sunlit waters of the ocean, photoheterotrophy, a form of mixotrophy, is often mediated by proteorhodopsin (PR), a seven helices transmembrane protein binding the retinal chromophore.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>392</offset>
        <text>Altogether, they allow bacteria to capture photic energy for sensory and proton gradient formation cell functions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>507</offset>
        <text>The seasonal occurrence and diversity of the gene coding for PR in cold oligotrophic polar oceans is not known and PR expression has not yet been reported.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>663</offset>
        <text>Here we show that PR is widely distributed among bacterial taxa, and that PR expression decreased markedly during the winter months in the Arctic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>816</offset>
        <text>Gammaproteobacteria-like PR sequences were always dominant.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>876</offset>
        <text>However, within the second most common affiliation, there was a transition from Flavobacteria-like PR in early winter to Alphaproteobacteria-like PR in late winter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1041</offset>
        <text>The phylogenetic shifts followed carbon dynamics, where patterns in expression were consistent with community succession, as identified by DNA community fingerprinting.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1210</offset>
        <text>Although genes for PR were always present, the trend in decreasing transcripts from January to February suggested reduced functional utility of PR during winter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1372</offset>
        <text>Under winter darkness, sustained expression suggests that PR may continue to be useful for non-ATP forming functions, such as environmental sensing or small solute transport.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1547</offset>
        <text>The persistence of PR expression in winter among some bacterial groups may offer a competitive advantage, where its multifunctionality enhances microbial survival under harsh polar conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1740</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 20 February 2015; doi:10.1038/ismej.2015.1
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
