<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.67#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2012.67</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bengtsson_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2012.67},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2012.67},
	year = 2012,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {6},
	number = {12},
	pages = {2188--2198},
	author = {Mia M Bengtsson and Kjersti Sj{\o}tun and Anders Lanz{\'{e}}n and Lise {\O}vre{\aa}s},
	title = {Bacterial diversity in relation to secondary production and succession on surfaces of the kelp Laminaria hyperborea},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Bacterial diversity in relation to secondary production and succession on surfaces of the kelp Laminaria hyperborea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>116</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>116</offset>
        <text>Kelp forests worldwide are known as hotspots for macroscopic biodiversity and primary production, yet very little is known about the biodiversity and roles of microorganisms in these ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>311</offset>
        <text>Secondary production by heterotrophic bacteria associated to kelp is important in the food web as a link between kelp primary production and kelp forest consumers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>475</offset>
        <text>The aim of this study was to investigate the relationship between bacterial diversity and two important processes in this ecosystem; bacterial secondary production and primary succession on kelp surfaces.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>680</offset>
        <text>To address this, kelp, Laminaria hyperborea, from southwestern Norway was sampled at different geographical locations and during an annual cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>826</offset>
        <text>Pyrosequencing (454-sequencing) of amplicons of the 16S rRNA gene of bacteria was used to study bacterial diversity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>943</offset>
        <text>Incorporation of tritiated thymidine was used as a measure of bacterial production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1027</offset>
        <text>Our data show that bacterial diversity (richness and evenness) increases with the age of the kelp surface, which corresponds to the primary succession of its bacterial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1208</offset>
        <text>Higher evenness of bacterial operational taxonomical units (OTUs) is linked to higher bacterial production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1316</offset>
        <text>Owing to the dominance of a few abundant OTUs, kelp surface biofilm communities may be characterized as low-diversity habitats.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1444</offset>
        <text>This is the first detailed study of kelp-associated bacterial communities using high-throughput sequencing and it extends current knowledge on microbial community assembly and dynamics on living surfaces.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
