<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature02227#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature02227</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Pace_2004,
	doi = {10.1038/nature02227},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature02227},
	year = 2004,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {427},
	number = {6971},
	pages = {240--243},
	author = {Michael L. Pace and Jonathan J. Cole and Stephen R. Carpenter and James F. Kitchell and James R. Hodgson and Matthew C. Van de Bogert and Darren L. Bade and Emma S. Kritzberg and David Bastviken},
	title = {Whole-lake carbon-13 additions reveal terrestrial support of aquatic food webs},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Whole-lake carbon-13 additions reveal terrestrial support of aquatic food webs
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>79</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>79</offset>
        <text>Ecosystems are supported by organic carbon from two distinct sources.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>149</offset>
        <text>Endogenous carbon is produced by photosynthesis within an ecosystem by autotrophic organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>243</offset>
        <text>Exogenous carbon is produced elsewhere and transported into ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>315</offset>
        <text>Consumers may use exogenous carbon with consequent influences on population dynamics, predator-prey relationships and ecosystem processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>454</offset>
        <text>For example, exogenous inputs provide resources that may enhance consumer abundance beyond levels supported by within-system primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>599</offset>
        <text>Exogenous fluxes of organic carbon to ecosystems are often large, but this material is recalcitrant and difficult to assimilate, in contrast to endogenously produced organic matter, which is used more easily.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>808</offset>
        <text>Here we show, by the experimental manipulation of dissolved inorganic 13C in two lakes, that internal primary production is insufficient to support the food webs of these ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>991</offset>
        <text>Additions of NaH13CO3 enriched the 13C content of dissolved inorganic carbon, particulate organic carbon, zooplankton and fish.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1119</offset>
        <text>Dynamics of 13C indicate that 40-55% of particulate organic carbon and 22-50% of zooplankton carbon are derived from terrestrial sources, showing that there is significant subsidy of these ecosystems by organic carbon produced outside their boundaries.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
