<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1782#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1782</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Ziegler_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1782},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1782},
	year = 2013,
	month = {apr},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {6},
	number = {6},
	pages = {457--461},
	author = {Martin Ziegler and Paula Diz and Ian R. Hall and Rainer Zahn},
	title = {Millennial-scale changes in atmospheric {CO}2 levels linked to the Southern Ocean carbon isotope gradient and dust flux},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Millennial-scale changes in atmospheric CO2 levels linked to the Southern Ocean carbon isotope gradient and dust flux
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>118</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>118</offset>
        <text>The rise in atmospheric CO2 concentrations observed at the end of glacial periods has, at least in part, been attributed to the upwelling of carbon-rich deep water in the Southern Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>305</offset>
        <text>The magnitude of outgassing of dissolved CO2, however, is influenced by the biological fixation of upwelled inorganic carbon and its transfer back to the deep sea as organic carbon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>487</offset>
        <text>The efficiency of this biological pump is controlled by the extent of nutrient utilization, which can be stimulated by the delivery of iron by atmospheric dust particles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>658</offset>
        <text>Changes in nutrient utilization should be reflected in the delta13C gradient between intermediate and deep waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>773</offset>
        <text>Here we use the delta13C values of intermediate- and bottom-dwelling foraminifera to reconstruct the carbon isotope gradient between thermocline and abyssal water in the subantarctic zone of the South Atlantic Ocean over the past 360,000 years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1018</offset>
        <text>We find millennial-scale oscillations of the carbon isotope gradient that correspond to changes in dust flux and atmospheric CO2 concentrations as reported from Antarctic ice cores.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1200</offset>
        <text>We interpret this correlation as a relationship between the efficiency of the biological pump and fertilization by dust-borne iron.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1332</offset>
        <text>As the correlation is exponential, we suggest that the sensitivity of the biological pump to dust-borne iron fertilization may be increased when the background dust flux is low.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
