<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep08476#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep08476</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Yang_2015,
	doi = {10.1038/srep08476},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep08476},
	year = 2015,
	month = {feb},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	pages = {8476},
	author = {Caiyun Yang and Yi Li and Benjamin Zhou and Yanyan Zhou and Wei Zheng and Yun Tian and Joy D. Van Nostrand and Liyou Wu and Zhili He and Jizhong Zhou and Tianling Zheng},
	title = {Illumina sequencing-based analysis of free-living bacterial community dynamics during an Akashiwo sanguine bloom in Xiamen sea, China},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Illumina sequencing-based analysis of free-living bacterial community dynamics during an Akashiwo sanguine bloom in Xiamen sea, China
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>134</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>134</offset>
        <text>Although phytoplankton are the major source of marine dissolved organic matter (DOM), their blooms are a global problem that can greatly affect marine ecological systems, especially free-living bacteria, which are the primary DOM degraders.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>375</offset>
        <text>In this study, we analyzed free-living bacterial communities from Xiamen sea during an Akashiwo sanguine bloom using Illumina MiSeq sequencing of 16S rRNA gene amplicons.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>546</offset>
        <text>The bloom was probably stimulated by low salinity and ended after abatement of eutrophication pollution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>651</offset>
        <text>A total of 658,446 sequence reads and 11,807 OTUs were obtained in both bloom and control samples with Alpha-proteobacteria and Gamma-proteobacteria being the predominant classes detected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>840</offset>
        <text>The bloom decreased bacterial diversity, increased species evenness, and significantly changed the bacterial community structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>970</offset>
        <text>Bacterial communities within the bloom were more homogeneous than those within the control area.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1067</offset>
        <text>The bacteria stimulated by this bloom included the SAR86 and SAR116 clades and the AEGEAN-169 marine group, but a few were suppressed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1202</offset>
        <text>In addition, many bacteria known to be associated with phytoplankton were detected only in the bloom samples.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1312</offset>
        <text>This study revealed the great influence of an A. sanguinea bloom on free-living bacterial communities, and provided new insights into the relationship between bacteria and A. sanguinea in marine ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
