<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#34630#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/34630</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Dugdale_1998,
	doi = {10.1038/34630},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F34630},
	year = 1998,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {391},
	number = {6664},
	pages = {270--273},
	author = {Richard C. Dugdale and Frances P. Wilkerson},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Silicate regulation of new production in the equatorial Pacific upwelling
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>74</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>74</offset>
        <text>Surface waters of the eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean present the enigma of apparently high plant-nutrient concentrations but low phytoplankton biomass and productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>245</offset>
        <text>One explanation for this 'high-nitrate, low-chlorophyll' (HNLC) phenomenon has been that growth is limited by iron availability,.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>375</offset>
        <text>Here we use field data and a simple silicon-cycle model to investigate the HNLC condition for the upwelling zone of this ocean region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>510</offset>
        <text>Measured silicate concentrations in surface waters are low and largely invariant with time, and set the upper limit on the total possible biological utilization of dissolved inorganic carbon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>702</offset>
        <text>Chemical and biological data from surface waters indicate that diatoms--silica-shelled phytoplankton--carry out all the 'new production' (nitrate uptake).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>857</offset>
        <text>Smaller phytoplankton (picoplankton) accomplish most of the total primary production, largely fuelled by nitrogen regenerated in reduced forms as a result of grazing by zooplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1039</offset>
        <text>The model predicts values of new and export production (the production exported to below the euphotic zone) that compare well with measured values.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1187</offset>
        <text>New and export production are in balance for biogenic silica, whereas new production exceeds export for nitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1301</offset>
        <text>The HNLC condition in the upwelling zone can therefore be understood to be due to a chemostat-like regulation of nitrate uptake by upwelled silicate supply to diatoms: 'low-silicate HNLC'.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1490</offset>
        <text>These results are not inconsistent with observations of iron-fertilized diatom growth during in situ experiments in 'low-iron HNLC' waters outside this upwelling zone,, but reflect the role of different supply rates of iron and silicate in determining the nature of the HNLC condition.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
