<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo612#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo612</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Kwon_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo612},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo612},
	year = 2009,
	month = {aug},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {9},
	pages = {630--635},
	author = {Eun Young Kwon and Fran{\c{c}}ois Primeau and Jorge L. Sarmiento},
	title = {The impact of remineralization depth on the air{\textendash}sea carbon balance},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The impact of remineralization depth on the air-sea carbon balance
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>67</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>67</offset>
        <text>As particulate organic carbon rains down from the surface ocean it is respired back to carbon dioxide and released into the ocean's interior.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>209</offset>
        <text>The depth at which this sinking carbon is converted back to carbon dioxide--known as the remineralization depth--depends on the balance between particle sinking speeds and their rate of decay.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>402</offset>
        <text>A host of climate-sensitive factors can affect this balance, including temperature, oxygen concentration, stratification, community composition and the mineral content of the sinking particles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>596</offset>
        <text>Here we use a three-dimensional global ocean biogeochemistry model to show that a modest change in remineralization depth can have a substantial impact on atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>794</offset>
        <text>For example, when the depth at which 63% of sinking carbon is respired increases by 24 m globally, atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations fall by 10-27 ppm.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>954</offset>
        <text>This reduction in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration results from the redistribution of remineralized carbon from intermediate waters to bottom waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1112</offset>
        <text>As a consequence of the reduced concentration of respired carbon in upper ocean waters, atmospheric carbon dioxide is preferentially stored in newly formed North Atlantic Deep Water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1295</offset>
        <text>We suggest that atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations are highly sensitive to the potential changes in remineralization depth that may be caused by climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
