<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo639#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo639</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Dyhrman_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo639},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo639},
	year = 2009,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {10},
	pages = {696--699},
	author = {Sonya T. Dyhrman and Claudia R. Benitez-Nelson and Elizabeth D. Orchard and Sheean T. Haley and Perry J. Pellechia},
	title = {A microbial source of phosphonates in oligotrophic marine systems},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A microbial source of phosphonates in oligotrophic marine systems
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>66</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>66</offset>
        <text>Phosphonates, compounds with a carbon-phosphorus bond, are a key component of the marine dissolved organic phosphorus pool.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>190</offset>
        <text>These compounds serve as a phosphorus source for primary producers, including the nitrogen-fixing cyanobacteria Trichodesmium.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>317</offset>
        <text>Phosphonates can therefore support marine primary production, as well as climate-driven increases in marine nitrogen fixation, carbon sequestration and possibly methane production, through the breakdown of methylphosphonate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>542</offset>
        <text>Despite their importance, the source of phosphonates to the open ocean has remained uncertain.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>637</offset>
        <text>Here, we use solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy to screen for the presence of phosphonates in cultured strains of Trichodesmium erythraeum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>794</offset>
        <text>We show that phosphonates comprise an average of 10% of the cellular particulate phosphorus pool in this species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>908</offset>
        <text>We therefore suggest that these cyanobacteria produce phosphonates, and might be a significant source of these compounds in the ocean, particularly in nutrient-poor regions, where Trichodesmium blooms occur.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1116</offset>
        <text>Given that Trichodesmium also thrives in a warm, carbon-dioxide-rich environment, phosphonate production may increase in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1249</offset>
        <text>This, in turn, might select for a microbial community that can use phosphonate, and could have implications for nitrogen fixation, carbon sequestration and greenhouse-gas production.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
