<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms6992#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms6992</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Jonsson_2015,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms6992},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms6992},
	year = 2015,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {6},
	pages = {5992},
	author = {Tomas Jonsson and Malin Setzer},
	title = {A freshwater predator hit twice by the effects of warming across trophic levels},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A freshwater predator hit twice by the effects of warming across trophic levels
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>80</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>80</offset>
        <text>Many ecological responses to climate change have been documented.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>146</offset>
        <text>However, due to indirect effects, some responses can be complex and difficult to predict.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>236</offset>
        <text>For example, our understanding of effects on consumers involving responses on several trophic levels is limited.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>349</offset>
        <text>Here, combining the knowledge of trophic interactions in the EU's fourth largest lake with long-term climate and catch data, we analyse potential drivers of change in this system's apex predator.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>545</offset>
        <text>We show that warm winters correlate with later poor catches of great Arctic charr (Salvelinus umbla), and that in recent years predator-prey cycles involving this species have disappeared.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>734</offset>
        <text>The likely mechanisms are trophic mismatches directly and indirectly affecting two stages of charr, the fry and the juveniles, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>875</offset>
        <text>Our study illustrates how a long-lived consumer may be subjected to double jeopardy from the effects of warming across trophic levels, and that a food web approach can aid in disentangling the chain of mechanisms responsible.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
