<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.105#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.105</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Barnett_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.105},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.105},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {1},
	pages = {32--45},
	author = {Alexandre Barnett and Vona M{\'{e}}l{\'{e}}der and Lander Blommaert and Bernard Lepetit and Pierre Gaudin and Wim Vyverman and Koen Sabbe and Christine Dupuy and Johann Lavaud},
	title = {Growth form defines physiological photoprotective capacity in intertidal benthic diatoms},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Growth form defines physiological photoprotective capacity in intertidal benthic diatoms
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>In intertidal marine sediments, characterized by rapidly fluctuating and often extreme light conditions, primary production is frequently dominated by diatoms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>249</offset>
        <text>We performed a comparative analysis of photophysiological traits in 15 marine benthic diatom species belonging to the four major morphological growth forms (epipelon (EPL), motile epipsammon (EPM-M) and non-motile epipsammon (EPM-NM) and tychoplankton (TYCHO)) found in these sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>536</offset>
        <text>Our analyses revealed a clear relationship between growth form and photoprotective capacity, and identified fast regulatory physiological photoprotective traits (that is, non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) and the xanthophyll cycle (XC)) as key traits defining the functional light response of these diatoms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>844</offset>
        <text>EPM-NM and motile EPL showed the highest and lowest NPQ, respectively, with EPM-M showing intermediate values.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>955</offset>
        <text>Like EPL, TYCHO had low NPQ, irrespective of whether they were grown in benthic or planktonic conditions, reflecting an adaptation to a low light environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1114</offset>
        <text>Our results thus provide the first experimental evidence for the existence of a trade-off between behavioural (motility) and physiological photoprotective mechanisms (NPQ and the XC) in the four major intertidal benthic diatoms growth forms using unialgal cultures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1380</offset>
        <text>Remarkably, although motility is restricted to the raphid pennate diatom clade, raphid pennate species, which have adopted a non-motile epipsammic or a tychoplanktonic life style, display the physiological photoprotective response typical of these growth forms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1642</offset>
        <text>This observation underscores the importance of growth form and not phylogenetic relatedness as the prime determinant shaping the physiological photoprotective capacity of benthic diatoms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
