<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature08179#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature08179</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Karlsson_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/nature08179},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature08179},
	year = 2009,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {460},
	number = {7254},
	pages = {506--509},
	author = {Jan Karlsson and PĂ¤r BystrĂśm and Jenny Ask and Per Ask and Lennart Persson and Mats Jansson},
	title = {Light limitation of nutrient-poor lake ecosystems},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Light limitation of nutrient-poor lake ecosystems
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>50</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>50</offset>
        <text>Productivity denotes the rate of biomass synthesis in ecosystems and is a fundamental characteristic that frames ecosystem function and management.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>198</offset>
        <text>Limitation of productivity by nutrient availability is an established paradigm for lake ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>298</offset>
        <text>Here, we assess the relevance of this paradigm for a majority of the world's small, nutrient-poor lakes, with different concentrations of coloured organic matter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>461</offset>
        <text>By comparing small unproductive lakes along a water colour gradient, we show that coloured terrestrial organic matter controls the key process for new biomass synthesis (the benthic primary production) through its effects on light attenuation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>705</offset>
        <text>We also show that this translates into effects on production and biomass of higher trophic levels (benthic invertebrates and fish).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>837</offset>
        <text>These results are inconsistent with the idea that nutrient supply primarily controls lake productivity, and we propose that a large share of the world's unproductive lakes, within natural variations of organic carbon and nutrient input, are limited by light and not by nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1117</offset>
        <text>We anticipate that our result will have implications for understanding lake ecosystem function and responses to environmental change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1251</offset>
        <text>Catchment export of coloured organic matter is sensitive to short-term natural variability and long-term, large-scale changes, driven by climate and different anthropogenic influences.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1436</offset>
        <text>Consequently, changes in terrestrial carbon cycling will have pronounced effects on most lake ecosystems by mediating changes in light climate and productivity of lakes.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
