<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature14235#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature14235</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Wang_2015,
	doi = {10.1038/nature14235},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature14235},
	year = 2015,
	month = {feb},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {518},
	number = {7539},
	pages = {390--394},
	author = {Daiwei Wang and Tarik C. Gouhier and Bruce A. Menge and Auroop R. Ganguly},
	title = {Intensification and spatial homogenization of coastal upwelling under climate change},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Intensification and spatial homogenization of coastal upwelling under climate change
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>85</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>85</offset>
        <text>The timing and strength of wind-driven coastal upwelling along the eastern margins of major ocean basins regulate the productivity of critical fisheries and marine ecosystems by bringing deep and nutrient-rich waters to the sunlit surface, where photosynthesis can occur.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>357</offset>
        <text>How coastal upwelling regimes might change in a warming climate is therefore a question of vital importance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>466</offset>
        <text>Although enhanced land-ocean differential heating due to greenhouse warming has been proposed to intensify coastal upwelling by strengthening alongshore winds, analyses of observations and previous climate models have provided little consensus on historical and projected trends in coastal upwelling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>767</offset>
        <text>Here we show that there are strong and consistent changes in the timing, intensity and spatial heterogeneity of coastal upwelling in response to future warming in most Eastern Boundary Upwelling Systems (EBUSs).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>979</offset>
        <text>An ensemble of climate models shows that by the end of the twenty-first century the upwelling season will start earlier, end later and become more intense at high but not low latitudes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1165</offset>
        <text>This projected increase in upwelling intensity and duration at high latitudes will result in a substantial reduction of the existing latitudinal variation in coastal upwelling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1342</offset>
        <text>These patterns are consistent across three of the four EBUSs (Canary, Benguela and Humboldt, but not California).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1456</offset>
        <text>The lack of upwelling intensification and greater uncertainty associated with the California EBUS may reflect regional controls associated with the atmospheric response to climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1644</offset>
        <text>Given the strong linkages between upwelling and marine ecosystems, the projected changes in the intensity, timing and spatial structure of coastal upwelling may influence the geographical distribution of marine biodiversity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
