<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#27878#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/27878</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{le_B_Williams_1998,
	doi = {10.1038/27878},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F27878},
	year = 1998,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {394},
	number = {6688},
	pages = {55--57},
	author = {P. J. le B. Williams},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The balance of plankton respiration and photosynthesis in the open oceans
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>74</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>74</offset>
        <text>Approximately half of plant production occurs in the oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>135</offset>
        <text>As oceans are open systems, a degree of imbalance between biological production and consumption can, in principle, be sustained by the import or export of organic material.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>308</offset>
        <text>Deficits in the overall oceanic budget of organic matter must be made up by import from terrestrial, freshwater and estuarine ecosystems, mainly as river-borne material.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>478</offset>
        <text>As these inputs occur at the periphery of the ocean, their contribution is largely restricted to continental-shelf waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>601</offset>
        <text>But it has been calculated -- using discrete in vitro observations -- that in environments where net carbon fixation rates are low, respiration exceeds photosynthesis, therefore leaving the system with an organic carbon deficit.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>830</offset>
        <text>Such areas would include the central oligotrophic parts of the oceans, and it is difficult to envisage that such imbalances in these remote areas could be sustained by organic-matter import.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1021</offset>
        <text>Here I use an analysis of depth-integrated measures of production and respiration from five open-ocean regions to show that, in the upper 100 m of the water column, biological production generally exceeds consumption.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1239</offset>
        <text>This excess is sufficient to sustain estimated organic-matter export out of these surface waters, consistent with the conclusion from simple mass-balance calculations that the open oceans as a whole are not substantially out of organic carbon balance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1491</offset>
        <text>There is no evidence of the large regional imbalances observed previously.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1566</offset>
        <text>I conclude that the form of data analysis is critical.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
