<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep01493#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep01493</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Burkepile_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/srep01493},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep01493},
	year = 2013,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	author = {Deron E. Burkepile and Jacob E. Allgeier and Andrew A. Shantz and Catharine E. Pritchard and Nathan P. Lemoine and Laura H. Bhatti and Craig A. Layman},
	title = {Nutrient supply from fishes facilitates macroalgae and suppresses corals in a Caribbean coral reef ecosystem},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Nutrient supply from fishes facilitates macroalgae and suppresses corals in a Caribbean coral reef ecosystem
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>109</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>109</offset>
        <text>On coral reefs, fishes can facilitate coral growth via nutrient excretion; however, as coral abundance declines, these nutrients may help facilitate increases in macroalgae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>283</offset>
        <text>By combining surveys of reef communities with bioenergetics modeling, we showed that fish excretion supplied 25 times more nitrogen to forereefs in the Florida Keys, USA, than all other biotic and abiotic sources combined.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>506</offset>
        <text>One apparent result was a positive relationship between fish excretion and macroalgal cover on these reefs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>614</offset>
        <text>Herbivore biomass also showed a negative relationship with macroalgal cover, suggesting strong interactions of top-down and bottom-up forcing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>757</offset>
        <text>Nutrient supply by fishes also showed a negative correlation with juvenile coral density, likely mediated by competition between macroalgae and corals, suggesting that fish excretion may hinder coral recovery following large-scale coral loss.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1000</offset>
        <text>Thus, the impact of nutrient supply by fishes may be context-dependent and reinforce either coral-dominant or coral-depauperate reef communities depending on initial community states.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
