<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1422#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1422</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Murray_2012,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1422},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1422},
	year = 2012,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	number = {4},
	pages = {270--274},
	author = {Richard W. Murray and Margaret Leinen and Christopher W. Knowlton},
	title = {Links between iron input and opal deposition in the Pleistocene equatorial Pacific Ocean},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Links between iron input and opal deposition in the Pleistocene equatorial Pacific Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>Increases in overall marine primary productivity and export production in high-nutrient, low-chlorophyll regions of the ocean have, particularly during dry and dusty glacial periods, been hypothesized to be linked to the enhanced delivery of iron.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>337</offset>
        <text>In the modern ocean, iron availability limits production in high-nutrient, low-chlorophyll regions, and may be important in lower-nutrient settings as well.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>494</offset>
        <text>Here, we assess the relationship between productivity and iron in sedimentary records from the high-nutrient, low-chlorophyll region of the equatorial Pacific Ocean over the past million years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>688</offset>
        <text>We find strong links between iron input, the export and burial of biogenic silica (opal) and total export production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>806</offset>
        <text>Our data demonstrate that iron accumulation was more closely tied to the accumulation of opal than any other biogenic component, with high iron input associated with substantially increased opal sedimentation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1016</offset>
        <text>The strong links between iron and opal accumulation over the past one million years are in agreement with the modern biogeochemical behaviour of iron and silica, and the response of the diatom community to their mutual availablity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1248</offset>
        <text>Our data support earlier suggestions of a biological response to iron delivery over geologic timescales.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
