<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#35012507#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/35012507</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Elderfield_2000,
	doi = {10.1038/35012507},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F35012507},
	year = 2000,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {405},
	number = {6784},
	pages = {305--310},
	author = {H. Elderfield and R. E. M. Rickaby},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Oceanic Cd/P ratio and nutrient utilization in the glacial Southern Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>74</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>74</offset>
        <text>During glacial periods, low atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration has been associated with increased oceanic carbon uptake, particularly in the southern oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>238</offset>
        <text>The mechanism involved remains unclear.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>278</offset>
        <text>Because ocean productivity is strongly influenced by nutrient levels, palaeo-oceanographic proxies have been applied to investigate nutrient utilization in surface water across glacial transitions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>476</offset>
        <text>Here we show that present-day cadmium and phosphorus concentrations in the global oceans can be explained by a chemical fractionation during particle formation, whereby uptake of cadmium occurs in preference to uptake of phosphorus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>709</offset>
        <text>This allows the reconstruction of past surface water phosphate concentrations from the cadmium/calcium ratio of planktonic foraminifera.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>846</offset>
        <text>Results from the Last Glacial Maximum show similar phosphate utilization in the subantarctic to that of today, but much smaller utilization in the polar Southern Ocean, in a model that is consistent with the expansion of glacial sea ice and which can reconcile all proxy records of polar nutrient utilization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1156</offset>
        <text>By restricting communication between the ocean and atmosphere, sea ice expansion also provides a mechanism for reduced CO2 release by the Southern Ocean and lower glacial atmospheric CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
