<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate2349#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nclimate2349</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Behrenfeld_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/nclimate2349},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnclimate2349},
	year = 2014,
	month = {sep},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {10},
	pages = {880--887},
	author = {Michael J. Behrenfeld},
	title = {Climate-mediated dance of the plankton},
	journal = {Nature Climate Change}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Climate-mediated dance of the plankton
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>39</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>39</offset>
        <text>Climate change will unquestionably influence global ocean plankton because it directly impacts both the availability of growth-limiting resources and the ecological processes governing biomass distributions and annual cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>265</offset>
        <text>Forecasting this change demands recognition of the vital, yet counterintuitive, attributes of the plankton world.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>379</offset>
        <text>The biomass of photosynthetic phytoplankton, for example, is not proportional to their division rate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>481</offset>
        <text>Perhaps more surprising, physical processes (such as deep vertical mixing) can actually trigger an accumulation in phytoplankton while simultaneously decreasing their division rates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>664</offset>
        <text>These behaviours emerge because changes in phytoplankton division rates are paralleled by proportional changes in grazing, viral attack and other loss rates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>822</offset>
        <text>Here I discuss this trophic dance between predators and prey, how it dictates when phytoplankton biomass remains constant or achieves massive blooms, and how it can determine even the sign of change in ocean ecosystems under a warming climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
