<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.49#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.49</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Moisander_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.49},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.49},
	year = 2014,
	month = {apr},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {8},
	number = {10},
	pages = {1962--1973},
	author = {Pia H Moisander and Tracy Serros and Ryan W Paerl and Roxanne A Beinart and Jonathan P Zehr},
	title = {Gammaproteobacterial diazotrophs and {nifH} gene expression in surface waters of the South Pacific Ocean},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Gammaproteobacterial diazotrophs and nifH gene expression in surface waters of the South Pacific Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>103</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>103</offset>
        <text>In addition to the cyanobacterial N2-fixers (diazotrophs), there is a high nifH gene diversity of non-cyanobacterial groups present in marine environments, yet quantitative information about these groups is scarce.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>318</offset>
        <text>N2 fixation potential (nifH gene expression), diversity and distributions of the uncultivated diazotroph phylotype gamma-24774A11, a putative gammaproteobacterium, were investigated in the western South Pacific Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>536</offset>
        <text>gamma-24774A11 gene copies correlated positively with diazotrophic cyanobacteria, temperature, dissolved organic carbon and ambient O2 saturation, and negatively with depth, chlorophyll a and nutrients, suggesting that carbon supply, access to light or inhibitory effects of DIN may control gamma-24774A11 abundances.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>854</offset>
        <text>Maximum nifH gene-copy abundance was 2 x 104 l-1, two orders of magnitude less than that for diazotrophic cyanobacteria, while the median gamma-24774A11 abundance, 8 x 102 l-1, was greater than that for the UCYN-A cyanobacteria, suggesting a more homogeneous distribution in surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1145</offset>
        <text>The abundance of nifH transcripts by gamma-24774A11 was greater during the night than during the day, and the transcripts generally ranged from 0-7%, but were up to 26% of all nifH transcripts at each station.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1355</offset>
        <text>The ubiquitous presence and low variability of gamma-24774A11 abundances across tropical and subtropical oceans, combined with the consistent nifH expression reported in this study, suggest that gamma-24774A11 could be one of the most important heterotrophic (or photoheterotrophic) diazotrophs and may need to be considered in future N budget estimates and models.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
