<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature12670#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature12670</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Delgado_Baquerizo_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/nature12670},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature12670},
	year = 2013,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {502},
	number = {7473},
	pages = {672--676},
	author = {Manuel Delgado-Baquerizo and Fernando T. Maestre and Antonio Gallardo and Matthew A. Bowker and Matthew D. Wallenstein and Jose Luis Quero and Victoria Ochoa and Beatriz Gozalo and Miguel Garc{\'{\i}}a-G{\'{o}}mez and Santiago Soliveres and Pablo Garc{\'{\i}}a-Palacios and Miguel Berdugo and Enrique Valencia and Cristina Escolar and Tulio Arredondo and Claudia Barraza-Zepeda and Donaldo Bran and Jos{\'{e}} Antonio Carreira and Mohamed Chaieb and Abel A. Concei{\c{c}}{\~{a}}o and Mchich Derak and David J. Eldridge and Adri{\'{a}}n Escudero and Carlos I. Espinosa and Juan Gait{\'{a}}n and M. Gabriel Gatica and Susana G{\'{o}}mez-Gonz{\'{a}}lez and Elizabeth Guzman and Julio R. Guti{\'{e}}rrez and Adriana Florentino and Estela Hepper and Rosa M. Hern{\'{a}}ndez and Elisabeth Huber-Sannwald and Mohammad Jankju and Jushan Liu and Rebecca L. Mau and Maria Miriti and Jorge Monerris and Kamal Naseri and Zouhaier Noumi and Vicente Polo and An{\'{\i}}bal Prina and Eduardo Pucheta and Elizabeth Ram{\'{\i}}rez and David A. Ram{\'{\i}}rez-Collantes and Roberto Rom{\~{a}}o and Matthew Tighe and Duilio Torres and Cristian Torres-D{\'{\i}}az and Eugene D. Ungar and James Val and Wanyoike Wamiti and Deli Wang and Eli Zaady},
	title = {Decoupling of soil nutrient cycles as a function of aridity in global drylands},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Decoupling of soil nutrient cycles as a function of aridity in global drylands
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>79</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>79</offset>
        <text>The biogeochemical cycles of carbon (C), nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) are interlinked by primary production, respiration and decomposition in terrestrial ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>248</offset>
        <text>It has been suggested that the C, N and P cycles could become uncoupled under rapid climate change because of the different degrees of control exerted on the supply of these elements by biological and geochemical processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>472</offset>
        <text>Climatic controls on biogeochemical cycles are particularly relevant in arid, semi-arid and dry sub-humid ecosystems (drylands) because their biological activity is mainly driven by water availability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>674</offset>
        <text>The increase in aridity predicted for the twenty-first century in many drylands worldwide may therefore threaten the balance between these cycles, differentially affecting the availability of essential nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>887</offset>
        <text>Here we evaluate how aridity affects the balance between C, N and P in soils collected from 224 dryland sites from all continents except Antarctica.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1036</offset>
        <text>We find a negative effect of aridity on the concentration of soil organic C and total N, but a positive effect on the concentration of inorganic P. Aridity is negatively related to plant cover, which may favour the dominance of physical processes such as rock weathering, a major source of P to ecosystems, over biological processes that provide more C and N, such as litter decomposition.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1426</offset>
        <text>Our findings suggest that any predicted increase in aridity with climate change will probably reduce the concentrations of N and C in global drylands, but increase that of P.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1601</offset>
        <text>These changes would uncouple the C, N and P cycles in drylands and could negatively affect the provision of key services provided by these ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
