<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms4950#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms4950</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Watanabe_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms4950},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms4950},
	year = 2014,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	author = {Eiji Watanabe and Jonaotaro Onodera and Naomi Harada and Makio C. Honda and Katsunori Kimoto and Takashi Kikuchi and Shigeto Nishino and Kohei Matsuno and Atsushi Yamaguchi and Akio Ishida and Michio J. Kishi},
	title = {Enhanced role of eddies in the Arctic marine biological pump},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Enhanced role of eddies in the Arctic marine biological pump
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>61</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>61</offset>
        <text>The future conditions of Arctic sea ice and marine ecosystems are of interest not only to climate scientists, but also to economic and governmental bodies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>217</offset>
        <text>However, the lack of widespread, year-long biogeochemical observations remains an obstacle to understanding the complicated variability of the Arctic marine biological pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>391</offset>
        <text>Here we show an early winter maximum of sinking biogenic flux in the western Arctic Ocean and illustrate the importance of shelf-break eddies to biological pumping from wide shelves to adjacent deep basins using a combination of year-long mooring observations and three-dimensional numerical modelling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>694</offset>
        <text>The sinking flux trapped in the present study included considerable fresh organic material with soft tissues and was an order of magnitude larger than previous estimates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>865</offset>
        <text>We predict that further reductions in sea ice will promote the entry of Pacific-origin biological species into the Arctic basin and accelerate biogeochemical cycles connecting the Arctic and subarctic oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
