<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1297#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo1297</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Cai_2011,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo1297},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo1297},
	year = 2011,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	number = {11},
	pages = {766--770},
	author = {Wei-Jun Cai and Xinping Hu and Wei-Jen Huang and Michael C. Murrell and John C. Lehrter and Steven E. Lohrenz and Wen-Chen Chou and Weidong Zhai and James T. Hollibaugh and Yongchen Wang and Pingsan Zhao and Xianghui Guo and Kjell Gundersen and Minhan Dai and Gwo-Ching Gong},
	title = {Acidification of subsurface coastal waters enhanced by eutrophication},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Acidification of subsurface coastal waters enhanced by eutrophication
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>70</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>70</offset>
        <text>Human inputs of nutrients to coastal waters can lead to the excessive production of algae, a process known as eutrophication.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>196</offset>
        <text>Microbial consumption of this organic matter lowers oxygen levels in the water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>276</offset>
        <text>In addition, the carbon dioxide produced during microbial respiration increases acidity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>365</offset>
        <text>The dissolution of atmospheric carbon dioxide in ocean waters also raises acidity, a process known as ocean acidification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>488</offset>
        <text>Here, we assess the combined impact of eutrophication and ocean acidification on acidity in the coastal ocean, using data collected in the northern Gulf of Mexico and the East China Sea--two regions heavily influenced by nutrient-laden rivers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>732</offset>
        <text>We show that eutrophication in these waters is associated with the development of hypoxia and the acidification of subsurface waters, as expected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>879</offset>
        <text>Model simulations, using data collected from the northern Gulf of Mexico, however, suggest that the drop in pH since pre-industrial times is greater than that expected from eutrophication and ocean acidification alone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1098</offset>
        <text>We attribute the additional drop in pH--of 0.05 units--to a reduction in the ability of these carbon dioxide-rich waters to buffer changes in pH. We suggest that eutrophication could increase the susceptibility of coastal waters to ocean acidification.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
