<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms3705#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms3705</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Beman_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms3705},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms3705},
	year = 2013,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {4},
	author = {J. Michael Beman and Molly T. Carolan},
	title = {Deoxygenation alters bacterial diversity and community composition in the ocean's largest oxygen minimum zone},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Deoxygenation alters bacterial diversity and community composition in the ocean's largest oxygen minimum zone
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>110</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>110</offset>
        <text>Oceanic oxygen minimum zones (OMZs) have a central role in biogeochemical cycles and are expanding as a consequence of climate change, yet how deoxygenation will affect the microbial communities that control these cycles is unclear.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>343</offset>
        <text>Here we sample across dissolved oxygen gradients in the oceans' largest OMZ and show that bacterial richness displays a unimodal pattern with decreasing dissolved oxygen, reaching maximum values on the edge of the OMZ and decreasing within it.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>587</offset>
        <text>Rare groups on the OMZ margin are abundant at lower dissolved oxygen concentrations, including sulphur-cycling Chromatiales, for which 16S rRNA was amplified from extracted RNA.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>765</offset>
        <text>Microbial species distribution models accurately replicate community patterns based on multivariate environmental data, demonstrate likely changes in distributions and diversity in the eastern tropical North Pacific Ocean, and highlight the sensitivity of key bacterial groups to deoxygenation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1060</offset>
        <text>Through these mechanisms, OMZ expansion may alter microbial composition, competition, diversity and function, all of which have implications for biogeochemical cycling in OMZs.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
