<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo416#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo416</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Goodwin_2009,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo416},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo416},
	year = 2009,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {2},
	number = {2},
	pages = {145--150},
	author = {Philip Goodwin and Richard G. Williams and Andy Ridgwell and Michael J. Follows},
	title = {Climate sensitivity to the carbon cycle modulated by past and future changes in ocean chemistry},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Climate sensitivity to the carbon cycle modulated by past and future changes in ocean chemistry
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>96</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>96</offset>
        <text>The carbon cycle has a central role in climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>151</offset>
        <text>For example, during glacial-interglacial cycles, atmospheric carbon dioxide has altered radiative forcing and amplified temperature changes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>292</offset>
        <text>However, it is unclear how sensitive the climate system has been to changes in carbon cycling in previous geological periods, or how this sensitivity may evolve in the future, following massive anthropogenic emissions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>511</offset>
        <text>Here we develop an analytical relationship that links the variation of radiative forcing from changes in carbon dioxide concentrations with changes in air-sea carbon cycling on a millennial timescale.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>712</offset>
        <text>We find that this relationship is affected by the ocean storage of carbon and its chemical partitioning in sea water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>830</offset>
        <text>Our analysis reveals that the radiative forcing of climate is more sensitive to carbon perturbations now than it has been over much of the preceding 400 million years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>998</offset>
        <text>This high sensitivity is likely to persist into the future as the oceans become more acidic and the bulk of the fossil-fuels inventory is transferred to the ocean and atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
