<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature03370#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature03370</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Michael_Beman_2005,
	doi = {10.1038/nature03370},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature03370},
	year = 2005,
	month = {mar},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {434},
	number = {7030},
	pages = {211--214},
	author = {J. Michael Beman and Kevin R. Arrigo and Pamela A. Matson},
	title = {Agricultural runoff fuels large phytoplankton blooms in vulnerable areas of the ocean},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Agricultural runoff fuels large phytoplankton blooms in vulnerable areas of the ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>Biological productivity in most of the world's oceans is controlled by the supply of nutrients to surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>200</offset>
        <text>The relative balance between supply and removal of nutrients--including nitrogen, iron and phosphorus--determines which nutrient limits phytoplankton growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>358</offset>
        <text>Although nitrogen limits productivity in much of the ocean, large portions of the tropics and subtropics are defined by extreme nitrogen depletion.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>506</offset>
        <text>In these regions, microbial denitrification removes biologically available forms of nitrogen from the water column, producing substantial deficits relative to other nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>682</offset>
        <text>Here we demonstrate that nitrogen-deficient areas of the tropical and subtropical oceans are acutely vulnerable to nitrogen pollution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>817</offset>
        <text>Despite naturally high nutrient concentrations and productivity, nitrogen-rich agricultural runoff fuels large (54-577 km2) phytoplankton blooms in the Gulf of California.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>989</offset>
        <text>Runoff exerts a strong and consistent influence on biological processes, in 80% of cases stimulating blooms within days of fertilization and irrigation of agricultural fields.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1165</offset>
        <text>We project that by the year 2050, 27-59% of all nitrogen fertilizer will be applied in developing regions located upstream of nitrogen-deficient marine ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1329</offset>
        <text>Our findings highlight the present and future vulnerability of these ecosystems to agricultural runoff.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
