<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature13376#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature13376</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Poulter_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/nature13376},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature13376},
	year = 2014,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {509},
	number = {7502},
	pages = {600--603},
	author = {Benjamin Poulter and David Frank and Philippe Ciais and Ranga B. Myneni and Niels Andela and Jian Bi and Gregoire Broquet and Josep G. Canadell and Frederic Chevallier and Yi Y. Liu and Steven W. Running and Stephen Sitch and Guido R. van der Werf},
	title = {Contribution of semi-arid ecosystems to interannual variability of the global carbon cycle},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Contribution of semi-arid ecosystems to interannual variability of the global carbon cycle
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>91</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>91</offset>
        <text>The land and ocean act as a sink for fossil-fuel emissions, thereby slowing the rise of atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>222</offset>
        <text>Although the uptake of carbon by oceanic and terrestrial processes has kept pace with accelerating carbon dioxide emissions until now, atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations exhibit a large variability on interannual timescales, considered to be driven primarily by terrestrial ecosystem processes dominated by tropical rainforests.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>558</offset>
        <text>We use a terrestrial biogeochemical model, atmospheric carbon dioxide inversion and global carbon budget accounting methods to investigate the evolution of the terrestrial carbon sink over the past 30 years, with a focus on the underlying mechanisms responsible for the exceptionally large land carbon sink reported in 2011 (ref.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>888</offset>
        <text>2).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>892</offset>
        <text>Here we show that our three terrestrial carbon sink estimates are in good agreement and support the finding of a 2011 record land carbon sink.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1035</offset>
        <text>Surprisingly, we find that the global carbon sink anomaly was driven by growth of semi-arid vegetation in the Southern Hemisphere, with almost 60 per cent of carbon uptake attributed to Australian ecosystems, where prevalent La Nina conditions caused up to six consecutive seasons of increased precipitation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1344</offset>
        <text>In addition, since 1981, a six per cent expansion of vegetation cover over Australia was associated with a fourfold increase in the sensitivity of continental net carbon uptake to precipitation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1539</offset>
        <text>Our findings suggest that the higher turnover rates of carbon pools in semi-arid biomes are an increasingly important driver of global carbon cycle inter-annual variability and that tropical rainforests may become less relevant drivers in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1790</offset>
        <text>More research is needed to identify to what extent the carbon stocks accumulated during wet years are vulnerable to rapid decomposition or loss through fire in subsequent years.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
