<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.114#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2013.114</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Freimann_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2013.114},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2013.114},
	year = 2013,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {7},
	number = {12},
	pages = {2361--2373},
	author = {Remo Freimann and Helmut BĂźrgmann and Stuart EG Findlay and Christopher T Robinson},
	title = {Bacterial structures and ecosystem functions in glaciated floodplains: contemporary states and potential future shifts},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Bacterial structures and ecosystem functions in glaciated floodplains: contemporary states and potential future shifts
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>119</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>119</offset>
        <text>Glaciated alpine floodplains are responding quickly to climate change through shrinking ice masses.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>219</offset>
        <text>Given the expected future changes in their physicochemical environment, we anticipated variable shifts in structure and ecosystem functioning of hyporheic microbial communities in proglacial alpine streams, depending on present community characteristics and landscape structures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>499</offset>
        <text>We examined microbial structure and functioning during different hydrologic periods in glacial (kryal) streams and, as contrasting systems, groundwater-fed (krenal) streams.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>673</offset>
        <text>Three catchments were chosen to cover an array of landscape features, including interconnected lakes, differences in local geology and degree of deglaciation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>832</offset>
        <text>Community structure was assessed by automated ribosomal intergenic spacer analysis and microbial function by potential enzyme activities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>970</offset>
        <text>We found each catchment to contain a distinct bacterial community structure and different degrees of separation in structure and functioning that were linked to the physicochemical properties of the waters within each catchment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1199</offset>
        <text>Bacterial communities showed high functional plasticity, although achieved by different strategies in each system.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1314</offset>
        <text>Typical kryal communities showed a strong linkage of structure and function that indicated a major prevalence of specialists, whereas krenal sediments were dominated by generalists.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1496</offset>
        <text>With the rapid retreat of glaciers and therefore altered ecohydrological characteristics, lotic microbial structure and functioning are likely to change substantially in proglacial floodplains in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1704</offset>
        <text>The trajectory of these changes will vary depending on contemporary bacterial community characteristics and landscape structures that ultimately determine the sustainability of ecosystem functioning.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
