<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#23680#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/23680</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Hutchins_1999,
	doi = {10.1038/23680},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2F23680},
	year = 1999,
	month = {aug},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {400},
	number = {6747},
	pages = {858--861},
	author = {David A. Hutchins and Amy E. Witter and Alison Butler and George W. Luther},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Competition among marine phytoplankton for different chelated iron species
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>75</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>75</offset>
        <text>Dissolved-iron availability plays a critical role in controlling phytoplankton growth in the oceans,.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>177</offset>
        <text>The dissolved iron is overwhelmingly (~99%) bound to organic ligands with a very high affinity for iron, but the origin, chemical identity and biological availability of this organically complexed Fe is largely unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>397</offset>
        <text>The release into sea water of complexes that strongly chelate iron could result from the inducible iron-uptake systems of prokaryotes (siderophore complexes) or by processes such as zooplankton-mediated degradation and release of intracellular material (porphyrin complexes).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>673</offset>
        <text>Here we compare the uptake of siderophore- and porphyrin-complexed 55Fe by phytoplankton, using both cultured organisms and natural assemblages.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>818</offset>
        <text>Eukaryotic phytoplankton efficiently assimilate porphyrin-complexed iron, but this iron source is relatively unavailable to prokaryotic picoplankton (cyanobacteria).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>984</offset>
        <text>In contrast, iron bound to a variety of siderophores is relatively more available to cyanobacteria than to eukaryotes, suggesting that the two plankton groups exhibit fundamentally different iron-uptake strategies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1199</offset>
        <text>Prokaryotes utilize iron complexed to either endogenous or exogenous siderophores, whereas eukaryotes may rely on a ferrireductase system, that preferentially accesses iron chelated by tetradentate porphyrins, rather than by hexadentate siderophores.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1450</offset>
        <text>Competition between prokaryotes and eukaryotes for organically-bound iron may therefore depend on the chemical nature of available iron complexes, with consequences for ecological niche separation, plankton community size-structure and carbon export in low-iron waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
