<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms6350#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms6350</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Bogard_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms6350},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms6350},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	pages = {5350},
	author = {Matthew J Bogard and Paul A del Giorgio and Lennie Boutet and Maria Carolina Garcia Chaves and Yves T Prairie and Anthony Merante and Alison M Derry},
	title = {Oxic water column methanogenesis as a major component of aquatic {CH}4 fluxes},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Oxic water column methanogenesis as a major component of aquatic CH4 fluxes
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>76</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>76</offset>
        <text>Methanogenesis has traditionally been assumed to occur only in anoxic environments, yet there is mounting, albeit indirect, evidence of methane (CH4) production in oxic marine and freshwaters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>269</offset>
        <text>Here we present the first direct, ecosystem-scale demonstration of methanogenesis in oxic lake waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>372</offset>
        <text>This methanogenesis appears to be driven by acetoclastic production, and is closely linked to algal dynamics.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>482</offset>
        <text>We show that oxic water methanogenesis is a significant component of the overall CH4 budget in a small, shallow lake, and provide evidence that this pathway may be the main CH4 source in large, deep lakes and open oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>704</offset>
        <text>Our results challenge the current global understanding of aquatic CH4 dynamics, and suggest a hitherto unestablished link between pelagic CH4 emissions and surface-water primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>894</offset>
        <text>This link may be particularly sensitive to widespread and increasing human influences on aquatic ecosystem primary productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
