<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature00851#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature00851</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Sunda_2002,
	doi = {10.1038/nature00851},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature00851},
	year = 2002,
	month = {jul},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {418},
	number = {6895},
	pages = {317--320},
	author = {W. Sunda and D. J. Kieber and R. P. Kiene and S. Huntsman},
	title = {An antioxidant function for {DMSP} and {DMS} in marine algae},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>An antioxidant function for DMSP and DMS in marine algae
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>57</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>57</offset>
        <text>The algal osmolyte dimethylsulphoniopropionate (DMSP) and its enzymatic cleavage product dimethylsulphide (DMS) contribute significantly to the global sulphur cycle, yet their physiological functions are uncertain.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>272</offset>
        <text>Here we report results that, together with those in the literature, show that DMSP and its breakdown products (DMS, acrylate, dimethylsulphoxide, and methane sulphinic acid) readily scavenge hydroxyl radicals and other reactive oxygen species, and thus may serve as an antioxidant system, regulated in part by enzymatic cleavage of DMSP.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>610</offset>
        <text>In support of this hypothesis, we found that oxidative stressors, solar ultraviolet radiation, CO2 limitation, Fe limitation, high Cu2+ (ref.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>752</offset>
        <text>9) and H2O2 substantially increased cellular DMSP and/or its lysis to DMS in marine algal cultures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>852</offset>
        <text>Our results indicate direct links between such stressors and the dynamics of DMSP and DMS in marine phytoplankton, which probably influence the production of DMS and its release to the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1049</offset>
        <text>As oxidation of DMS to sulphuric acid in the atmosphere provides a major source of sulphate aerosols and cloud condensation nuclei, oxidative stressors--including solar radiation and Fe limitation--may be involved in complex ocean-atmosphere feedback loops that influence global climate and hydrological cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
