<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep01037#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/srep01037</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Segura_2013,
	doi = {10.1038/srep01037},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fsrep01037},
	year = 2013,
	month = {jan},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	author = {A. M. Segura and C. Kruk and D. Calliari and F. Garc{\'{\i}}a-Rodriguez and D. Conde and C. E. Widdicombe and H. Fort},
	title = {Competition Drives Clumpy Species Coexistence in Estuarine Phytoplankton},
	journal = {Scientific Reports}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Competition Drives Clumpy Species Coexistence in Estuarine Phytoplankton
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>73</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>73</offset>
        <text>Understanding the mechanisms that maintain biodiversity is a fundamental problem in ecology.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>166</offset>
        <text>Competition is thought to reduce diversity, but hundreds of microbial aquatic primary producers species coexist and compete for a few essential resources (e.g., nutrients and light).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>349</offset>
        <text>Here, we show that resource competition is a plausible mechanism for explaining clumpy distribution on individual species volume (a proxy for the niche) of estuarine phytoplankton communities ranging from North America to South America and Europe, supporting the Emergent Neutrality hypothesis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>644</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, such a clumpy distribution was also observed throughout the Holocene in diatoms from a sediment core.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>759</offset>
        <text>A Lotka-Volterra competition model predicted position in the niche axis and functional affiliation of dominant species within and among clumps.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>903</offset>
        <text>Results support the coexistence of functionally equivalent species in ecosystems and indicate that resource competition may be a key process to shape the size structure of estuarine phytoplankton, which in turn drives ecosystem functioning.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
