<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms5143#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms5143</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Tang_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms5143},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms5143},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	author = {Tiantian Tang and Kim Kisslinger and Cindy Lee},
	title = {Silicate deposition during decomposition of cyanobacteria may promote export of picophytoplankton to the deep ocean},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Silicate deposition during decomposition of cyanobacteria may promote export of picophytoplankton to the deep ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>116</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>116</offset>
        <text>Marine particles transport organic matter through the water column to the sediment where the organic matter can be buried.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>239</offset>
        <text>This pathway is one of the few natural removal mechanisms of CO2 from the atmosphere over geological time.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>346</offset>
        <text>Picophytoplankton, major primary producers in the ocean, have until recently been thought unimportant regarding particle transport.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>478</offset>
        <text>Here we provide evidence that silicate is deposited on extracellular polymeric substance (EPS) associated with decomposing picophytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>620</offset>
        <text>We also find that Si is enriched in a previously unexplored group of marine particles (called micro-blebs) from the deep-water column.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>755</offset>
        <text>The surprising similarity in morphology and composition between EPS-Si and micro-blebs suggests that EPS-Si may be a precursor of micro-blebs observed in the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>925</offset>
        <text>This previously unexplored source of silicon may be important to silicon cycling and may further enhance export of picophytoplankton to the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
