<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.39#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.39</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Eckert_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.39},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.39},
	year = 2014,
	month = {apr},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {8},
	number = {9},
	pages = {1808--1819},
	author = {Ester M Eckert and Jakob Pernthaler},
	title = {Bacterial epibionts of Daphnia: a potential route for the transfer of dissolved organic carbon in freshwater food webs},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Bacterial epibionts of Daphnia: a potential route for the transfer of dissolved organic carbon in freshwater food webs
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>119</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>119</offset>
        <text>The identification of interacting species and elucidation of their mode of interaction may be crucial to understand ecosystem-level processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>262</offset>
        <text>We analysed the activity and identity of bacterial epibionts in cultures of Daphnia galeata and of natural daphnid populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>390</offset>
        <text>Epibiotic bacteria incorporated considerable amounts of dissolved organic carbon (DOC), as estimated via uptake of tritiated leucine: three times more tracer was consumed by microbes on a single Daphnia than in 1 ml of lake water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>621</offset>
        <text>However, there was virtually no incorporation if daphnids were anaesthetised, suggesting that their filtration activity was essential for this process.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>773</offset>
        <text>Microbial DOC uptake could predominantly be assigned to microbes that were located on the filter combs of daphnids, where the passage of water would ensure a continuously high DOC supply.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>961</offset>
        <text>Most of these bacteria were Betaproteobacteria from the genus Limnohabitans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1038</offset>
        <text>Specifically, we identified a monophyletic cluster harbouring Limnohabitans planktonicus that encompassed sequence types from D. galeata cultures, from the gut of Daphnia magna and from daphnids of Lake Zurich.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1249</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that the epibiotic growth of bacteria related to Limnohabitans on Daphnia spp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1348</offset>
        <text>may be a widespread and rather common phenomenon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1398</offset>
        <text>Moreover, most of the observed DOC flux to Daphnia in fact does not seem to be associated with the crustacean biomass itself but with its epibiotic microflora.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1558</offset>
        <text>The unexplored physical association of daphnids with heterotrophic bacteria may have considerable implications for our understanding of carbon transfer in freshwater food webs, that is, a trophic 'shortcut' between microbial DOC uptake and predation by fish.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
