<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo755#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo755</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Ridgwell_2010,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo755},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo755},
	year = 2010,
	month = {feb},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {3},
	pages = {196--200},
	author = {Andy Ridgwell and Daniela N. Schmidt},
	title = {Past constraints on the vulnerability of marine calcifiers to massive carbon dioxide release},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Past constraints on the vulnerability of marine calcifiers to massive carbon dioxide release
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>93</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>93</offset>
        <text>Increasing concentrations of carbon dioxide in sea water are driving a progressive acidification of the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>204</offset>
        <text>Although the associated changes in the carbonate chemistry of surface and deep waters may adversely affect marine calcifying organisms, current experiments do not always produce consistent results for a given species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>422</offset>
        <text>Ocean sediments record past biological responses to transient greenhouse warming and ocean acidification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>528</offset>
        <text>During the Palaeocene-Eocene thermal maximum, for example, the biodiversity of benthic calcifying organisms decreased markedly, whereas extinctions of surface dwellers were very limited.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>715</offset>
        <text>Here we use the Earth system model GENIE-1 to simulate and compare directly past and present environmental changes in the marine realm.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>851</offset>
        <text>In our simulation of future ocean conditions, we find an undersaturation with respect to carbonate in the deep ocean that exceeds that experienced during the Palaeocene-Eocene thermal maximum and could endanger calcifying organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1084</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, our simulations show higher rates of environmental change at the surface for the future than the Palaeocene-Eocene thermal maximum, which could potentially challenge the ability of plankton to adapt.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
