<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.197#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ismej.2014.197</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Monier_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ismej.2014.197},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fismej.2014.197},
	year = 2014,
	month = {oct},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {9},
	number = {4},
	pages = {990--1002},
	author = {Adam Monier and J{\'{e}}r{\^{o}}me Comte and Marcel Babin and Alexandre Forest and Atsushi Matsuoka and Connie Lovejoy},
	title = {Oceanographic structure drives the assembly processes of microbial eukaryotic communities},
	journal = {The {ISME} Journal}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Oceanographic structure drives the assembly processes of microbial eukaryotic communities
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Arctic Ocean microbial eukaryote phytoplankton form subsurface chlorophyll maximum (SCM), where much of the annual summer production occurs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>231</offset>
        <text>This SCM is particularly persistent in the Western Arctic Ocean, which is strongly salinity stratified.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>335</offset>
        <text>The recent loss of multiyear sea ice and increased particulate-rich river discharge in the Arctic Ocean results in a greater volume of fresher water that may displace nutrient-rich saltier waters to deeper depths and decrease light penetration in areas affected by river discharge.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>617</offset>
        <text>Here, we surveyed microbial eukaryotic assemblages in the surface waters, and within and below the SCM.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>721</offset>
        <text>In most samples, we detected the pronounced SCM that usually occurs at the interface of the upper mixed layer and Pacific Summer Water (PSW).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>863</offset>
        <text>Poorly developed SCM was seen under two conditions, one above PSW and associated with a downwelling eddy, and the second in a region influenced by the Mackenzie River plume.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1037</offset>
        <text>Four phylogenetically distinct communities were identified: surface, pronounced SCM, weak SCM and a deeper community just below the SCM.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1174</offset>
        <text>Distance-decay relationships and phylogenetic structure suggested distinct ecological processes operating within these communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1306</offset>
        <text>In the pronounced SCM, picophytoplanktons were prevalent and community assembly was attributed to water mass history.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1424</offset>
        <text>In contrast, environmental filtering impacted the composition of the weak SCM communities, where heterotrophic Picozoa were more numerous.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1563</offset>
        <text>These results imply that displacement of Pacific waters to greater depth and increased terrigenous input may act as a control on SCM development and result in lower net summer primary production with a more heterotroph dominated eukaryotic microbial community.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
