<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo856#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo856</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Mills_2010,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo856},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo856},
	year = 2010,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {3},
	number = {6},
	pages = {412--416},
	author = {Matthew M. Mills and Kevin R. Arrigo},
	title = {Magnitude of oceanic nitrogen fixation influenced by the nutrient uptake ratio of phytoplankton},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Magnitude of oceanic nitrogen fixation influenced by the nutrient uptake ratio of phytoplankton
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>96</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>96</offset>
        <text>The elemental stoichiometry of sea water and particulate organic matter is remarkably similar.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>191</offset>
        <text>This observation led Redfield to hypothesize that the oceanic ratio of nitrate to phosphate is controlled by the remineralization of phytoplankton biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>347</offset>
        <text>The Redfield ratio is used universally to quantitatively link the marine nitrogen and phosphorus cycles in numerous biogeochemical applications.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>492</offset>
        <text>Yet, empirical and theoretical studies show that the ratio of nitrogen to phosphorus in phytoplankton varies greatly with taxa and growth conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>642</offset>
        <text>Here we present a dynamic five-box ecosystem model showing that non-Redfield utilization of dissolved nitrogen and phosphorus by non-nitrogen-fixing phytoplankton controls the magnitude and distribution of nitrogen fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>867</offset>
        <text>In our simulations, systems dominated by rapidly growing phytoplankton with low nitrogen to phosphorus uptake ratios reduce the phosphorus available for nitrogen fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1039</offset>
        <text>In contrast, in systems dominated by slow-growing phytoplankton with high nitrogen to phosphorus uptake ratios nitrogen deficits are enhanced, and nitrogen fixation is promoted.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1217</offset>
        <text>We show that estimates of nitrogen fixation are up to fourfold too high when non-Redfield uptake stoichiometries are ignored.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1343</offset>
        <text>We suggest that the relative abundance of fast- and slow-growing phytoplankton controls the amount of new nitrogen added to the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
