<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms4929#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms4929</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Hawkings_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms4929},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms4929},
	year = 2014,
	month = {may},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	author = {Jon R. Hawkings and Jemma L. Wadham and Martyn Tranter and Rob Raiswell and Liane G. Benning and Peter J. Statham and Andrew Tedstone and Peter Nienow and Katherine Lee and Jon Telling},
	title = {Ice sheets as a significant source of highly reactive nanoparticulate iron to the oceans},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Ice sheets as a significant source of highly reactive nanoparticulate iron to the oceans
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>The Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheets cover ~\n10% of global land surface, but are rarely considered as active components of the global iron cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>238</offset>
        <text>The ocean waters around both ice sheets harbour highly productive coastal ecosystems, many of which are iron limited.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>356</offset>
        <text>Measurements of iron concentrations in subglacial runoff from a large Greenland Ice Sheet catchment reveal the potential for globally significant export of labile iron fractions to the near-coastal euphotic zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>569</offset>
        <text>We estimate that the flux of bioavailable iron associated with glacial runoff is 0.40-2.54 Tg per year in Greenland and 0.06-0.17 Tg per year in Antarctica.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>726</offset>
        <text>Iron fluxes are dominated by a highly reactive and potentially bioavailable nanoparticulate suspended sediment fraction, similar to that identified in Antarctic icebergs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>897</offset>
        <text>Estimates of labile iron fluxes in meltwater are comparable with aeolian dust fluxes to the oceans surrounding Greenland and Antarctica, and are similarly expected to increase in a warming climate with enhanced melting.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
