<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms5077#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ncomms5077</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Tanentzap_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ncomms5077},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fncomms5077},
	year = 2014,
	month = {jun},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {5},
	author = {Andrew J. Tanentzap and Erik J. Szkokan-Emilson and Brian W. Kielstra and Michael T. Arts and Norman D. Yan and John M. Gunn},
	title = {Forests fuel fish growth in freshwater deltas},
	journal = {Nature Communications}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Forests fuel fish growth in freshwater deltas
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>46</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>46</offset>
        <text>Aquatic ecosystems are fuelled by biogeochemical inputs from surrounding lands and within-lake primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>161</offset>
        <text>Disturbances that change these inputs may affect how aquatic ecosystems function and deliver services vital to humans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>280</offset>
        <text>Here we test, using a forest cover gradient across eight separate catchments, whether disturbances that remove terrestrial biomass lower organic matter inputs into freshwater lakes, thereby reducing food web productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>502</offset>
        <text>We focus on deltas formed at the stream-lake interface where terrestrial-derived particulate material is deposited.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>618</offset>
        <text>We find that organic matter export increases from more forested catchments, enhancing bacterial biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>723</offset>
        <text>This transfers energy upwards through communities of heavier zooplankton, leading to a fourfold increase in weights of planktivorous young-of-the-year fish.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>880</offset>
        <text>At least 34% of fish biomass is supported by terrestrial primary production, increasing to 66% with greater forest cover.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1002</offset>
        <text>Habitat tracers confirm fish were closely associated with individual catchments, demonstrating that watershed protection and restoration increase biomass in critical life-stages of fish.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
