<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature14145#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/nature14145</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Mart_nez_Bot__2015,
	doi = {10.1038/nature14145},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fnature14145},
	year = 2015,
	month = {feb},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {518},
	number = {7537},
	pages = {49--54},
	author = {M. A. Mart{\'{\i}}nez-Bot{\'{\i}} and G. L. Foster and T. B. Chalk and E. J. Rohling and P. F. Sexton and D. J. Lunt and R. D. Pancost and M. P. S. Badger and D. N. Schmidt},
	title = {Plio-Pleistocene climate sensitivity evaluated using high-resolution {CO}2 records},
	journal = {Nature}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Plio-Pleistocene climate sensitivity evaluated using high-resolution CO2 records
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>81</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>81</offset>
        <text>Theory and climate modelling suggest that the sensitivity of Earth's climate to changes in radiative forcing could depend on the background climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>230</offset>
        <text>However, palaeoclimate data have thus far been insufficient to provide a conclusive test of this prediction.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>339</offset>
        <text>Here we present atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2) reconstructions based on multi-site boron-isotope records from the late Pliocene epoch (3.3 to 2.3 million years ago).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>507</offset>
        <text>We find that Earth's climate sensitivity to CO2-based radiative forcing (Earth system sensitivity) was half as strong during the warm Pliocene as during the cold late Pleistocene epoch (0.8 to 0.01 million years ago).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>725</offset>
        <text>We attribute this difference to the radiative impacts of continental ice-volume changes (the ice-albedo feedback) during the late Pleistocene, because equilibrium climate sensitivity is identical for the two intervals when we account for such impacts using sea-level reconstructions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1009</offset>
        <text>We conclude that, on a global scale, no unexpected climate feedbacks operated during the warm Pliocene, and that predictions of equilibrium climate sensitivity (excluding long-term ice-albedo feedbacks) for our Pliocene-like future (with CO2 levels up to maximum Pliocene levels of 450 parts per million) are well described by the currently accepted range of an increase of 1.5 K to 4.5 K per doubling of CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
