<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs2</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo2303#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs2/10.1038/ngeo2303</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Teng_2014,
	doi = {10.1038/ngeo2303},
	url = {https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fngeo2303},
	year = 2014,
	month = {nov},
	publisher = {Springer Nature},
	volume = {7},
	number = {12},
	pages = {895--898},
	author = {Yi-Cheng Teng and Fran{\c{c}}ois W. Primeau and J. Keith Moore and Michael W. Lomas and Adam C. Martiny},
	title = {Global-scale variations of the ratios of carbon to phosphorus in exported marine organic matter},
	journal = {Nature Geoscience}
}</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Global-scale variations of the ratios of carbon to phosphorus in exported marine organic matter
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>96</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>96</offset>
        <text>The ratio of carbon (C) to phosphorus (P) in marine phytoplankton is thought to be constant throughout the worlds' oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>219</offset>
        <text>Known as the Redfield ratio, this relationship describes the links between carbon and phosphorus cycling and marine ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>347</offset>
        <text>However, variations in the stoichiometry of phytoplankton have recently been identified, in particular strong latitudinal variability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>482</offset>
        <text>Here we assess the impact of this variability in the C:P ratio of biomass on the C:P ratio of organic matter that is exported to the deep ocean using a biogeochemical inverse-model based on a data-constrained ocean circulation model and a global database of dissolved inorganic carbon and phosphate measurements.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>795</offset>
        <text>We identify global patterns of variability in the C:P ratios of exported organic matter, with higher values in the nutrient-depleted subtropical gyres, where organic matter export is relatively low, and lower ratios in nutrient-rich upwelling zones and high-latitude regions, where organic matter export is high.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1108</offset>
        <text>This suggests that total carbon export is relatively constant throughout the oceans, in agreement with recent estimates of carbon fluxes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1246</offset>
        <text>We conclude that the latitudinal patterns of C:P in exported organic matter are consistent with the large-scale stoichiometric variations in phytoplankton C:P.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1406</offset>
        <text>We suggest that a future expansion of nutrient-depleted waters could result in a shift to more efficient C export that compensates for the expected decline in productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
