<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.60#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Malmstrom_2010, title={Temporal dynamics of Prochlorococcus ecotypes in the Atlantic and Pacific oceans}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.60}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.60}, number={10}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Malmstrom, Rex R and Coe, Allison and Kettler, Gregory C and Martiny, Adam C and Frias-Lopez, Jorge and Zinser, Erik R and Chisholm, Sallie W}, year={2010}, month={Oct}, pages={1252–1264}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.60</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Temporal dynamics of Prochlorococcus ecotypes in the Atlantic and Pacific oceans
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>81</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>81</offset>
        <text>To better understand the temporal and spatial dynamics of Prochlorococcus populations, and how these populations co-vary with the physical environment, we followed monthly changes in the abundance of five ecotypes--two high-light adapted and three low-light adapted--over a 5-year period in coordination with the Bermuda Atlantic Time Series (BATS) and Hawaii Ocean Time-series (HOT) programs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>475</offset>
        <text>Ecotype abundance displayed weak seasonal fluctuations at HOT and strong seasonal fluctuations at BATS.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>579</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, stable 'layered' depth distributions, where different Prochlorococcus ecotypes reached maximum abundance at different depths, were maintained consistently for 5 years at HOT.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>767</offset>
        <text>Layered distributions were also observed at BATS, although winter deep mixing events disrupted these patterns each year and produced large variations in ecotype abundance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>939</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, the layered ecotype distributions were regularly reestablished each year after deep mixing subsided at BATS.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1063</offset>
        <text>In addition, Prochlorococcus ecotypes each responded differently to the strong seasonal changes in light, temperature and mixing at BATS, resulting in a reproducible annual succession of ecotype blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1266</offset>
        <text>Patterns of ecotype abundance, in combination with physiological assays of cultured isolates, confirmed that the low-light adapted eNATL could be distinguished from other low-light adapted ecotypes based on its ability to withstand temporary exposure to high-intensity light, a characteristic stress of the surface mixed layer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1594</offset>
        <text>Finally, total Prochlorococcus and Synechococcus dynamics were compared with similar time series data collected a decade earlier at each location.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1741</offset>
        <text>The two data sets were remarkably similar--testimony to the resilience of these complex dynamic systems on decadal time scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
