<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.24#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Yamasaki_2009, title={Extracellular polysaccharide-protein complexes of a harmful alga mediate the allelopathic control it exerts within the phytoplankton community}, volume={3}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2009.24}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2009.24}, number={7}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Yamasaki, Yasuhiro and Shikata, Tomoyuki and Nukata, Atsushi and Ichiki, Satoko and Nagasoe, Sou and Matsubara, Tadashi and Shimasaki, Yohei and Nakao, Miki and Yamaguchi, Kenichi and Oshima, Yuji and et al.}, year={2009}, month={Mar}, pages={808–817}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2009.24</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Extracellular polysaccharide-protein complexes of a harmful alga mediate the allelopathic control it exerts within the phytoplankton community
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>143</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>143</offset>
        <text>The goal of this study was to examine the significance of allelopathy by the raphidophyte Heterosigma akashiwo in a multispecies phytoplankton community in the field.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>310</offset>
        <text>Towards this aim, we sought allelochemicals of H. akashiwo, which had allelopathic effect both in laboratory experiments and in the field.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>449</offset>
        <text>As an initial step, we showed that the allelopathic effects of H. akashiwo filtrate were both species-specific and dependent upon the cell density of the target species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>619</offset>
        <text>Secondly, we found for the first time that extracellular, high-molecular weight allelochemicals [that is, polysaccharide-protein complexes (APPCs)] were produced by a marine phytoplankton species, H. akashiwo.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>829</offset>
        <text>Thirdly, we indicated that the purified APPCs selectively inhibited the growth of the diatom Skeletonema costatum that is a major competitor of H. akashiwo, and thereby tended to promote the formation of monospecific H. akashiwo blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1066</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, we demonstrated that the inhibitory effect of APPCs on the growth of the diatoms was determined by binding to the cell surface of the target species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1229</offset>
        <text>Finally, we succeeded in the detection of APPCs in the field samples at concentrations exceeding their experimentally determined action threshold during the H. akashiwo bloom.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1405</offset>
        <text>Strategies for ecosystem control, including mitigation of harmful algal blooms (HABs), should take into account that red-tide organisms like H. akashiwo are already part of complex webs involving inter-specific allelopathic inhibition and ecosystem control during their dense blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
