<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.94#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Wagner_D_bler_2010, title={The complete genome sequence of the algal symbiont Dinoroseobacter shibae: a hitchhiker’s guide to life in the sea}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2009.94}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2009.94}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Wagner-Döbler, Irene and Ballhausen, Britta and Berger, Martine and Brinkhoff, Thorsten and Buchholz, Ina and Bunk, Boyke and Cypionka, Heribert and Daniel, Rolf and Drepper, Thomas and Gerdts, Gunnar and et al.}, year={2010}, month={Jan}, pages={61–77}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2009.94</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The complete genome sequence of the algal symbiont Dinoroseobacter shibae: a hitchhiker's guide to life in the sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>115</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>115</offset>
        <text>Dinoroseobacter shibae DFL12T, a member of the globally important marine Roseobacter clade, comprises symbionts of cosmopolitan marine microalgae, including toxic dinoflagellates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>295</offset>
        <text>Its annotated 4 417 868 bp genome sequence revealed a possible advantage of this symbiosis for the algal host.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>406</offset>
        <text>D. shibae DFL12T is able to synthesize the vitamins B1 and B12 for which its host is auxotrophic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>504</offset>
        <text>Two pathways for the de novo synthesis of vitamin B12 are present, one requiring oxygen and the other an oxygen-independent pathway.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>637</offset>
        <text>The de novo synthesis of vitamin B12 was confirmed to be functional, and D. shibae DFL12T was shown to provide the growth-limiting vitamins B1 and B12 to its dinoflagellate host.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>816</offset>
        <text>The Roseobacter clade has been considered to comprise obligate aerobic bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>897</offset>
        <text>However, D. shibae DFL12T is able to grow anaerobically using the alternative electron acceptors nitrate and dimethylsulfoxide; it has the arginine deiminase survival fermentation pathway and a complex oxygen-dependent Fnr (fumarate and nitrate reduction) regulon.
</text>
        <annotation id="T1">
          <infon key="brat-id">T1</infon>
          <infon key="type">Increase</infon>
          <infon key="brat-type">text-bound</infon>
          <location length="4" offset="934"/>
          <text>grow</text>
        </annotation>
        <annotation id="T2">
          <infon key="brat-id">T2</infon>
          <infon key="type">Variable</infon>
          <infon key="brat-type">text-bound</infon>
          <location length="16" offset="906"/>
          <text>D. shibae DFL12T</text>
        </annotation>
        <relation id="E1">
          <infon key="brat-id">E1</infon>
          <infon key="type">Increase</infon>
          <infon key="brat-type">event</infon>
          <node refid="T1" role="Increase"/>
          <node refid="T2" role="Theme"/>
        </relation>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1162</offset>
        <text>Many of these traits are shared with other members of the Roseobacter clade.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1239</offset>
        <text>D. shibae DFL12T has five plasmids, showing examples for vertical recruitment of chromosomal genes (thiC) and horizontal gene transfer (cox genes, gene cluster of 47 kb) possibly by conjugation (vir gene cluster).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1453</offset>
        <text>The long-range (80%) synteny between two sister plasmids provides insights into the emergence of novel plasmids.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1566</offset>
        <text>D. shibae DFL12T shows the most complex viral defense system of all Rhodobacterales sequenced to date.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
