<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.117#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Treusch_2011, title={Phytoplankton distribution patterns in the northwestern Sargasso Sea revealed by small subunit rRNA genes from plastids}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.117}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.117}, number={3}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Treusch, Alexander H and Demir-Hilton, Elif and Vergin, Kevin L and Worden, Alexandra Z and Carlson, Craig A and Donatz, Michael G and Burton, Robert M and Giovannoni, Stephen J}, year={2011}, month={Sep}, pages={481–492}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.117</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton distribution patterns in the northwestern Sargasso Sea revealed by small subunit rRNA genes from plastids
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>120</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>120</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton species vary in their physiological properties, and are expected to respond differently to seasonal changes in water column conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>270</offset>
        <text>To assess these varying distribution patterns, we used 412 samples collected monthly over 12 years (1991-2004) at the Bermuda Atlantic Time-Series Study site, located in the northwestern Sargasso Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>471</offset>
        <text>We measured plastid 16S ribosomal RNA gene abundances with a terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism approach and identified distribution patterns for members of the Prymnesiophyceae, Pelagophyceae, Chrysophyceae, Cryptophyceae, Bacillariophyceae and Prasinophyceae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>748</offset>
        <text>The analysis revealed dynamic bloom patterns by these phytoplankton taxa that begin early in the year, when the mixed layer is deep.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>881</offset>
        <text>Previously, unreported open-ocean prasinophyte blooms dominated the plastid gene signal during convective mixing events.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1002</offset>
        <text>Quantitative PCR confirmed the blooms and transitions of Bathycoccus, Micromonas and Ostreococcus populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1113</offset>
        <text>In contrast, taxa belonging to the pelagophytes and chrysophytes, as well as cryptophytes, reached annual peaks during mixed layer shoaling, while Bacillariophyceae (diatoms) were observed only episodically in the 12-year record.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1343</offset>
        <text>Prymnesiophytes dominated the integrated plastid gene signal.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1405</offset>
        <text>They were abundant throughout the water column before mixing events, but persisted in the deep chlorophyll maximum during stratified conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1550</offset>
        <text>Various models have been used to describe mechanisms that drive vernal phytoplankton blooms in temperate seas.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1661</offset>
        <text>The range of taxon-specific bloom patterns observed here indicates that different 'spring bloom' models can aptly describe the behavior of different phytoplankton taxa at a single geographical location.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1864</offset>
        <text>These findings provide insight into the subdivision of niche space by phytoplankton and may lead to improved predictions of phytoplankton responses to changes in ocean conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
