<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2008.83#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Sowell_2009, title={Transport functions dominate the SAR11 metaproteome at low-nutrient extremes in the Sargasso Sea}, volume={3}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2008.83}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2008.83}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Sowell, Sarah M and Wilhelm, Larry J and Norbeck, Angela D and Lipton, Mary S and Nicora, Carrie D and Barofsky, Douglas F and Carlson, Craig A and Smith, Richard D and Giovanonni, Stephen J}, year={2009}, month={Jan}, pages={93–105}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2008.83</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Transport functions dominate the SAR11 metaproteome at low-nutrient extremes in the Sargasso Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>97</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>97</offset>
        <text>The northwestern Sargasso Sea undergoes annual cycles of productivity with increased production in spring corresponding to periods of upwelling, and oligotrophy in summer and autumn, when the water column becomes highly stratified.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>329</offset>
        <text>The biological productivity of this region is reduced during stratified periods as a result of low concentrations of phosphorus and nitrogen in the euphotic zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>492</offset>
        <text>To better understand the mechanisms of microbial survival in this oligotrophic environment, we used capillary liquid chromatography (LC)-tandem mass spectrometry to detect microbial proteins in surface samples collected in September 2005.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>731</offset>
        <text>A total of 2215 peptides that mapped to 236 SAR11 proteins, 1911 peptides that mapped to 402 Prochlorococcus proteins and 2407 peptides that mapped to 404 Synechococcus proteins were detected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>924</offset>
        <text>Mass spectra from SAR11 periplasmic substrate-binding proteins accounted for a disproportionately large fraction of the peptides detected, consistent with observations that these extremely small cells devote a large proportion of their volume to periplasm.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1181</offset>
        <text>Abundances were highest for periplasmic substrate-binding proteins for phosphate, amino acids, phosphonate, sugars and spermidine.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1312</offset>
        <text>Proteins implicated in the prevention of oxidative damage and protein refolding were also abundant.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1412</offset>
        <text>Our findings support the view that competition for multiple nutrients in oligotrophic systems is extreme, but nutrient flux is sufficient to sustain microbial community activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
