<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.61#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Carini_2014, title={Discovery of a SAR11 growth requirement for thiamin’s pyrimidine precursor and its distribution in the Sargasso Sea}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.61}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.61}, number={8}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Carini, Paul and Campbell, Emily O and Morré, Jeff and Sañudo-Wilhelmy, Sergio A and Cameron Thrash, J and Bennett, Samuel E and Temperton, Ben and Begley, Tadhg and Giovannoni, Stephen J}, year={2014}, month={Apr}, pages={1727–1738}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.61</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Discovery of a SAR11 growth requirement for thiamins pyrimidine precursor and its distribution in the Sargasso Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>115</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>115</offset>
        <text>Vitamin traffic, the production of organic growth factors by some microbial community members and their use by other taxa, is being scrutinized as a potential explanation for the variation and highly connected behavior observed in ocean plankton by community network analysis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>392</offset>
        <text>Thiamin (vitamin B1), a cofactor in many essential biochemical reactions that modify carboncarbon bonds of organic compounds, is distributed in complex patterns at subpicomolar concentrations in the marine surface layer (0300m).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>621</offset>
        <text>Sequenced genomes from organisms belonging to the abundant and ubiquitous SAR11 clade of marine chemoheterotrophic bacteria contain genes coding for a complete thiamin biosynthetic pathway, except for thiC, encoding the 4-amino-5-hydroxymethyl-2-methylpyrimidine (HMP) synthase, which is required for de novo synthesis of thiamins pyrimidine moiety.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>971</offset>
        <text>Here we demonstrate that the SAR11 isolate Candidatus Pelagibacter ubique, strain HTCC1062, is auxotrophic for the thiamin precursor HMP, and cannot use exogenous thiamin for growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1154</offset>
        <text>In culture, strain HTCC1062 required 0.7 zeptomoles per cell (ca. 400HMP molecules per cell).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1248</offset>
        <text>Measurements of dissolved HMP in the Sargasso Sea surface layer showed that HMP ranged from undetectable (detection limit: 2.4pM) to 35.7pM, with maximum concentrations coincident with the deep chlorophyll maximum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1463</offset>
        <text>In culture, some marine cyanobacteria, microalgae and bacteria exuded HMP, and in the Western Sargasso Sea, HMP profiles changed between the morning and evening, suggesting a dynamic biological flux from producers to consumers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1691</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 29 April 2014; doi:10.1038/ismej.2014.61
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
