<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.138#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.138</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Sison_Mangus_2014, title={Host-specific adaptation governs the interaction of the marine diatom, Pseudo-nitzschia and their microbiota}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.138}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.138}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Sison-Mangus, Marilou P and Jiang, Sunny and Tran, Kevin N and Kudela, Raphael M}, year={2014}, month={Jan}, pages={63–76}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Host-specific adaptation governs the interaction of the marine diatom, Pseudo-nitzschia and their microbiota
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>109</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>109</offset>
        <text>The association of phytoplankton with bacteria is ubiquitous in nature and the bacteria that associate with different phytoplankton species are very diverse.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>267</offset>
        <text>The influence of these bacteria in the physiology and ecology of the host and the evolutionary forces that shape the relationship are still not understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>423</offset>
        <text>In this study, we used the Pseudo-nitzschia-microbiota association to determine (1) if algal species with distinct domoic acid (DA) production are selection factors that structures the bacterial community, (2) if host-specificity and co-adaptation govern the association, (3) the functional roles of isolated member of microbiota on diatom-hosts fitness and (4) the influence of microbiota in changing the phenotype of the diatom hosts with regards to toxin production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>893</offset>
        <text>Analysis of the pyrosequencing-derived 16S rDNA data suggests that the three tested species of Pseudo-nitzschia, which vary in toxin production, have phylogenetically distinct bacterial communities, and toxic Pseudo-nitzschia have lower microbial diversity than non-toxic Pseudo-nitzschia.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1183</offset>
        <text>Transplant experiments showed that isolated members of the microbiota are mutualistic to their native hosts but some are commensal or parasitic to foreign hosts, hinting at co-evolution between partners.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1387</offset>
        <text>Moreover, Pseudo-nitzschia host can gain protection from algalytic bacteria by maintaining association with its microbiota.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1511</offset>
        <text>Pseudo-nitzschia also exhibit different phenotypic expression with regards to DA production, and this depends on the bacterial species with which the host associates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1678</offset>
        <text>Hence, the influences of the microbiota on diatom host physiology should be considered when studying the biology and ecology of marine diatoms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
