<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.80#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Brettar_2011, title={Analysis of bacterial core communities in the central Baltic by comparative RNA–DNA-based fingerprinting provides links to structure–function relationships}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.80}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.80}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Brettar, Ingrid and Christen, Richard and Höfle, Manfred G}, year={2011}, month={Jun}, pages={195–212}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.80</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Analysis of bacterial core communities in the central Baltic by comparative RNA-DNA-based fingerprinting provides links to structure-function relationships
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>156</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>156</offset>
        <text>Understanding structure-function links of microbial communities is a central theme of microbial ecology since its beginning.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>281</offset>
        <text>To this end, we studied the spatial variability of the bacterioplankton community structure and composition across the central Baltic Sea at four stations, which were up to 450 km apart and at a depth profile representative for the central part (Gotland Deep, 235 m).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>549</offset>
        <text>Bacterial community structure was followed by 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA)- and 16S rRNA gene-based fingerprints using single-strand conformation polymorphism (SSCP) electrophoresis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>728</offset>
        <text>Species composition was determined by sequence analysis of SSCP bands.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>799</offset>
        <text>High similarities of the bacterioplankton communities across several hundred kilometers were observed in the surface water using RNA- and DNA-based fingerprints.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>961</offset>
        <text>In these surface communities, the RNA- and DNA-based fingerprints resulted in very different pattern, presumably indicating large difference between the active members of the community as represented by RNA-based fingerprints and the present members represented by the DNA-based fingerprints.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1254</offset>
        <text>This large discrepancy changed gradually over depth, resulting in highly similar RNA- and DNA-based fingerprints in the anoxic part of the water column below 130 m depth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1425</offset>
        <text>A conceivable mechanism explaining this high similarity could be the reduced oxidative stress in the anoxic zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1539</offset>
        <text>The stable communities on the surface and in the anoxic zone indicate the strong influence of the hydrography on the bacterioplankton community structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1694</offset>
        <text>Comparative analysis of RNA- and DNA-based community structure provided criteria for the identification of the core community, its key members and their links to biogeochemical functions.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
