<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nrmicro1745#abs#sent#bioc#annot</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{J_rgensen_2007, title={Feast and famine — microbial life in the deep-sea bed}, volume={5}, ISSN={1740-1534}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro1745}, DOI={10.1038/nrmicro1745}, number={10}, journal={Nature Reviews Microbiology}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Jørgensen, Bo Barker and Boetius, Antje}, year={2007}, month={Oct}, pages={770–781}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nrmicro1745</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Feast and famine -- microbial life in the deep-sea bed
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>55</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>55</offset>
        <text>The seabed is a diverse environment that ranges from the desert-like deep seafloor to the rich oases that are present at seeps, vents, and food falls such as whales, wood or kelp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>235</offset>
        <text>As well as the sedimentation of organic material from above, geological processes transport chemical energy -- hydrogen, methane, hydrogen sulphide and iron -- to the seafloor from the subsurface below, which provides a significant proportion of the deep-sea energy.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>502</offset>
        <text>At the sites on the seafloor where chemical energy is delivered, rich and diverse microbial communities thrive.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>614</offset>
        <text>However, most subsurface microorganisms live in conditions of extreme energy limitation, with mean generation times of up to thousands of years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>759</offset>
        <text>Even in the most remote subsurface habitats, temperature rather than energy seems to set the ultimate limit for life, and in the deep biosphere, where energy is most depleted, life might even be based on the cleavage of water by natural radioisotopes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1011</offset>
        <text>Here, we review microbial biodiversity and function in these intriguing environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
