<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1126#science.1154122#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1126/science.1154122</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Iglesias_Rodriguez_2008,
	doi = {10.1126/science.1154122},
	url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1154122},
	year = 2008,
	month = {Apr},
	publisher = {American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)},
	volume = {320},
	number = {5874},
	pages = {336-340},
	author = {M. D. Iglesias-Rodriguez and P. R. Halloran and R. E. M. Rickaby and I. R. Hall and E. Colmenero-Hidalgo and J. R. Gittins and D. R. H. Green and T. Tyrrell and S. J. Gibbs and P. von Dassow and E. Rehm and E. V. Armbrust and K. P. Boessenkool},
	title = {Phytoplankton Calcification in a High-CO2 World},
	journal = {Science}
}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Ocean acidification in response to rising atmospheric CO2 partial pressures is widely expected to reduce calcification by marine organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>140</offset>
        <text>From the mid-Mesozoic, coccolithophores have been major calcium carbonate producers in the world’s oceans, today accounting for about a third of the total marine CaCO3 production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>320</offset>
        <text>Here, we present laboratory evidence that calcification and net primary production in the coccolithophore species Emiliania huxleyi are significantly increased by high CO2 partial pressures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>511</offset>
        <text>Field evidence from the deep ocean is consistent with these laboratory conclusions, indicating that over the past 220 years there has been a 40% increase in average coccolith mass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>692</offset>
        <text>Our findings show that coccolithophores are already responding and will probably continue to respond to rising atmospheric CO2 partial pressures, which has important implications for biogeochemical modeling of future oceans and climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
