<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1126#science.1164533#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1126/science.1164533</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Montes_Hugo_2009,
	doi = {10.1126/science.1164533},
	url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1164533},
	year = 2009,
	month = {Mar},
	publisher = {American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)},
	volume = {323},
	number = {5920},
	pages = {1470-1473},
	author = {M. Montes-Hugo and S. C. Doney and H. W. Ducklow and W. Fraser and D. Martinson and S. E. Stammerjohn and O. Schofield},
	title = {Recent Changes in Phytoplankton Communities Associated with Rapid Regional Climate Change Along the Western Antarctic Peninsula},
	journal = {Science}
}

</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The climate of the western shelf of the Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) is undergoing a transition from a cold-dry polar-type climate to a warm-humid sub-Antarctic–type climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>172</offset>
        <text>Using three decades of satellite and field data, we document that ocean biological productivity, inferred from chlorophyll a concentration (Chl a), has significantly changed along the WAP shelf.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>367</offset>
        <text>Summertime surface Chl a (summer integrated Chl a ~63% of annually integrated Chl a) declined by 12% along the WAP over the past 30 years, with the largest decreases equatorward of 63°S and with substantial increases in Chl a occurring farther south.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>618</offset>
        <text>The latitudinal variation in Chl a trends reflects shifting patterns of ice cover, cloud formation, and windiness affecting water-column mixing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>763</offset>
        <text>Regional changes in phytoplankton coincide with observed changes in krill (Euphausia superba) and penguin populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
