<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1029#2006gl026213#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1029/2006gl026213</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Omta_2006,
	doi = {10.1029/2006gl026213},
	url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2006gl026213},
	year = 2006,
	publisher = {Wiley-Blackwell},
	volume = {33},
	number = {14},
	author = {Anne Willem Omta and Jorn Bruggeman and S. A. L. M. Kooijman and Henk A. Dijkstra},
	title = {Biological carbon pump revisited: Feedback mechanisms between climate and the Redfield ratio},
	journal = {Geophysical Research Letters}
}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Biological activity gives rise to a difference in carbon concentration between the ocean surface and the deep waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>118</offset>
        <text>This difference is determined by the carbon:nutrient ratio of the sinking organic material and it is crucial in determining the distribution of CO2 between the atmosphere and the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>304</offset>
        <text>For this reason, it is interesting to determine whether the physical environment affects the carbon:nitrogen ratio of phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>437</offset>
        <text>Using a model with a novel representation of the effect of temperature on phytoplankton stoichiometry, we have investigated the influence of mixed-layer depth and water temperature on the elemental composition of an algal community.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>670</offset>
        <text>In the light-limited regime, the carbon:nutrient ratio turns out to decrease with increasing mixed-layer depth and temperature.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>798</offset>
        <text>Hence our model suggests the existence of a positive feedback between temperature and atmospheric CO2 content through the stoichiometry of phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>952</offset>
        <text>This feedback may have contributed to the glacial/interglacial cycles in the atmospheric CO2 concentration.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
