<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1016#j.dsr2.2000.10.001#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1016/j.dsr2.2000.10.001</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{_zt_rk_2004,
	doi = {10.1016/j.dsr2.2000.10.001},
	url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2000.10.001},
	year = 2004,
	month = {Nov},
	publisher = {Elsevier BV},
	volume = {51},
	number = {22-24},
	pages = {2841-2856},
	author = {Murat Öztürk and Peter L. Croot and Stefan Bertilsson and Katarina Abrahamsson and Bengt Karlson and Roland David and Agneta Fransson and Egil Sakshaug},
	title = {Iron enrichment and photoreduction of iron under UV and PAR in the presence of hydroxycarboxylic acid: implications for phytoplankton growth in the Southern Ocean},
	journal = {Deep Sea Research Part II: Topical Studies in Oceanography}
}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Iron(III) photoreduction and the responses of phytoplankton under ultraviolet (UV) and photosynthetically available radiation (PAR) were investigated with the presence of hydroxycarboxylic acid (glucaric acid (GA), a model compound for organic acids excreted by phytoplankton).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>278</offset>
        <text>The incubation experiments were carried out on board using seawater samples collected in the location of the winter ice edge (WIE) and the spring ice edge (SIE) of the Southern Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>462</offset>
        <text>In this paper, we focus on the results of experiment in WIE.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>523</offset>
        <text>Throughout the experiments, dissolved Fe(II), major nutrients and in vivo fluorescence were monitored regularly.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>636</offset>
        <text>In addition, Chl-a, POC/PON, cell densities of phytoplankton and bacteria, bacterial production, organic peroxide, hydrogen peroxide and total CO2 were measured.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>798</offset>
        <text>The results from the WIE show that iron enrichment had a substantial effect on phytoplankton growth rate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>904</offset>
        <text>Fe(III) addition in the presence of GA (FeGA) gave higher Fe(II) concentration and higher growth rate of phytoplankton than those in controls.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1047</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that hydroxycarboxylic acid had a significant chemical and biological impact.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1145</offset>
        <text>The presence of GA influenced iron photochemistry and iron availability to phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1235</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton growth responses to iron enrichments in incubations under UV and PAR were completely dissimilar.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1346</offset>
        <text>It seems that FeGA addition prominently changes the harmful effect of UV on the phytoplankton population.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1452</offset>
        <text>This study provides preliminary information on how the photoreduction of iron(III) and the phytoplankton growth are affected by iron enrichment in the presence of hydroxycarboxylic acid.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
