<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature07235#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1038/nature07235</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Thingstad_2008, title={Counterintuitive carbon-to-nutrient coupling in an Arctic pelagic ecosystem}, volume={455}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature07235}, DOI={10.1038/nature07235}, number={7211}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Thingstad, T. F. and Bellerby, R. G. J. and Bratbak, G. and Børsheim, K. Y. and Egge, J. K. and Heldal, M. and Larsen, A. and Neill, C. and Nejstgaard, J. and Norland, S. and et al.}, year={2008}, month={Aug}, pages={387–390}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Predicting the ocean’s role in the global carbon cycle requires an understanding of the stoichiometric coupling between carbon and growth-limiting elements in biogeochemical processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>185</offset>
        <text>A recent addition to such knowledge is that the carbon/nitrogen ratio of inorganic consumption and release of dissolved organic matter may increase in a high-CO2 world.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>354</offset>
        <text>This will, however, yield a negative feedback on atmospheric CO2 only if the extra organic material escapes mineralization within the photic zone.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>501</offset>
        <text>Here we show, in the context of an Arctic pelagic ecosystem, how the fate and effects of added degradable organic carbon depend critically on the state of the microbial food web.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>680</offset>
        <text>When bacterial growth rate was limited by mineral nutrients, extra organic carbon accumulated in the system.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>789</offset>
        <text>When bacteria were limited by organic carbon, however, addition of labile dissolved organic carbon reduced phytoplankton biomass and activity and also the rate at which total organic carbon accumulated, explained as the result of stimulated bacterial competition for mineral nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1075</offset>
        <text>This counterintuitive ‘more organic carbon gives less organic carbon’ effect was particularly pronounced in diatom-dominated systems where the carbon/mineral nutrient ratio in phytoplankton production was high.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1286</offset>
        <text>Our results highlight how descriptions of present and future states of the oceanic carbon cycle require detailed understanding of the stoichiometric coupling between carbon and growth-limiting mineral nutrients in both autotrophic and heterotrophic processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
