<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1507#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Gao_2012, title={Rising CO2 and increased light exposure synergistically reduce marine primary productivity}, ISSN={1758-6798}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1507}, DOI={10.1038/nclimate1507}, journal={Nature Climate Change}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Gao, Kunshan and Xu, Juntian and Gao, Guang and Li, Yahe and Hutchins, David A. and Huang, Bangqin and Wang, Lei and Zheng, Ying and Jin, Peng and Cai, Xiaoni and et al.}, year={2012}, month={May}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1038/nclimate1507</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Carbon dioxide and light are two major prerequisites of photosynthesis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>72</offset>
        <text>Rising CO2 levels in oceanic surface waters in combination with ample light supply are therefore often considered stimulatory to marine primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>228</offset>
        <text>Here we show that the combination of an increase in both CO2 and light exposure negatively impacts photosynthesis and growth of marine primary producers.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>382</offset>
        <text>When exposed to CO2 concentrations projected for the end of this century, natural phytoplankton assemblages of the South China Sea responded with decreased primary production and increased light stress at light intensities representative of the upper surface layer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>648</offset>
        <text>The phytoplankton community shifted away from diatoms, the dominant phytoplankton group during our field campaigns.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>764</offset>
        <text>To examine the underlying mechanisms of the observed responses, we grew diatoms at different CO2 concentrations and under varying levels (5–100%) of solar radiation experienced by the phytoplankton at different depths of the euphotic zone. 
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1005</offset>
        <text>Above 22–36% of incident surface irradiance, growth rates in the high-CO2-grown cells were inversely related to light levels and exhibited reduced thresholds at which light becomes inhibitory.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1198</offset>
        <text>Future shoaling of upper-mixed-layer depths will expose phytoplankton to increased mean light intensities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1305</offset>
        <text>In combination with rising CO2 levels, this may cause a widespread decline in marine primary production and a community shift away from diatoms, the main algal group that supports higher trophic levels and carbon export in the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
