<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#35030078#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1038/35030078</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Riebesell_2000, volume={407}, ISSN={0028-0836}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35030078}, DOI={10.1038/35030078}, number={6802}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Riebesell, Ulf and Zondervan, Ingrid and Rost, Björn and Tortell, Philippe D. and Zeebe, Richard E. and Morel, François M. M.}, year={2000}, month={Sep}, pages={364–367}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The formation of calcareous skeletons by marine planktonic organisms and their subsequent sinking to depth generates a continuous rain of calcium carbonate to the deep ocean and underlying sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>200</offset>
        <text>This is important in regulating marine carbon cycling and ocean-atmosphere CO2 exchange.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>289</offset>
        <text>The present rise in atmospheric CO2 levels causes significant changes in surface ocean pH and carbonate chemistry.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>404</offset>
        <text>Such changes have been shown to slow down calcification in corals and coralline macroalgae, but the majority of marine calcification occurs in planktonic organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>569</offset>
        <text>Here we report reduced calcite production at increased CO2 concentrations in monospecific cultures of two dominant marine calcifying phytoplankton species, the coccolithophorids Emiliania huxleyi and Gephyrocapsa oceanica.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>792</offset>
        <text>This was accompanied by an increased proportion of malformed coccoliths and incomplete coccospheres.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>893</offset>
        <text>Diminished calcification led to a reduction in the ratio of calcite precipitation to organic matter production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1005</offset>
        <text>Similar results were obtained in incubations of natural plankton assemblages from the north Pacific ocean when exposed to experimentally elevated CO2 levels.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1163</offset>
        <text>We suggest that the progressive increase in atmospheric CO2 concentrations may therefore slow down the production of calcium carbonate in the surface ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1320</offset>
        <text>As the process of calcification releases CO2 to the atmosphere, the response observed here could potentially act as a negative feedback on atmospheric CO2 levels.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
