<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">pilot</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1146#annurev.marine.010908.163917#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
@article{Chavez_2011,
	doi = {10.1146/annurev.marine.010908.163917},
	url = {http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.marine.010908.163917},
	year = 2011,
	month = {Jan},
	publisher = {Annual Reviews},
	volume = {3},
	number = {1},
	pages = {227-260},
	author = {Francisco P. Chavez and Monique Messié and J. Timothy Pennington},
	title = {Marine Primary Production in Relation to Climate Variability and Change},
	journal = {Annual Review of Marine Science}
}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/pilot/10.1146/annurev.marine.010908.163917</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Marine photosynthetic plankton are responsible for approximately 50 petagrams (10 15) of carbon per year of net primary production, an amount equivalent to that on land.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>170</offset>
        <text>This primary production supports essentially all life in the oceans and profoundly affects global biogeochemical cycles and climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>303</offset>
        <text>This review discusses the general distribution of primary production in the sea, the processes that regulate this distribution, and how marine primary production is sensitive to climate variability and change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>513</offset>
        <text>Statistical modes of ocean variability and their characteristic interannual to multi-decadal timescales over the last century are described.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>654</offset>
        <text>Recent in situ and satellite time-series of primary production can be clearly linked to interannual ocean variability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>773</offset>
        <text>Global marine primary production appears to have increased over the past several decades in association with multi-decadal variations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>908</offset>
        <text>A paleoclimate record extends discussion to the centennial scale, providing contrasting insights into how marine primary production might vary in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
