<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher></journal-meta>
    <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-19293</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047887</article-id><article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Ecology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Ecological environments</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Marine environments</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Microbiology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Microbial ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Environmental chemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine chemistry</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Geochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Carbon sink</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Earth sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Atmospheric science</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Climatology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Climate change</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Geochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biogeochemistry</subject>
              <subject>Carbon cycle</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Marine and aquatic sciences</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine geology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Sediment</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Oceanography</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Biological oceanography</subject>
                <subject>Chemical oceanography</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Marine biology</subject>
              <subject>Marine ecology</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Chemistry</subject>
          <subject>Microbiology</subject>
          <subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories><title-group><article-title>An Unaccounted Fraction of Marine Biogenic CaCO<sub>3</sub> Particles</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Marine Biogenic CaCO<sub>3</sub> Particles</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Heldal</surname>
            <given-names>Mikal</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Norland</surname>
            <given-names>Svein</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Erichsen</surname>
            <given-names>Egil S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thingstad</surname>
            <given-names>T. Frede</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bratbak</surname>
            <given-names>Gunnar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>*</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
        <label>1</label>
        <addr-line>Department of Biology, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</addr-line>
      </aff><aff id="aff2">
        <label>2</label>
        <addr-line>Laboratory for Electron Microscopy, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</addr-line>
      </aff><contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Paranhos</surname>
            <given-names>Rodolfo</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
        <addr-line>Instituto de Biologia, Brazil</addr-line>
      </aff><author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">gunnar.bratbak@bio.uib.no</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="conflict">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MH SN GB TFT. Performed the experiments: MH SN GB. Analyzed the data: MH SN GB TFT ESE. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MH SN ESE. Wrote the paper: MH SN GB TFT.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e47887</elocation-id><history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history><permissions>
        
        <copyright-holder>Heldal et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:type="simple">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions><abstract>
        <p>Biogenic production and sedimentation of calcium carbonate in the ocean, referred to as the carbonate pump, has profound implications for the ocean carbon cycle, and relate both to global climate, ocean acidification and the geological past. In marine pelagic environments coccolithophores, foraminifera and pteropods have been considered the main calcifying organisms. Here, we document the presence of an abundant, previously unaccounted fraction of marine calcium carbonate particles in seawater, presumably formed by bacteria or in relation to extracellular polymeric substances. The particles occur in a variety of different morphologies, in a size range from &lt;1 to &gt;100 µm, and in a typical concentration of 10<sup>4</sup>–10<sup>5</sup> particles L<sup>−1</sup> (size range counted 1–100 µm). Quantitative estimates of annual averages suggests that the pure calcium particles we counted in the 1–100 µm size range account for 2–4 times more CaCO<sub>3</sub> than the dominating coccolithophoride <italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic> and for 21% of the total concentration of particulate calcium. Due to their high density, we hypothesize that the particles sediment rapidly, and therefore contribute significantly to the export of carbon and alkalinity from surface waters. The biological and environmental factors affecting the formation of these particles and possible impact of this process on global atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> remains to be investigated.</p>
      </abstract><funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was financed by the Research Council of Norway through the project 184860/S30 ‘MERCLIM’ and the International Polar Year project 175939/S30 ‘PAME-Nor’ (IPY activity ID no. 71), and by the European Research Council through the Advanced Grant project No. 250254 “MINOS”. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group><counts>
        <page-count count="6"/>
      </counts></article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Calcification increases the <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> and acidity of seawater and is a central process in ocean-atmosphere CO<sub>2</sub> exchange and in regulation of the global atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> level <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Fabry1">[1]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Houghton1">[3]</xref>.</p>
      <p>A large fraction of the carbon exported from the sea surface to deep waters and sediments is in the form of biogenic calcium carbonate (CaCO<sub>3</sub>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Berelson1">[4]</xref>. The importance of biogenic calcification is, in a geological perspective, evident from the global presence of calcium carbonate rocks like limestone and dolomite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Tucker1">[5]</xref>. The relative contributions of the major planktonic CaCO<sub>3</sub> producers, coccolithophores, foraminifera and pteropods, to global calcification rates are poorly constrained <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Berelson1">[4]</xref>. Coccolithophores and foraminifera have been estimated to account for 20–80% and 23–56% of biogenic carbonate exported from the photic zone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Schiebel1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ziveri1">[7]</xref>. Pteropods and calcareous dinophytes are thought to be of minor importance and have been reported to account for &lt;10% and 3.5% of the total planktonic carbonate production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Schiebel1">[6]</xref>. Precipitation of calcium carbonate particles induced by photosynthetic picoplankton and creating patches of particles (lime mud) called whiting event, are known to be of local or regional importance in both freshwater and tropical to subtropical marine environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Robbins1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Thompson1">[9]</xref>. Carbonate precipitation is however also a common property of many different bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ehrlich1">[10]</xref> and it is found to take place in many different aquatic and soil environments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Vasconcelos1">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Decho1">[13]</xref>. As far as we are aware, CaCO<sub>3</sub> precipitation by marine bacteria was first described about 100 years ago <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Drew1">[14]</xref> and later studied by a number of others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Lipman1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Novitsky1">[19]</xref>. The quantitative significance of the process <italic>in situ</italic> in marine waters has however remained undecided <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ehrlich1">[10]</xref> and bacteria have hence not been considered among the major planktonic CaCO<sub>3</sub> producers.</p>
      <p>In this study we used X-ray fluorescence (XRF) to quantify total particulate calcium in seawater and analytical scanning electron microscopy (SEM) to observe, determine elemental composition of and count marine calcium particles harvested onto polycarbonate filters (pore size 0.6 or 1.0 µm).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Ethics Statement</title>
        <p>No specific permits were required for the described field studies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Sampling</title>
        <p>Raunefjorden (60<sup>o</sup>16.2′N, 5<sup>o</sup>12.5′E): Samples were collected from 5 m depth in Raunefjorden a coastal sampling station south of Bergen, Norway. CTD and chl <italic>a</italic> data were obtained with an STD SAIV a/s SD 204 with a Sea Point fluorometer (SAIV A/S, Environmental Sensors and Systems).</p>
        <p>The Norwegian Sea: Samples were collected at 7 stations in The Norwegian Sea from, November 3.-8. 2010 during Cruise no 2010115 with R/V G.O. Sars. Samples were collected between 0 and 2500 m depth. CTD and chl <italic>a</italic> data were obtained with a Sea-Bird SBE 9. For details on sampling positions and depths see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s001">Fig. S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s010">Table S1</xref>.</p>
        <p>Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B (43°41.10′N–7°18.94′E): Samples were collected at 0, 10, 20, 30, 50 and 75 m on November 23. 2010. CTD and Chla <italic>a</italic> fluorescence data, obtained with a Seabird SBE 25, was provided by Service d’Observation en Milieu Littoral, INSU-CNRS, Point B, and by Service d’Observation de la Rade de Villefranche.</p>
        <p>Kings Bay, Svalbard (78°58′N - 11°50E): Samples were collected at 5 m on June 14. 2010.</p>
        <p>Sediment samples from the Norwegian continental margin: Sediment cores were collected in 1998 at 63°45'44''N; 05°15'19''E where the water depth is 840 m. The particles were sub sampled from the cores at ca 9 cm depth in the sediment, a stratum dated to 1953. (For details on cores see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Sejrup1">[20]</xref>).</p>
        <p>Samples for counting of particles and X-ray analysis was prepared as described below within 1–4 h after sampling.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Counting and X-ray Analysis of Particles in Scanning Electron Microscope</title>
        <p>Particles from 200–750 mL of each water sample were harvested on a 0.6 µm (Raunefjorden and The Norwegian Sea) or 1 µm (Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B) pore size (25 mm diameter) polycarbonate membrane filter (GE Water &amp; Process Technologies, PA, USA) within 2 h after sampling. Sediment samples for qualitative scrutiny were collected from the cores, resuspended in distilled water and filtered onto 1 µm filters as described above to make microscope specimens with a particle density appropriate for visual inspection.No fixatives, washing or staining was applied. The filters were air dried and coated for 30 seconds with Au/Pd in a Polaron SC502 Sputter Coater. The samples were viewed and analyzed in Zeiss Supra 55 VP scanning electron microscope equipped with EDS detector for X-ray elemental analysis. The microscope was operated at 8 kV accelerating voltage, and working distance of 4 mm. For X-ray microanalysis the instrument was operated at 15 kV accelerating voltage and working distance of 8–12 mm. Given the filter area, counting at 4000× magnification, known screen size and known sample volume, we calculated cells and particles pr mL.</p>
        <p>The amount of CaCO<sub>3</sub> in the particles we counted was estimated from particle abundance and volume, and assuming them to have a density of 2.7 g cm<sup>−3</sup> as for calcite. The irregular morphology and variable size of the particles precluded accurate volume estimates based on microscope sizing. A conservative estimate of volume was nevertheless obtained assuming them to be spherical and with a mean diameter of 5 µm.The amount of CaCO<sub>3</sub> in <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> was estimated from cell abundance, assuming a Ca content of 0.7 pg Ca pr coccolith and an average of 15 coccoliths pr cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Paasche1">[21]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Quantification of Total Particulate Ca by X-ray Fluorescence</title>
        <p>Particles from 0.5–2L of the water samples were harvested on filters within 2–4 h after sampling. The samples from Raunefjorden and from Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B were harvested onto 0.6 µm pore size (47 mm diameter) polycarbonate membrane filter (GE Water &amp; Process Technologies, PA, USA). The samples from The Norwegian Sea were fractionated on 0.2, 1, 5 and 10 µm pore size (47 mm diameter) polycarbonate membrane filter (GE Water &amp; Process Technologies, PA, USA) and the results added up to give particulate Ca&gt;0.2 µm or on 0.2 µm pore size (47 mm diameter) Anodisc Al filters (Whatman, Maidstone, UK).</p>
        <p>The filters were rinsed briefly by pulling 5 mL deionized water through the filters after filtration of the samples to remove seawater ions and reduce background signal. Excess water on the back and the brim of the filters was blotted off using clean paper tissue and they were then air dried at room temperature before analyses. Analyzing filters with and without rinsing with deionized water showed that the procedure did not affect the Ca measurements. The filters were analyzed in a Bruker AXE S4 Pioneer WDXRF instrument. The Ca measurements were calibrated with CaCl<sub>2</sub> dissolved in ethanol to known concentration, applied to a silver plate and air dried before analysis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <p>The CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles we observed and counted were of different morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Some particles had a morphology that resembles bacteria or micro colonies of bacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1a–b</xref>). Others (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1</xref> c–d) were very similar to the Ca carbonates described to precipitate as needles and microcrystalline aragonite growing both parallel and perpendicular to the cell surface of cultured marine heterotrophic bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Krumbein1">[22]</xref>, or as the 20–30 µm long and 5–10 µm wide “Weisenkörner” found in Black Sea sediments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Mller1">[23]</xref>. Some particles had one flat surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1e–f</xref>) and resemble the highly oriented vaterite CaCO<sub>3</sub> tablet-like arrays with a smooth air-side and rugged water-side formed at the air/water interface in the presence of polypeptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Liu1">[24]</xref>. Particles with rhombohedral (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1</xref> g–h) or baton like (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1</xref> i–j) structure were also relatively frequent in our material. The former resembles calcite particles formed under experimental conditions in the presence of bacteria and bacterial extracellular polymers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Tourney1">[25]</xref>. The latter show some resemblance to the baton like particles found in Bahaman ooids and interpreted as calcified rod-shaped bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Kahle1">[26]</xref>. The differences in morphology strongly suggest that the particles result from different processes or differences in the precipitation nuclei. We find it unlikely that the particles we have observed should originate from any land based mineral sources and since some have the appearance of growing crystals we conclude that they are formed <italic>in situ</italic>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0047887-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Scanning electron microscope images of marine calcium particles with different morphology.</title>
          <p>Samples were collected at 5 m depth in Raunefjorden, a coastal sampling station south of Bergen, Norway. A and B) Particles resembling bacteria and microcolonies of bacteria. B and D) Particles similar to the Ca carbonates described to precipitate on the cell surface of cultured marine bacteria. E and F) Particles with one flat surface suggesting that they are formed on a surface or interface. G and H) Particles with rhombohedral shape. I and J) Baton like particles resembling Bahaman ooids. All scale bars are 2 µm except in d) where it is 1 µm and f) where it is 10 µm.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The microscope’s X-ray detector was used to assess the elemental composition of particles and to identify calcium containing particles before counting. The chemical composition of the particles varied from nearly pure CaCO<sub>3</sub> to particles containing significant and variable amounts of Mg, Fe and Si (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s002">Fig. S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s003">S3</xref>). In this context we counted the pure CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles with size &gt;1 µm. The annual variation in CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles observed at 5 m depth in Raunefjorden, a coastal sampling station south of Bergen, Norway, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g002">Fig. 2a</xref> in comparison to CaCO<sub>3</sub> in the coccoliths of <italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic>. Hydrographical data and chl <italic>a</italic> profiles are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s004">Fig. S4</xref>. The abundance of CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles ranged from undetectable to 150 000 particles L<sup>−1</sup> with an average of about 30 000 particles L<sup>−1</sup>. The abundance of <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> was typically in the range of 10<sup>3</sup>–10<sup>5</sup> cells L<sup>−1</sup> except for the bloom period when it reached 2 10<sup>6</sup> cells L<sup>−1</sup>. The abundance of other coccolithophores like <italic>Syracosphaera borealis, Algirosphaera robusta</italic> and <italic>Acanthoica quattrospina</italic> never exceeded 5000 cells L<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0047887-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>The annual variation in CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles and chl <italic>a.</italic></title>
          <p>Samples were collected at 5 m depth in Raunefjorden, a coastal sampling station south of Bergen, Norway. A) Calcium in the coccolithophore <italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic> and in Ca particles estimated from scanning electron microscope counts. B) Total particulate Ca concentration measured by X-ray fluorescence (error bars are SE, n = 3–4) and chl <italic>a</italic> concentration. Hydrographical data and chl <italic>a</italic> profiles are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s004">Fig. S4</xref>.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The counting based estimates of CaCO<sub>3</sub> concentration gave an annual average of 60±50 nM in particles and 30±80 nM in <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> (Mean±SD). Excluding the bloom, the annual average for <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> was 14±15 nM. The total concentration of particulate calcium, as measured by XRF analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>), amount to an annual average of 420±280 nM excluding the <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> bloom period with a peak value of 6400 nM when the abundance of free coccoliths was high. The XRF analysis will, in addition to the CaCO<sub>3</sub> in the pure CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles with size &gt;1 µm we counted, also include the CaCO<sub>3</sub> in smaller particles (0.2–1 µm), in free coccoliths, in faecal pellets, and in particles containing additional elements like Mg, Fe or Si. This suggests that our estimate of particulate CaCO<sub>3</sub> based on counting of particles and <italic>E. huxleyi</italic> cells is conservative and that the CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles, in comparison to coccolithophores may contribute significantly to the CaCO<sub>3</sub> budget in surface waters. We note that there is a significant positive correlation (R = 0.644, p&lt;0.0003, DF = 25) between total concentration of particulate calcium and chl <italic>a</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g002">Fig. 2b</xref>) suggesting that there is a link between CaCO<sub>3</sub> particle production and biological production.</p>
      <p>In samples collected along two transects across The Norwegian Sea (3–8. Nov. 2010) at 68–70°N, 5–14°E and at 63–64<sup>o</sup>N, 0–4<sup>o</sup>E and at depths from 5 to 2500 m (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s001">Fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s010">Table S1</xref>) we found similar particles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s005">Fig. S5</xref>) and a particulate Ca concentration of 220±100 nM (Mean±SD) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s006">Fig. S6</xref>) but no obvious correlation with depth, distance offshore or chl <italic>a.</italic> Similar particles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s007">Fig. S7</xref>) were also found in samples collected at 1–75 m depths in the Mediterranean Sea (Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B, 23. Nov. 2010) where the particulate Ca concentration was 430±120 nM (Mean±SD) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s008">Fig. S8</xref>) and in samples collected at 5 m depth in Kings Bay (Svalbard), indicating a ubiquitous distribution in the ocean. Moreover, both amorphous particles and particles with one flat surface were found at ca 9 cm depth in sediment core samples collected at 840 m depth on the Norwegian continental margin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s009">Fig. S9</xref>).</p>
      <p>The formation of the CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles we have observed may be related to bacterial activity and processes generating biogeochemical conditions facilitating precipitation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Decho1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Douglas1">[27]</xref> or to chemical processes driving precipitation in bacterial outer structures such as exopolysaccharides and capsular polysaccharides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Decho1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ercole1">[28]</xref>. These conditions and processes may involve nucleation sites, pH, electrostatic charge, ionic concentration etc. and make the microenvironment in and on the cell wall and adjacent matrix different from the surrounding bulk habitat. The biofilm formed at the air-sea surface interface by coagulation and aggregation of dissolved organic substances released from phytoplankton bacteria and other organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Cunliffe1">[29]</xref> is another possible site of calcium carbonate precipitation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Decho1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Liu1">[24]</xref>. The variety of different processes and chemical microenvironments possibly involved in precipitation and formation of CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles may explain the morphological diversity of the CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ercole1">[28]</xref>. The diversity may also be related to different bacteria precipitating different amounts, shapes, and types of carbonate crystals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ercole1">[28]</xref>. The CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles we have observed may be classified as different morphotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0047887-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) but each morphotype is far more variable in size and structure than the CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles produced by e.g. coccolithophores and foraminifera, supporting the view that bacterial CaCO<sub>3</sub> precipitation is not very carefully controlled or structurally directed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Decho1">[13]</xref>. Correlation between particulate calcium and chl <italic>a</italic> concentration suggests that biological processes are important but additional data such as bacterial biomass and production is not available to support this view. A comprehensive understanding of the mechanisms, conditions and (micro)environments facilitating CaCO<sub>3</sub> precipitation in pelagic ecosystems is also lacking and precludes a more detailed interpretation of the results. The processes producing these particles are in any case different from the calcification processes currently considered to be of major importance, i.e. coccolithophores, foraminifera and pteropods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Fabry1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Schiebel1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Ziveri1">[7]</xref>, the environmental factors that regulate their production remains elusive and the subject calls for further studies.</p>
      <p>Estimates of marine particulate CaCO<sub>3</sub> concentration will include the particles we have described here when based on chemical analysis of particulate material collected by filtration. They may however not be included in estimates based on optical and remote sensing techniques presuming the particles to have optical properties that are different from those considered when calibrating and verifying these techniques. If the production of the particles takes place in the bulk water phase they are presumably also included in current estimates of calcification based on <sup>14</sup>C–CO<sub>2</sub> or <sup>45</sup>Ca incorporation, but if the production is closely coupled to interfaces they may add to current production estimates. The flux of CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles from surface waters to the deep ocean, and hence their role in ocean carbon cycle, depends on sedimentation and dissolution rates. The sedimentation rate of the pure calcium particles we have observed will, due to a higher density, presumably be higher than the sedimentation rate of similarly sized calcifying organisms like coccolithophores and foraminifera (&lt;5− &gt;100 µm) which in addition to calcite contains significant amounts of organic material. The crystal structure of the particles, aragonite being more soluble than calcite <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Gangst1">[30]</xref>, and the absence of a protective organic coating <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Paasche1">[21]</xref> as for coccoliths and foraminifera tests, will influence the depth the particles may reach before they dissolve. Observations of similar particles in marine sediment samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Mller1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Duguid1">[31]</xref> calls for cautious interpretation but may suggest that particles produced in surface waters reach the seafloor at some depth and hence contribute to the export of carbon from surface waters. Moreover, bacterial calcification may provide an additional explanation for the discrepancy between coccolith-CaCO<sub>3</sub> and total-CaCO<sub>3</sub> flux estimates that has been noted in some sediment trap studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Broerse1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Young1">[33]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The global carbonate budget is far from resolved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Berelson1">[4]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Dunne1">[34]</xref> and balancing production, sedimentation and dissolution processes on the global scale does therefore not exclude the possibility for significant additional sources of CaCO<sub>3</sub> in ocean surface waters. The novel CaCO<sub>3</sub> particles described and counted in this study amount to 21±28% (Mean±SD) of the total concentration of particulate calcium. Our estimates are crude but in concert with the ubiquitous distribution of the particles it suggests nonetheless that they may be of quantitative significance in the global carbonate budget. Calcium precipitation associated with bacterial activity appears to be a common process which also has been related to carbonate sediment formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Vasconcelos1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Castanier1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-SanchezRoman1">[36]</xref>. Understanding the geological record of calcareous rocks and sediments is based on knowledge about the organisms considered to be the main producers of calcium carbonate (coccolithophores and foraminifera), including their occurrence, abundance, size, habitat requirements etc. If bacteria have been an additional quantitatively significant source of calcium carbonate in marine ecosystems it may call for a reexamination to affirm the current interpretation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s001" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Map showing sampling positions in The Norwegian Sea.</bold> Station 649, 654, 658 and 664 are from the Gimsøy transect. Station 677, 668 and 667 are from the Svinøy transect. The positions of the sampling stations are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s010">Table S1</xref>.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s002" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>X-ray spectrum of a marine calcium carbonate particle.</bold> X-ray spectrum of a pure calcium carbonate particle containing only carbon, oxygen and calcium. The peak at 2.12 keV is gold from the AuPd sputter coating of the samples. Non-pure calcium carbonate particles contained significant and variable amounts of Mg (K-line at 1.25 keV), Fe (K-line at 6.4keV and L-line at 0.7 keV) and Si (K-line at 1.74 keV).</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s003" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s003" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>X-ray mapping of marine particles.</bold> X-ray mapping of particles collected at 15 m depth in Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B, on November 23, 2010. Ca containing particles labelled red (left panel) and Si containing particles labelled green (right panel). Comparing the X-ray mappings with the greyscale image (centre) shows that some particles contain Ca and no Si and <italic>vice versa</italic>. Some amorphous particles contain both Ca and Si. The images demonstrate the difficulty of recognizing calcium carbonate particles by morphology alone.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s004" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Hydrography and chl </bold><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold> profiles from Raunefjorden.</bold> Isopleth plots of temperature, salinity, density and chl <italic>a</italic> concentration in Raunefjorden, a coastal sampling station south of Bergen, Norway, during the sampling program 2009–2010.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s005" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s005" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Scanning electron microscope images of calcium carbonate particles from The Norwegian Sea.</bold> Particles collected at A) Station 658, 50 m depth. B) Station 677, 100 m depth. C) Station 658. 5 m depth, D) Close up of the particle shown in C. For positions of sampling stations see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s001">Fig. S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s010">Table S1</xref>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s006" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Hydrography, chl </bold><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold> and particulate Ca in the the Norwegian Sea.</bold> Depths profiles from the Norwegian Sea, November 3.-8. 2010 showing water density (black line), salinity (blue line), temperature (red line), chl <italic>a</italic> concentration (green line) and particulate Ca concentration (black dots, error bar shows SEM, n = 3). The bottom is marked with a dotted line when different from the X-axis. For positions of sampling stations see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s001">Fig. S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0047887.s010">Table S1</xref>.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s007" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s007" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Scanning electron microscope images of calcium carbonate particles.</bold> A and B) Particles from 1 m depth in The Mediterranean Sea, Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B. C) Particle from 5 m depth in Kings Bay (Svalbard).</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s008" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s008" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S8</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Hydrography, chl </bold><bold><italic>a</italic></bold><bold> and particulate Ca in the Mediterranean Sea.</bold> Depths profile from Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B (43°41.10′N–7°18.94′E on November 23. 2010 showing water density (black line), salinity (blue line), temperature (red line), chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence (green line) and particulate Ca concentration (black dots, error bar shows SEM, n = 3–4). CTD and chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence data, obtained with a Seabird SBE 25, was provided by Service d’Observation en Milieu Littoral, INSU-CNRS, Point B, and by Service d’Observation de la Rade de Villefranche.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s009" mimetype="image/tiff" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s009" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Figure S9</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Scanning electron microscope images of calcium carbonate particles in sediment core samples.</bold> Sediment core samples were collected at 840 m depth on the Norwegian continental margin. The particles were sub sampled at ca 9 cm depth in the sediment cores, a stratum dated to 1953. Note the flat surface of the particle in A. For details on cores see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0047887-Sejrup1">[20]</xref>.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material id="pone.0047887.s010" mimetype="application/pdf" orientation="portrait" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0047887.s010" xlink:type="simple">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
            <bold>Table of sampling times and positions in The Norwegian Sea, R/V G.O. Sars, Cruise no 2010115.</bold>
          </p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>Tomas Sørlie is thanked for help with sampling CTD data from Raunefjorden. Hilde Kristiansen, Henrik Søiland and the crew at R/V G.O. Sars are thanked for sampling and CTD data from The Norwegian Sea. Ornella Passafiume and Marie-Emmanuelle Kerros are thanked for help with sampling and CTD data from Bay Villefranche sur Mer, Point B. Hans Petter Sejrup and Hilde Kjennbakken are thanked for providing access to and help with sampling of the sediments cores.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Fabry1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabry</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seibel</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feely</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Impacts of ocean acidification on marine fauna and ecosystem processes</article-title>. <source>ICES J Mar Sci</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Ilyina1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilyina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeebe</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maier-Reimer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Early detection of ocean acidification effects on marine calcification</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>GB1008</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2008GB003278" xlink:type="simple">10.1029/2008GB003278</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Houghton1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Balancing the Global Carbon Budget</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Earth Planet Sci</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Berelson1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berelson</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Najjar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feely</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Relating estimates of CaCO<sub>3</sub> production, export, and dissolution in the water column to measurements of CaCO<sub>3</sub> rain into sediment traps and dissolution on the sea floor: A revised global carbonate budget</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>GB1024</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2006GB002803" xlink:type="simple">10.1029/2006GB002803</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Tucker1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tucker ME, Wright VP, Dickson JAD (1990) Carbonate Sedimentology. Oxford: Blackwell Sci. Ltd. 482 p.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Schiebel1">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiebel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Planktic foraminiferal sedimentation and the marine calcite budget. Global Biogeochem</article-title>. <source>Cycles</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage> <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2001GB001459" xlink:type="simple">10.1029/2001GB001459</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Ziveri1">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziveri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Bernardi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baumannd</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mortyn</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sinking of coccolith carbonate and potential contribution to organic carbon ballasting in the deep ocean</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res II</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>675</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Robbins1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwelder</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Biochemical and ultrastructural evidence for the origin of whitings: A biologically induced calcium carbonate precipitation mechanism</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Thompson1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultze-Lam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Des Marais</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Whiting events: Biogenic origin due to the photosynthetic activity of cyanobacterial picoplankton. Lirmol</article-title>. <source>Oceanogr</source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Ehrlich1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ehrlich HL, Newman DK (2009) Geomicrobiology, 5th ed. Ch. 9 Microbial Formation and Degradation of Carbonates. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press/Taylor &amp; Francis Group. 157–190.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Vasconcelos1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernasconi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grujic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Microbial mediation as a possible mechanism for natural dolomite formation at low temperatures</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>377</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Zavarzin1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavarzin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Microbial geochemical calcium cycle</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Decho1">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Decho</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Overview of biopolymer-induced mineralization: What goes on in biofilms?</article-title> <source>Ecol Eng</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Drew1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>1913</year>) <article-title>On the Precipitation of Calcium Carbonate in the Sea by Marine Bacteria, and on the Action of Denitrifying Bacteria in Tropical and Temperate Seas</article-title>. <source>J Mar Biol Ass UK (New Series)</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0025315400071526" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0025315400071526</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Lipman1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name> (<year>1929</year>) <article-title>Further Studies on Marine Bacteria with Special Reference to the Drew Hypothesis on CaCO<sub>3</sub> Precipitation in the Sea. Carnegie Inst Wash Publ 391</article-title>. <source>Papers from Tortugas Laboratory</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Bavendamm1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bavendamm</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>1932</year>) <article-title>Die mikrobiologische Kalkfällung in der tropischen See</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Greenfield1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name> (<year>1963</year>) <article-title>Metabolism and concentration of calcium and magnesium and precipitation of calcium carbonate by a marine bacterium</article-title>. <source>Ann NY Acad Sci</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Morita1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Calcite precipitation by marine bacteria</article-title>. <source>Geomicrobiol J</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Novitsky1">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Novitsky</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Calcium-carbonate precipitation by marine-bacteria</article-title>. <source>Geomicrobiol J</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Sejrup1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sejrup HP, Haflidason H, Andrews JT (2011) A Holocene North Atlantic SST record and regional climate variability. Quat Sci Rev doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.quascirev.2011.07.025" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.quascirev.2011.07.025</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Paasche1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paasche</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A review of the coccolithophorid <italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic> (Prymnesiophyceae), with particular reference to growth, coccolith formation, and calcification-photosynthesis interactions</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Krumbein1">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krumbein</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Precipitation of aragonite on surface of marine bacteria</article-title>. <source>Naturwissenschaften</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Mller1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaschke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Origin of deep sea neat lime in black sea</article-title>. <source>Naturwissenschaften</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Liu1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Oriented Vaterite CaCO<sub>3</sub> Tablet-Like Arrays Mineralized at Air/Water Interface through Cooperative Regulation of Polypeptide and Double Hydrophilic Block Copolymer</article-title>. <source>J Phys Chem C</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>9632</fpage>–<lpage>9636</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Tourney1">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tourney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ngwenya</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bacterial extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) mediate CaCO<sub>3</sub> morphology and polymorphism</article-title>. <source>Chem Geol</source> <volume>262</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Kahle1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahle</surname><given-names>CFJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Proposed origin of aragonite Bahaman and some Pleistocene marine ooids involving bacteria, nannobacteria(?), and biofilms</article-title>. <source>Carbonate Evaporite</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Douglas1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Mineral formation by bacteria in natural microbial communities</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microb Ecol</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Ercole1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ercole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cacchio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botta</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Centi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bacterially induced mineralization of calcium carbonate: The role of exopolysaccharides and capsular polysaccharides</article-title>. <source>Microsc Microanal</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Cunliffe1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunliffe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The sea-surface microlayer is a gelatinous biofilm</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Gangst1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gangstø</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gehlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bopp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aumont</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Modeling the marine aragonite cycle: changes under rising carbon dioxide and its role in shallow water CaCO<sub>3</sub> dissolution</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1057</fpage>–<lpage>1072</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Duguid1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duguid</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kyser</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rankey</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Microbes and ooids</article-title>. <source>J Sediment Res</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>236</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Broerse1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broerse</surname><given-names>ATC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziveri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Hinte</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honjo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Coccolithophore export production, species composition, and coccolith-CaCO<sub>3</sub> fuxes in the NE Atlantic (34<sup>o</sup>N 21<sup>o</sup>W and 48<sup>o</sup>N 21<sup>o</sup>W)</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res II</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1877</fpage>–<lpage>1905</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Young1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ziveri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Calculation of coccolith volume and its use in calibration of carbonate flux estimates</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res II</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1679</fpage>–<lpage>1700</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Dunne1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gnanadesikan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A synthesis of global particle export from the surface ocean and cycling through the ocean interior and on the seafloor, Global Biogeochem Cycles</article-title>. <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>GB4006</fpage> <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2006GB002907" xlink:type="simple">10.1029/2006GB002907</ext-link></comment>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-Castanier1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castanier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Métayer-Levrel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perthuisot</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Ca-carbonates precipitation and limestone genesis - the microbiogeologist point of view</article-title>. <source>Sediment Geol</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0047887-SanchezRoman1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Roman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Aerobic microbial dolomite at the nanometer scale: Implications for the geologic record</article-title>. <source>Geology</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>879</fpage>–<lpage>882</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>