<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
<title>
The complete genome sequence of the algal symbiont <i>Dinoroseobacter shibae</i>: a hitchhiker's guide to life in the sea
</title>
<description>
<p><i>Dinoroseobacter shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup>, a member of the globally important marine <i>Roseobacter</i> clade, comprises symbionts of cosmopolitan marine microalgae, including toxic dinoflagellates. Its annotated 4 417 868 bp genome sequence revealed a possible advantage of this symbiosis for the algal host. <i>D. shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup> is able to synthesize the vitamins B<span>1</span> and B<span>12</span> for which its host is auxotrophic. Two pathways for the <i>de novo</i> synthesis of vitamin B<span>12</span> are present, one requiring oxygen and the other an oxygen-independent pathway. The <i>de novo</i> synthesis of vitamin B<span>12</span> was confirmed to be functional, and <i>D. shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup> was shown to provide the growth-limiting vitamins B<span>1</span> and B<span>12</span> to its dinoflagellate host. The <i>Roseobacter</i> clade has been considered to comprise obligate aerobic bacteria. However, <i>D. shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup> is able to grow anaerobically using the alternative electron acceptors nitrate and dimethylsulfoxide; it has the arginine deiminase survival fermentation pathway and a complex oxygen-dependent Fnr (fumarate and nitrate reduction) regulon. Many of these traits are shared with other members of the <i>Roseobacter</i> clade. <i>D. shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup> has five plasmids, showing examples for vertical recruitment of chromosomal genes (<i>thiC</i>) and horizontal gene transfer (<i>cox</i> genes, gene cluster of 47 kb) possibly by conjugation (<i>vir</i> gene cluster). The long-range (80%) synteny between two sister plasmids provides insights into the emergence of novel plasmids. <i>D. shibae</i> DFL12<sup>T</sup> shows the most complex viral defense system of all <i>Rhodobacterales</i> sequenced to date.</p>
</description>
</abstract>
