<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-26603</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Iron Limitation Modulates Ocean Acidification Effects on Southern Ocean Phytoplankton Communities</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Effects of Fe Limitation &amp; OA on SO Phytoplankton</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>Clara J. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>Christel S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"><sup>¤</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>Christopher D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tortell</surname><given-names>Philippe D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>Björn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trimborn</surname><given-names>Scarlett</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Alfred Wegener Institute Helmholtz Centre for Polar and Marine Research, Bremerhaven, Germany</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>University of Technology Sydney, Plant Functional Biology and Climate Chance Cluster, New South Wales, Australia</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thuesen</surname><given-names>Erik V.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>The Evergreen State College, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">Clara.Hoppe@awi.de</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CJMH ST BR CH PDT. Performed the experiments: CJMH ST CDP. Analyzed the data: CJMH ST CH CDP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CJMH ST BR CH PDT CDP. Wrote the paper: CJMH ST BR CH PDT. Wrote the revised manuscript: CJMH ST BR CH PDT. Wrote the response to the reviewers: CJMH ST BR CH PDT.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff"><label>¤</label><p>Current address: University of Geneva, Institute F. A. Forel, Versoix, Switzerland</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<elocation-id>e79890</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Hoppe et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The potential interactive effects of iron (Fe) limitation and Ocean Acidification in the Southern Ocean (SO) are largely unknown. Here we present results of a long-term incubation experiment investigating the combined effects of CO<sub>2</sub> and Fe availability on natural phytoplankton assemblages from the Weddell Sea, Antarctica. Active Chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence measurements revealed that we successfully cultured phytoplankton under both Fe-depleted and Fe-enriched conditions. Fe treatments had significant effects on photosynthetic efficiency (F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>; 0.3 for Fe-depleted and 0.5 for Fe-enriched conditions), non-photochemical quenching (NPQ), and relative electron transport rates (rETR). pCO<sub>2</sub> treatments significantly affected NPQ and rETR, but had no effect on F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>. Under Fe limitation, increased pCO<sub>2</sub> had no influence on C fixation whereas under Fe enrichment, primary production increased with increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> levels. These CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent changes in productivity under Fe-enriched conditions were accompanied by a pronounced taxonomic shift from weakly to heavily silicified diatoms (i.e. from <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> sp. to <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic> sp.). Under Fe-depleted conditions, this functional shift was absent and thinly silicified species dominated all pCO<sub>2</sub> treatments (<italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> sp. and <italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp. for low and high pCO<sub>2</sub>, respectively). Our results suggest that Ocean Acidification could increase primary productivity and the abundance of heavily silicified, fast sinking diatoms in Fe-enriched areas, both potentially leading to a stimulation of the biological pump. Over much of the SO, however, Fe limitation could restrict this possible CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization effect.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>S.T. was funded by the German Science Foundation (DFG; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dfg.de" xlink:type="simple">www.dfg.de</ext-link>), project TR 899/2. B.R. and C.J.M.H. were funded by the European Research Council (ERC; erc.europa.eu) under the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013), ERC grant agreement no. 205150. C.H. was funded by the Australian Research Council (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arc.gov.au" xlink:type="simple">www.arc.gov.au</ext-link>; DP1092892) and a UTS Chancellor Fellowship (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uts.edu.au" xlink:type="simple">www.uts.edu.au</ext-link>). P.D.T. was funded by an Alexander von Humboldt research fellowship (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.humboldt-foundation.de" xlink:type="simple">http://www.humboldt-foundation.de</ext-link>)and grants from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca" xlink:type="simple">www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The Southern Ocean (SO) exerts a disproportionate control on the global carbon cycle over glacial-interglacial timescales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Moore1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sigman1">[2]</xref> and contributes significantly to the oceanic sequestration of anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-LeQur1">[3]</xref>. Besides abiotic drivers such as ocean circulation and sea-ice cover, biological carbon uptake and drawdown also control the air-sea-flux of CO<sub>2</sub> in the SO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Moore1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sigman1">[2]</xref>. These biological processes are mediated by phytoplankton communities, dominated mainly by silicifying diatoms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sakshaug1">[4]</xref>.</p>
<p>The surface waters of the SO are rich in major nutrients such as nitrate and phosphate, but in vast areas of this region primary production is limited by low iron (Fe) availability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Martin1">[5]</xref>. Both laboratory and <italic>in-situ</italic> fertilisation experiments have demonstrated that the growth of SO phytoplankton is strongly enhanced by the addition of Fe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Timmermans1">[6]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-deBaar1">[7]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Smetacek1">[8]</xref>. As Fe is a key nutrient for biochemical pathways including photosynthesis and nitrate assimilation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Behrenfeld1">[9]</xref>, limiting Fe concentrations lead to decreased photochemical efficiencies and photosynthetic rates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Greene1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Strzepek1">[11]</xref>. One important source of iron in open-ocean waters is the melting of sea-ice, which causes seasonal and localized phytoplankton blooms and strong vertical particle fluxes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Fischer1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Lizotte1">[13]</xref>. These factors make the marginal sea-ice zone a biogeochemically important region of the SO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Fischer1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>The effects of seawater carbonate chemistry on SO phytoplankton have received increasing attention over recent years. Laboratory studies suggest that Antarctic phytoplankton can be growth-limited by CO<sub>2</sub> supply under present-day CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Riebesell1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>. Field data from continental shelf waters of the Ross Sea have demonstrated CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent changes in primary productivity and phytoplankton assemblages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Feng1">[17]</xref>. In these prior studies, phytoplankton assemblages were not demonstrably Fe-limited (e.g. high F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Feng1">[17]</xref>), making the extrapolation of results to the open SO waters difficult. Recently, pH-dependent shifts in Fe speciation have been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Shi1">[18]</xref>, suggesting a strong potential for ocean acidification (OA) to reduce Fe bioavailability as seen in experiments with Arctic phytoplankton assemblages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie1">[19]</xref>.</p>
<p>Given the Fe-limited status of much of the SO, there is a great need to investigate combined effects of OA and Fe limitation in this region. Here we present results from a CO<sub>2</sub>-Fe-incubation experiment (190, 390 and 800 μatm pCO<sub>2</sub> under Fe-enriched and Fe-depleted conditions) using an open ocean phytoplankton assemblage from the Weddell Sea, an important region for SO primary productivity. The aim of this study was to investigate the interactive effects of OA and Fe availability on species composition, primary production, as well as iron uptake and photophysiology of Fe-limited phytoplankton assemblages.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Experimental Setup</title>
<p>A ship-board incubation experiment was designed using a CO<sub>2</sub>-Fe-matrix-approach to examine potential interactive effects between CO<sub>2</sub> and Fe availability on SO phytoplankton communities. A natural phytoplankton assemblage from the Weddell Sea (66°50′S, 0°W) was sampled during mid Dec. 2010 on the <italic>RV Polarstern</italic> ANT-XXVII/2 cruise. The permission for field work according to the Antarctic Treaty was issued by the Umweltbundesamt (Germany). Seawater was collected from 30 m depth using a “torpedo fish” towed outside the ship's wake <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-deJong1">[20]</xref>. To eliminate large grazers, we filtered seawater through an acid-cleaned 200 µm mesh. Water containing the natural phytoplankton community was transferred into acid-cleaned 4L polycarbonate bottles and incubated in growth chambers at 3±1°C with a constant daylight irradiance of 40±5 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> (Master TL-D 18W daylight lamps, Philips, adjusted by neutral density screens). The applied irradiance was based on several light measurements in the SO at the sampling depth (data by Mitchell; e.g. DOI: 10.1594/PANGAEA.132802). To provide sufficient time for changes in the phytoplankton assemblages to occur and achieve ecologically relevant information, experiments lasted between 18 and 30 days depending on experimental treatment (18–20 days in case of Fe-enriched and 27–30 days in case of Fe-depleted treatments). In order to prevent significant changes in chemical conditions due to phytoplankton growth, incubations were diluted with 0.2 µm filtered seawater when nitrate concentrations were about 10 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>. Dilution water was obtained from the initial sampling location and filtered through acid-cleaned 0.2 µm filter cartridges (AcroPak 1500, PALL). Experiments were run with triplicate treatments of two Fe levels (Fe-enriched and Fe-depleted; see below) and 3 pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (190, 390 and 800 μatm).</p>
<p>Tubing, bubbling systems, reservoir carboys, incubation bottles and other equipment were acid-cleaned prior to the cruise using trace metal-clean techniques: After a 2-day Citranox detergent bath and subsequent rinsing steps with Milli-Q (MQ, Millipore), equipment was kept in acid (5N HCl for polyethylene and 1N HCl for polycarbonate materials) for 7 days, followed by 7 rinses with MQ. Equipment was kept triple-bagged during storage and experiments. Incubation bottles were stored under acidified conditions (addition of 500 µL 10N suprapure quarz destilled HCl, Carl Roth, in 500 mL MQ) and rinsed twice with seawater prior to the start of the experiment.</p>
<p>In order to mimic different pCO<sub>2</sub> conditions, the incubation bottles were continuously sparged with air of different CO<sub>2</sub> partial pressures (190, 390 and 800 μatm) delivered through sterile 0.2 um air-filters (Midisart 2000, Sartorius stedim). Gas mixtures were generated using a gas flow controller (CGM 2000 MCZ Umwelttechnik), in which CO<sub>2</sub>-free air (&lt;1 ppmv CO<sub>2</sub>; Dominick Hunter) was mixed with pure CO<sub>2</sub> (Air Liquide Deutschland). The CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the mixed gas was regularly monitored with a non-dispersive infrared analyzer system (LI6252, LI-COR Biosciences) calibrated with CO<sub>2</sub>-free air and purchased gas mixtures of 150±10 and 1000±20 ppmv CO<sub>2</sub> (Air Liquide Deutschland).</p>
<p>To promote phytoplankton growth, 1 nM Fe (FeCl<sub>3</sub>, ICP-MS standard, TraceCERT, Fluka) was added to the Fe-enriched treatments. In the Fe-depleted treatments, 10 nM of the hydroxamate siderophore desferrioxamine B (DFB, Sigma) was added to bind and thereby reduce the bioavailable Fe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Maldonado1">[22]</xref>. No additional macronutrients were added to the incubation bottles. Abiotic control bottles, used to assess changes in Fe chemistry, contained filtered seawater (0.2 µm) exposed to each treatment condition over the duration of the experiment.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Chemical parameters</title>
<p>Nutrients were determined colorimetrically on-board with a Technicon TRAACS 800 Auto-analyzer on a daily basis over the course of the experiments, following procedures improved after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Grasshoff1">[23]</xref>. Samples for total alkalinity (TA) were 0.6 µm-filtered (glass fibre filters, GF/F, Whatman), fixed with 0.03% HgCl<sub>2</sub> and stored in 150 mL borosilicate bottles at 4°C. TA was estimated at the Alfred Wegener Institute (Germany) from duplicate potentiometric titration <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Brewer1">[24]</xref> using a TitroLine alpha plus (Schott Instruments). The calculated TA values were corrected for systematic errors based on measurements of certified reference materials (CRMs provided by Prof. A. Dickson, Scripps, USA; batch #111; reproducibility ±5 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>). Dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) samples were filtered through 0.2 µm cellulose-acetate filters (Sartorius stedim), fixed with 0.03% HgCl<sub>2</sub> and stored in 5 mL gas-tight borosilicate bottles at 4°C. Also in the home laboratory, DIC was measured colourimetrically in triplicate with a QuAAtro autoanalyzer (Seal) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Stoll1">[25]</xref>. The analyser was calibrated with NaHCO<sub>3</sub> solutions (with a salinity of 35, achieved by addition of NaCl) with concentrations ranging from 1800 to 2300 µmol DIC kg<sup>−1</sup>. CRMs were used for corrections of errors in instrument performance (e.g. baseline drift). Seawater pH was measured potentiometrically on the NBS scale (pH<sub>NBS</sub>; overall uncertainty 0.02 units) with a two-point calibrated glass reference electrode (IOline, Schott Instruments). Values for pH were reported on the pH<sub>total</sub> scale for better comparability with other datasets. Following suggestions by Hoppe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hoppe1">[26]</xref>, seawater carbonate chemistry (including pCO<sub>2</sub>) was calculated based on TA and pH using CO<sub>2</sub>SYS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Pierrot1">[27]</xref>. The dissociation constants of carbonic acid of Mehrbach et al. (refit by Dickson and Millero) were used for calculations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Mehrbach1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Dickson1">[29]</xref>. Dissociation constants for HSO<sub>4</sub> were taken from Dickson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Dickson2">[30]</xref>. Iron chemistry was analyzed using the competitive ligand exchange adsorptive cathodic stripping voltammetry using the ligand 2-(2-thiazolylazo)-p-cresol (TAC, 10 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Croot1">[31]</xref>). Total dissolved (&lt;0.2 um) Fe concentrations were analyzed following a 45 min UV-photo-oxidation step (acid washed quartz tubes closed with Teflon lids) and concentrations were determined in triplicate using standard additions of a freshly made FeCl<sub>3</sub> standard (ICP-MS standard, TraceCERT, Fluka, 1–4 nM).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Biological Parameters</title>
<p>To determine the taxonomic compositions at the end of the experiment, duplicate aliquots of 200 mL unfiltered seawater were preserved with both hexamine-buffered formalin solution (2% final concentration) and Lugols (1% final concentration). Preserved samples were stored at 4°C in the dark until further analysis by inverted light microscopy (Axiovert 200, Zeiss). Additionally, species dominating the final communities were identified using scanning electron microscopy (Philips XL30) according to taxonomic literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tomas1">[32]</xref>. Average biovolume of the dominant species was calculated based on representative cell size measurements <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hillebrand1">[33]</xref>. Values were in good agreement with the MAREDAT database <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Leblanc1">[34]</xref>. For analysis of particulate organic carbon (POC), cells were collected onto precombusted GF/F-filters (15 h, 500°C), which were subsequently stored at −20°C and dried for &gt;12 h at 60°C prior to sample analysis. Analysis was performed using an Automated Nitrogen Carbon Analyser mass spectrometer system (ANCA-SL 20-20, SerCon Ltd.). Samples for determination of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> (Chl <italic>a</italic>) concentration were filtered onto 0.45 µm cellulose acetate filters (Sartorius stedim) and stored at −20°C until analysis onboard. Chl <italic>a</italic> was subsequently extracted in 10 mL 90% acetone (overnight in darkness, at 4°C) and concentrations determined on a fluorometer (10-000 R, Turner Designs), using an acidification step to determine phaeopigments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Knap1">[35]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Physiological assays</title>
<p>Primary production of the final phytoplankton assemblages was determined in 100 mL incubations after addition of a 10 µCi (0.37 MBq) spike of NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (PerkinElmer, 53.1 mCi mmol<sup>−1</sup>). From the incubations, 0.5 mL aliquots were immediately removed and mixed with 10 mL of scintillation cocktail (Ultima Gold AB, PerkinElmer) to determine the total amount of added NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub>. For blank determination, samples were filtered and acidified immediately after <sup>14</sup>C spikes. After 24 h of incubation under acclimation light intensity, samples were filtered onto GF/F-filters, acidified with 6N HCl and left to degas overnight. Filters were then transferred into scintillation vials, to which 10 mL of scintillation cocktail was added. After ≥2 h, the samples were measured on a ship-board liquid scintillation counter (Tri-Carb 2900TR, PerkinElmer), using automatic quench correction and a maximum counting time of 5 minutes.</p>
<p>Maximum Fe uptake capacity of the final phytoplankton assemblages was estimated after 2–4 h dark-acclimation in 500 mL acid-cleaned PC-bottles. In case of the Fe- treatments, cells were gently concentrated by filtration over an HCl-cleaned 2 µm membrane filter (Isopore, Millipore), rinsed and resuspended in 500 mL filtered seawater from the initial sampling location in order to dispose all DFB. From this, 50 mL were taken for Chl <italic>a</italic> measurements. Subsequently, 1 nM of <sup>55</sup>Fe (Perkin Elmer, 33.84 mCi mg<sup>−1</sup> as FeCl<sub>3</sub> in 0.5 N HCl) was added to each sample (both Fe- and -enriched). Generally, 2 mL were taken from all samples to determine the initial amount of <sup>55</sup>Fe. Subsequently, cells were exposed for at least 24 h to the acclimation light intensity. At the end of the incubation time, the sample was filtered onto GF/F-filters and rinsed 5 times with oxalate solution (gravity filtered, 2 min between rinses) and 3 times with natural seawater <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler2">[36]</xref>. Each filter was then collected in a scintillation vial, amended with 10 mL scintillation cocktail (Ultima Gold A, PerkinElmer) and mixed thoroughly (Vortex). <sup>55</sup>Fe counts per minute were estimated for each sample on the ship-board liquid scintillation counter (Tri-Carb 2900TR, PerkinElmer), and converted into disintegrations per minute considering the radioactive decay and custom quench curves. <sup>55</sup>Fe uptake was then calculated taking into account the initial <sup>55</sup>Fe concentration and the total dissolved Fe concentration (background and added). Fe uptake rates were normalized to POC using Chl <italic>a</italic>∶POC ratios from the respective treatments.</p>
<p>Photophysiological parameters were measured using a Fluorescence Induction Relaxation System (FIRe; Satlantic, Canada; 37). Samples were 1 h dark-acclimated prior to measurements to ensure that all photosystem II (PSII) reaction centers were fully oxidized and non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) was relaxed. The duration of the dark acclimation was chosen after testing different time intervals (data not shown). Samples were then exposed to a strong short pulse (Single Turnover Flash, STF), which was applied in order to cumulatively saturate PSII. Afterwards, a long saturating pulse (Multiple Turnover Flash, MTF) was applied in order to fully reduce the PSII and the plastoquinone (PQ) pool. The minimum (F<sub>0</sub>) of the STF phase and maximum (F<sub>m</sub>) fluorescence of the MTF was used to calculate the apparent maximum quantum yield of photochemistry in PSII (F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>) according to the equation (F<sub>m</sub>−F<sub>0</sub>)/F<sub>m</sub>. This parameter was calculated for all bottles on a regular basis (every 6–7 days). Values of these parameters as well as of the functional absorption cross section of PSII (σ<sub>PSII</sub> [Å<sup>2</sup> quanta<sup>−1</sup>]) were derived using the FIRePro software provided by Satlantic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Gorbunov1">[37]</xref>. Additional fluorescence measurements were performed under increasing irradiances (21, 41, 66, 88, 110 and 220 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) provided by an external actinic light source (warm white 350 mA LEDs, ILL3A003, CML Innovative Technologies). After 5 minutes acclimation to the respective light level, the light-acclimated minimum (F<sub>q</sub>′) and maximum (F<sub>m</sub>′) fluorescence were estimated. The effective quantum yield of photochemistry in open reaction centers of PSII was derived according to the equation (F<sub>m</sub>′−F<sub>q</sub>′)/F<sub>m</sub>′ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Genty1">[38]</xref>. Relative electron transport rates (rETR) were then calculated as the product of effective quantum yield and applied growth irradiance of 40 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. Using the Stern-Volmer equation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Bilger1">[39]</xref>, NPQ of Chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence under growth irradiance was calculated as F<sub>m</sub>/F<sub>q</sub>′−1. NPQ was relaxed (values &lt;0.1) at lowest light levels for all treatments (data not shown). All measurements were conducted at the growth temperature.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Statistics</title>
<p>All data is given as the mean of the replicates (<italic>n</italic> = 3) with 1 standard deviation. To test for significant differences between the treatments, Two Way Analyses of Variance (ANOVA) with additional normality tests (Shapiro-Wilk; passed for all data shown) were performed. The significance level was set to 0.05. Statistical analyses were performed with the program SigmaPlot (SysStat Software Inc).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Seawater chemistry</title>
<p>The initial carbonate system (pH: 7.93±0.01; DIC 2210±17 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>; TA: 2303±14 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>) shifted to experimental treatment levels (average pH of 8.39±0.02, 8.13±0.02, and 7.80±0.03 for the three CO<sub>2</sub> treatments) within the first 2 days of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g001">Figure 1 A</xref>). The semi-continuous dilute-batch approach led to stable seawater carbonate chemistry over the course of the experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g001">Figure 1 A</xref>). Compared to abiotic controls, drift was &lt;8% and &lt;5% for TA and DIC, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t001">Table 1</xref>). Initial seawater nutrient concentrations were 29 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup> nitrate, 76 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup> silicate and 2 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup> phosphate. Over the course of the experiment, concentrations of nitrate never fell below 7 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>, while silicate and phosphate concentrations were always above 40 and 0.8 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>, respectively. Initial Fe concentration in the water sampled for incubations was 1.12±0.15 nmol kg<sup>−1</sup>. In 0.2 µm filtered seawater (i.e. abiotic control treatments) enriched with 10 nM DFB, dissolved Fe concentrations remained 1.16±0.08 nmol kg<sup>−1</sup> until the end of the experiment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t001">Table 1</xref>), indicating that the experimental bottles remained free of Fe contamination. Dissolved Fe concentrations decreased in Fe-enriched seawater (1 nM Fe added, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0079890-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>pH and F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> over the course of the experiment.</title>
<p>Experimental conditions over the course of the experiment. A: Development of pH<sub>total</sub> (n = 3; mean ±1 s.d.) in Fe-enriched (solid circles, 190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>; solid squares, 390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>; solid triangles, 800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>) and Fe-depleted treatments (open circles, 190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>; open squares, 390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>; open triangles, 800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>). B: Development of dark-adapted F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> (n = 3; mean ±1 s.d.) in Fe-enriched (solid squares) and Fe-depleted treatments (open squares).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0079890-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Seawater chemistry.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079890-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Treatment</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Fe<sub>diss</sub></td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">DIC</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">TA</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">pH</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">pCO<sub>2</sub></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">[µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>]</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">[µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>]</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">[µmol kg<sup>−1</sup>]</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">[total]</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">[μatm]</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial seawater</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2071</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2271</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.93</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">518</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+Fe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2208</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±36</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.04</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2082</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">369</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2175</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±14</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">801</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±51</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−Fe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2209</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.28</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2096</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2219</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.09</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2155</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2241</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.74</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">813</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±11</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Parameters of the seawater carbonate chemistry were sampled at the beginning (<italic>n</italic> = 1) and the end of the experiment (<italic>n</italic> = 3; mean ±1 s.d.). Total dissolved Fe measurements in abiotic control treatments after 0.2 µm filtration as measured by voltammetry (<italic>n</italic> = 2; mean ± 1 s.d.). The decreased dissolved Fe concentration in the +Fe treatment can be attributed to precipitation/absorption of colloidal iron. pCO<sub>2</sub> was calculated from TA and pH<sub>total</sub> at 3°C and a salinity of 34 using CO<sub>2</sub>SYS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Pierrot1">[27]</xref>, using average final nutrient concentrations of 1 and 60 µmol kg<sup>−1</sup> for phosphate and silicate, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Photophysiology</title>
<p>Over the course of the experiment, we observed significant Fe-dependent differences in the apparent maximum quantum yield of PSII reaction centres (F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g001">Figure 1 B</xref>; p&lt;0.001). Average values of F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> at the end of the experiment were 0.51±0.04 and 0.32±0.03 for Fe-enriched and -depleted treatments, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>). In contrast, the pCO<sub>2</sub> treatments had no effects on F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> under either of the Fe treatments. Relative electron transfer rates from PSII (rETR) were significantly higher in Fe-enriched treatments, and also showed pCO<sub>2</sub>-dependent increases under both Fe-enriched (5.7±0.8 at low and 7.5±0.9 at high pCO<sub>2</sub>; p&lt;0.001) and Fe-depleted conditions (4.2±0.4 at low and 5.3±0.1 at high pCO<sub>2</sub>; p&lt;0.001). Significant interactive effects between Fe- and pCO<sub>2</sub>-treatments were also observed in photoprotective non-photochemical quenching (NPQ; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>; p&lt;0.001). Under Fe-limitation, NPQ decreased from 0.22±0.03 at low pCO<sub>2</sub> to 0.11±0.00 at high pCO<sub>2</sub>, while under Fe-enriched conditions, NPQ was independent of pCO<sub>2</sub> (0.06±0.01 at all pCO<sub>2</sub> levels; p&lt;0.001).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0079890-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Physiological differences between treatments.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079890-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Treatment</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Chl a∶ POC</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub></td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">σ<sub>PSII</sub></td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">NPQ</td>
<td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">rETR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+Fe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.003</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 59.57</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 162.69</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±37.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 36.89</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 166.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 59.03</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.005</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe]</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe]</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±34.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe]</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe]</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe]</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.004</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>CO2</sub> = 6.84</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±19.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>CO2</sub> = 5.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.87</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>CO2</sub> = 22.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−Fe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.012</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.894</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±21.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.136</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>CO2</sub> = 0.568</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>CO2</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±26.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F<sub>[Fe],CO2</sub> = 36.07</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.34</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 μatm CO<sub>2</sub></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.001</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±35.9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.00</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p<sub>[Fe],CO2</sub>&lt;0.001</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0.08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Final Chl a∶ POC ratios (µg∶µg) and photophysiological parameters (apparent maximum quantum yield of PSII F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub>, proportion of non-photochemical quenching, NPQ, functional absorption cross section of PSII (σ<sub>PSII</sub> [Å<sup>2</sup> quanta<sup>−1</sup>]), and relative electron transport rates from PSII, rETR) of the final communities grown under different CO<sub>2</sub> and Fe levels (n = 3; mean ±1 s.d.). Fe-depleted (−Fe) and Fe-enriched (+Fe) conditions were achieved by the addition of 10 nmol kg<sup>−1</sup> DFB and 1 nmol kg<sup>−1</sup> FeCl<sub>3</sub>, respectively. Bold <italic>p</italic> values indicate statistically significant differences between treatments (p&lt;0.05; 2-way ANOVA).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p>The ratios of Chl <italic>a</italic> to POC of the final phytoplankton assemblages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t001">Table 1</xref>) were significantly higher (p&lt;0.001) in Fe-enriched (0.023±0.003 at low and 0.017±0.004 at high pCO<sub>2</sub>) compared to Fe-depleted treatments (0.012±0.001 at low and 0.010±0.001 at high pCO<sub>2</sub>). Chl <italic>a</italic>∶POC ratios furthermore decreased significantly with increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (p = 0.012), irrespective of the Fe-status.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Fe and C uptake</title>
<p>For all pCO<sub>2</sub> levels, carbon-normalized Fe uptake capacities at the end of the experiment were 10-fold higher in Fe-depleted compared to Fe-enriched treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g002">Figure 2</xref>; p&lt;0.001), but with no significant CO<sub>2</sub> effect. Combining data across pCO<sub>2</sub> treatments, mean Fe uptake capacities were 7.50±3.35 pmol Fe (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> and 0.72±0.38 pmol Fe (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> at low and high Fe, respectively. Under Fe-enriched conditions, we observed a significant CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent increase in C-specific primary productivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g003">Figure 3</xref>; p&lt;0.001). Primary productivity increased from 4.21±0.44 nmol C (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> at low pCO<sub>2</sub> to 8.15±0.75 nmol C (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> at high pCO<sub>2</sub>. In contrast, no CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent productivity responses were observed in Fe-depleted treatments, with values of 3.62±0.38 nmol C (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> at low pCO<sub>2</sub> and 3.93±0.16 nmol C (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup> at high pCO<sub>2</sub>. Thus, there was a significant interactive effect of the CO<sub>2</sub>- and Fe-treatments on NPP (p = 0.023).</p>
<fig id="pone-0079890-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Iron uptake capacities of final phytoplankton communities.</title>
<p>Fe uptake capacities [pmol Fe (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup>] of Fe-enriched (solid bars) and -depleted (open bars) final phytoplankton communities (n = 3; mean ±1 s.d.) estimated from 24 h incubation with 1 nM <sup>55</sup>Fe as a function of pCO<sub>2</sub> [μatm]. Statistical analysis (2-way ANOVA) revealed significant differences between Fe-treatments (F = 62.217, p = &lt;0.001) but not between CO<sub>2</sub>-treatments (F = 1.205, p = 0.349).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0079890-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Net primary production of final phytoplankton communities.</title>
<p>NPP [nmol C (µmol POC)<sup>−1</sup> h<sup>−1</sup>] was estimated from <sup>14</sup>C incubations over 24 h as a function of pCO<sub>2</sub> [μatm]. Black and grey bars indicate Fe-enriched (solid bars) and -depleted treatments (open bars), respectively (n = 3; mean ± s.d.). ANOVA analysis revealed significant effects of pCO<sub>2</sub> levels as well as a significant interaction term of [Fe] and pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (F<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 0.01, p<sub>[Fe]</sub> = 0.92; F<sub>pCO2</sub> = 15.56, p<sub>pCO2</sub>&lt;0.001; F<sub>[Fe],pCO2</sub> = 5.85, p<sub>[Fe],pCO2</sub> = 0.023).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Species composition</title>
<p>We observed pronounced shifts in the diatom-dominated phytoplankton assemblages in association with the CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent changes in primary productivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>). Shifts in species composition did not lead to changes in average cell size in the different assemblages (data not shown). After Fe-enrichment, <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgiduloides</italic> was the most abundant species under low and intermediate pCO<sub>2</sub> (39±5% and 40±9%, respectively)<sub>,</sub> whereas <italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic> dominated communities under high pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (72±5%). Furthermore, <italic>Chaetoceros</italic> cf. <italic>simplex</italic> abundances increased with rising CO<sub>2</sub> (from 11±0% at low pCO<sub>2</sub> to 17±1% at high pCO<sub>2</sub>). Phytoplankton composition changes were also observed under Fe limitation, but the nature of these species shifts differed significantly from those seen under high Fe levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>). Under Fe-depleted conditions, <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgiduloides</italic> dominated the low pCO<sub>2</sub> treatment (55±16%), while <italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp. was the most prevalent species under high pCO<sub>2</sub> (78±2%).</p>
<fig id="pone-0079890-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Representative microscopy pictures of species composition of the final communities.</title>
<p>A, Fe-enriched 190 μatm (39±5% <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>, 43±4% <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic>); B, Fe-enriched 390 μatm (40±9% <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>, 42±12% <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic>); C, Fe-enriched 800 μatm (72±5% <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic>); D, Fe-depleted 190 μatm (55±16% <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>, 26±20% <italic>Synedropsis</italic>); E, Fe-depleted 390 μatm (51±15% <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>, 29±16% <italic>Synedropsis</italic>); F, Fe-depleted 800 μatm (78±2% <italic>Synedropsis</italic>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0079890-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
<title>Microscopic cell counts.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0079890-t003-3" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0079890.t003" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxonomic group</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">+Fe</td>
<td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">−Fe</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">190 μatm</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">390 μatm</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">800 μatm</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">190 μatm</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">390 μatm</td>
<td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">800 μatm</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgiduloides</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chaetoceros</italic> cf. <italic>simplex</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phaeocystis antarctica</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unidentified flagellates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choanoflagellates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ceratoneis closterium</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dinoflagellates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">±1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgidula</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fragilariopsis kerguelensis</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thalassiosira</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large <italic>Chaetoceros</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rhizosolenia</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thalassiothrix</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Guinardia</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eucampia</italic> sp.</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciliates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silicoflagellates</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Species composition of the initial community (n = 1) and at the end of the experiment (% of total cell count; n = 3; average ±1s.d.).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Confirmation of Fe limitation</title>
<p>Dissolved Fe concentrations in Fe-depleted abiotic controls remained at initial concentrations, showing that experimental manipulations and CO<sub>2</sub> bubbling resulted in no significant Fe contamination (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t001">Table 1</xref>). In Fe-enriched abiotic controls, dissolved Fe concentrations decreased over the course of the experiment. This can be attributed to precipitation and absorption of colloidal iron in the absence of significant concentrations of Fe-binding ligands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Johnson1">[40]</xref>. Fe limitation of phytoplankton in the DFB treatments was confirmed by significant differences in F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> between Fe-enriched and -depleted treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g001">Figure 1 B</xref>). F<sub>v</sub>/F<sub>m</sub> values of Fe-depleted treatments are comparable to those observed in naturally Fe-limited phytoplankton communities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Kolber1">[41]</xref>. In line with previous findings on SO phytoplankton, also other photophysiological parameters like NPQ and rETR differed significantly between Fe treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-vanOijen1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Alderkamp1">[43]</xref>). Moreover, the significantly higher Fe uptake capacity in Fe-depleted treatments likely reflects the induction of high-affinity uptake systems and/or the selection of phytoplankton communities with greater Fe affinities <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Maldonado1">[22]</xref>. All of these observations confirm Fe limitation in the Fe-depleted treatments.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>OA response under Fe-enriched conditions</title>
<p>The observed CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent increase in primary productivity under Fe-enriched conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g003">Figure 3</xref>) confirms that CO<sub>2</sub> fixation in SO phytoplankton can be limited by carbon supply under current CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Riebesell1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref>. This hypothesis is further supported by the decrease in Chl <italic>a</italic>∶POC ratios and the increase in rETRs with increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>). Similarly, Ihnken et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Ihnken1">[44]</xref> observed ETR<sub>max</sub> in Fe-sufficient <italic>Chaetoceros muelleri</italic> to increase with increasing CO<sub>2</sub>. These findings suggest that the Calvin cycle, the major sink of photosynthetic energy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Behrenfeld1">[9]</xref>, is the rate-limiting step of photosynthesis under low pCO<sub>2</sub> levels. NPQ was not affected under high pCO<sub>2</sub>, Fe-enriched conditions. Under the applied irradiance of 40 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, however, NPQ values were generally very low (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>) suggesting that there is little requirement for dissipation of light. For one of the dominant species in the Fe-enriched treatments, <italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic>, a significant induction of NPQ was only found at irradiances larger than 200 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Alderkamp1">[43]</xref>. We can therefore conclude that even when photosynthesis was carbon limited under low pCO<sub>2</sub>, the applied irradiance was too low to induce NPQ under Fe-enriched conditions and other pathways were operated as electron sinks (e.g. midstream-oxidases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Behrenfeld1">[9]</xref>).</p>
<p>The changes in physiological responses in Fe-enriched phytoplankton assemblages were accompanied by a pronounced shift in the species composition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>) from <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgiduloides</italic> under low and intermediate pCO<sub>2</sub> to <italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic> under high pCO<sub>2</sub> levels. Likely mechanisms for this floristic shift include species-specific differences in carbon acquisition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell2">[45]</xref>, as well as pH-mediated differences in cellular physiology, e.g. changes in electrochemical membrane potentials and ion transport processes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Taylor1">[46]</xref>. <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> has also been observed to dominate in bloom situations after Fe fertilization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-deBaar1">[7]</xref>, where pH increases due to biomass build-up and drawdown of CO<sub>2</sub>. This is in line with results from CO<sub>2</sub> manipulations on SO phytoplankton assemblages, which were dominated by <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> at high pH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref>. In a laboratory study under Fe-enriched conditions, growth and rETRs of <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia subcurvata</italic> were unaffected by pCO<sub>2</sub>, suggesting that this species shows little to no responses to CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>. Our field experiment suggests that <italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic>, in contrast, benefited from increased <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>. Even though information of OA responses for this species is lacking, the related <italic>Fragilariopsis kerguelensis</italic> showed enhanced rETRs with increasing <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (S. Trimborn, unpublished data). We thus speculate that <italic>F. cylindrus</italic> increased its photosynthetic activity under elevated pCO<sub>2</sub>, thereby outcompeting the otherwise faster growing <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>. Under OA, also the relative abundance of <italic>Chaetoceros</italic> sp. increased by 50% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>), which is consistent with previous findings on SO phytoplankton assemblages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref> as well as growth responses of <italic>Chaetoceros debilis</italic> to increased pCO<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4c">
<title>OA response under Fe-limitation</title>
<p>The observation that under Fe-limitation, productivity was not stimulated by increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g003">Figure 3</xref>) may indicate that Fe acts as the main limiting factor suppressing the effects of other nutrients such as inorganic carbon. Alternatively, the apparent insensitivity of primary production to OA may arise from antagonistic physiological responses to pCO<sub>2</sub> and pH.</p>
<p>Under Fe limitation, elevated pCO<sub>2</sub> significantly increased rETRs and decreased NPQ, while the functional absorption cross section was not affected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>). These results suggest a greater electron sink associated with the Calvin cycle and thus a decreased need for energy dissipation under OA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Ihnken1">[44]</xref>. It is also known that linear electron transport (LET) towards the Calvin cycle is not the sole sink for photosynthetic energy and that, depending on the ATP demand of the cells, alternative electron pathways can play an important role (<italic>e.g.</italic> Mehler reaction, MOX pathway, pseudocyclic electron flow around PSI) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Behrenfeld1">[9]</xref>. Increased pCO<sub>2</sub>, however, is known to decrease photorespiration and/or the need for carbon concentrating mechanism (CCMs), which would lead to a decrease in cellular ATP demand <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Beardall1">[47]</xref>. The observed increase in rETRs in Fe-limited cells at high pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t002">Table 2</xref>) may therefore rather be linked to higher LET rates than to alternative electron pathways. The higher LET, enabled by the enhanced CO<sub>2</sub> fixation in the Calvin cycle, could counteract the generally greater need for photoprotection under Fe limitation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-vanOijen1">[42]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Alderkamp1">[43]</xref>. This could explain the opposing CO<sub>2</sub> effects on NPQ under Fe-depleted and Fe-enriched conditions. The CO<sub>2</sub> effect, apparent in photophysiology, is potentially masked in primary production by co-occurring pH effects on Fe bioavailability. According to the observed decline in Fe bioavailability with decreasing pH <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Shi1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie1">[19]</xref>, Fe-depleted phytoplankton would experience the greatest Fe stress under high pCO<sub>2</sub>.</p>
<p>In this study, Fe-limitation was achieved by the addition of the chelator DFB. Even though DFB has been shown to form strong complexes with Fe and thereby decrease Fe availability by &gt;90% <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler2">[36]</xref>, phytoplankton can still access DFB-bound Fe to some extent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Maldonado2">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Maldonado3">[49]</xref>. Since the phytoplankton assemblages in our DFB-treatments were strongly Fe-limited (as demonstrated by photophysiology, Fe and C uptake), bioavailability of Fe must have been largely reduced. Fe bioavailability also seems to be slightly reduced with increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g002">Figure 2</xref>), as has been observed in natural phytoplankton communities (i.e. without any added chelators) and in studies using different chelators such as EDTA and DFB <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Shi1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie2">[50]</xref>. Also, Maldonado et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Maldonado3">[49]</xref> suggest that the in-situ organic Fe-complexes observed in the SO have similar bioavailability compared to DFB. Although the chemical nature of in-situ organic Fe-binding ligands is not fully resolved, hydroxamate siderophores have been reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Velasquez1">[51]</xref>. It is thus possible that at least some of the organically bound Fe exhibits a similar pH-dependent bioavailability as induced by DFB, and thus may allow for the extrapolation of our results to field situations. In order to study the bioavailability of Fe associated with in-situ Fe-binding organic ligands under OA scenarios, future experiments without added chelators should be conducted. As the nature of Fe-binding ligands remains largely unknown and can vary spatially <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler3">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Shaked1">[53]</xref>, one should address the Fe bioavailability of various compounds (e.g., humic acids, saccharids, exopolymeric substances) that were reported to affect iron biogeochemistry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler2">[36]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Laglera1">[54]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler4">[55]</xref>. Furthermore, organic ligands control the bioavailability and the physico-chemistry of trace metals in general <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler3">[52]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Gledhill1">[56]</xref>. As some of those (Co, Cd, Zn) are also essential for phytoplankton physiology (e.g. for the activity of the carbonic anhydrase) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Morel1">[57]</xref>, joint measurements of other trace metals as well as their ligands would be desirable.</p>
<p>Although primary productivity was not sensitive to OA under Fe limitation, we did observe CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent species shifts, with <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> sp. dominating under low and <italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp. under high pCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>). The low abundances of <italic>F. cylindrus</italic> in Fe-depleted treatments probably reflect the rather high sensitivity of this species towards Fe limitation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Alderkamp1">[43]</xref>, which could be due to low Fe uptake capacities observed for this species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler1">[21]</xref>. In contrast, <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> has been shown to be an efficient user of Fe under limiting concentrations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Marchetti1">[58]</xref> and sporadic Fe input events <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Coale1">[59]</xref>. Interestingly, the final proportion of <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> declined strongly with increasing pCO<sub>2</sub>, irrespectively of the Fe status (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>), suggesting that its growth rates must have been significantly lower than those of the dominant species (<italic>F. cylindrus</italic> and <italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp. under Fe-enriched and -depleted conditions, respectively). This observation is in line with a recent study on <italic>P. pseudodelicatissima</italic>, whose growth rates were not affected by OA under either Fe-deplete nor -replete conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie2">[50]</xref>. As <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> generally does not seem to benefit from increased pCO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sugie2">[50]</xref>, this study), one could expect OA to have a negative effect on the abundances of this genus under on-going climate change. At present, nothing is known about the Fe and CO<sub>2</sub> requirements of <italic>Synedropsis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hasle1">[60]</xref>. However, a possible appearance of <italic>Synedropsis</italic> in phytoplankton assemblages or incubation experiments might have been overlooked in past studies, as their delicately silicified frustules are very prone to dissolution <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Stickley1">[61]</xref> and not distinguishable from <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> by light microscopy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<p>Our results clearly demonstrate a strong difference in CO<sub>2</sub>-dependent community structure between Fe-enriched and Fe-depleted conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0079890-g004">Figure 4</xref>). To explain these shifts, more information on species-specific differences in Fe requirements, uptake, as well as allocation strategies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hassler1">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Sarthou1">[62]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Marchetti2">[63]</xref>, and inorganic carbon acquisition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Trimborn1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref> is needed for all dominant species.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4d">
<title>Biogeochemical implications</title>
<p>The findings of our study suggest that the effects of OA on primary production and community structure are strongly modulated by the prevailing Fe concentrations. Our results, and those of others <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Tortell1">[16]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Riebesell2">[64]</xref>, indicate a potential stimulation of the biological pump as a result of increased pCO<sub>2</sub> in Fe-replete regions. Under Fe enrichment and increasing pCO<sub>2</sub> levels, we observed a shift from weakly silicified <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> towards more heavily silicified <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic>. <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> remineralizes quickly in subsurface waters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Parsons1">[65]</xref>, while <italic>Fragilariopsis</italic> is a more efficient vector of carbon export <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Fischer1">[12]</xref>. Thus, enhanced primary production, in concert with potentially higher export efficiencies, could lead to a stronger downward flux of organic matter in Fe-replete areas under OA.</p>
<p>The described feedback by ‘CO<sub>2</sub>-fertilisation’, however, may not operate over the broad expanse of the Fe-limited SO. These regional differences in CO<sub>2</sub>-sensitivity might be even more pronounced in terms of carbon export efficiencies, as under Fe-depleted conditions no functional shifts in species composition were observed. Here, all assemblages were dominated by weakly silicified species such as <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> cf. <italic>turgiduloides</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Laglera1">[54]</xref> or <italic>Synedropsis</italic> sp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Hasle1">[60]</xref>. Frustules of both species are delicate and only preserved in shallow waters or under special circumstances such as large aggregation events in combination with anoxia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Stickley1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Parsons1">[65]</xref>. Irrespective of their potential for carbon export, all species dominating our incubations are ecologically important <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Stickley1">[61]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Almandoz1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Kang1">[67]</xref>. Furthermore, both <italic>F. cylindrus</italic> and <italic>P. turgiduloides</italic> are not only characteristic sea-ice algae but also dominate phytoplankton assemblages in open waters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Almandoz1">[66]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Kang1">[67]</xref>. In fact, most genera being characteristic for SO phytoplankton assemblages were present in initial and final phytoplankton assemblages (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0079890-t003">Table 3</xref>). Overall, species in the incubations resemble a mixture of typical open-ocean and sea-ice associated species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Garibotti1">[68]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Assmy1">[71]</xref>. Hence, our interpretations may not be restricted to sea-ice influenced habitats only.</p>
<p>Our results suggest that the potential ‘CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization’ effect critically depends on the availability of Fe, determining how strongly the biological pump will serve as a carbon sink in the future SO. Realistic projections of primary production and CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration thus remain difficult as long as scenarios for Fe input as well as its bioavailability to phytoplankton remain poorly constrained <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Shi1">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Boyd1">[72]</xref>. The results of this study furthermore highlight the need to assess combined effects of important environmental factors in order to understand and predict responses to single stressors such as OA. In this respect, irradiance levels should also be considered as a potentially interacting factor. Indeed, the level of energization has been shown to strongly influence the strength of phytoplankton responses to OA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0079890-Rokitta1">[73]</xref>, suggesting that also the interaction between Fe and CO<sub>2</sub> availability could be modulated by light conditions. To thoroughly assess consequences of OA, multifactorial perturbation experiments (including factors such as different Fe sources or grazing) should target physiological as well as ecological responses of SO phytoplankton assemblages.</p>
</sec></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We thank A. McMinn as well as two anonymous referees for helpful comments on this manuscript. We also thank K. Bakker for nutrient analysis, L. Norman, U. Richter, K.-U. Richter, C. Couture, and B. Müller for laboratory or field assistance. L. Wischnewski measured DIC, T. Brenneis measured TA and POC. We also thank P. Assmy, M. Montresor, and D. Sarno for help with taxonomic identifications, F. Hinz and U. Bock for SEM pictures, and the cruise leader, captain and crew of RV Polarstern during ANTXXVII/2. We gratefully thank H.W. de Baar for providing a towed fish for trace-metal clean sampling of seawater.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Moore1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The southern ocean at the Last Glacial Maximum: A strong sink for atmospheric carbon dioxide</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>475</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Sigman1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hain</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The polar ocean and glacial cycles in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>466</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-LeQur1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Quéré</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buitenhuis</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rödenbeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Impact of climate change and variability on the global oceanic sink of CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>24</volume>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Sakshaug1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakshaug</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slagstad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holm-Hansen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Factors controlling the development of phytoplankton blooms in the Antarctic Ocean - a mathematical model</article-title>. <source>Mar Chem</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Martin1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzwater</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Iron Deficiency Limits Phytoplankton Growth in Antarctic Waters</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Timmermans1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timmermans</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerringa</surname><given-names>LJA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Baar</surname><given-names>HJW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wagt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veldhuis</surname><given-names>MJW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Growth rates of large and small Southern Ocean diatoms in relation to availability of iron in natural seawater</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-deBaar1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Baar</surname><given-names>HJW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coale</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Synthesis of iron fertilization experiments: From the Iron Age in the Age of Enlightenment</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>C09S16</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Smetacek1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smetacek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strass</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assmy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Montresor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Deep carbon export from a Southern Ocean iron-fertilized diatom bloom</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>487</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Behrenfeld1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrenfeld</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Photophysiological Expressions of Iron Stress in Phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Mar Sci</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Greene1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geider</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkowski</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Effect of Iron Limitation on Photosynthesis in a Marine Diatom</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1772</fpage>–<lpage>1782</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Strzepek1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strzepek</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frew</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Iron-light interactions differ in Southern Ocean phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1182</fpage>–<lpage>1200</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Fischer1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Futterer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gersonde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honjo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ostermann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wefer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Seasonal variability of particle flux in the Weddell Sea and its relation to ice cover</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Lizotte1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lizotte</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Contributions of Sea Ice Algae to Antarctic Marine Primary Production</article-title>. <source>Am Zool</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Riebesell1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riebesell</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf-Gladrow</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smetacek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Carbon dioxide limitation of marine phytoplankton growth rates</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>361</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Trimborn1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trimborn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brenneis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity of Antarctic phytoplankton species to ocean acidification: Growth carbon aquisition, and species interaction</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1007</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Tortell1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tortell</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trimborn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> sensitivity of Southern Ocean phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>L04605</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Feng1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Handy</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DiTullio</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interactive effects of iron, irradiance and CO<sub>2</sub> on Ross Sea phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res Part 1 Oceanogr Res Pap</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>368</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Shi1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkinson</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>FMM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Effect of Ocean Acidification on Iron Availability to Marine Phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>327</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Sugie1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiyosawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Synergistic effects of pCO<sub>2</sub> and iron availability on nutrient consumption ratio of the Bering Sea phytoplankton community</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>6309</fpage>–<lpage>6321</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-deJong1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>JTM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>den Das</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bathmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>MHC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kattner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Dissolved iron at subnanomolar levels in the Southern Ocean as determined by ship-board analysis</article-title>. <source>Anal Chim Acta</source> <volume>377</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hassler1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoemann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bioavailability of organically bound Fe to model phytoplankton of the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2281</fpage>–<lpage>2296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Maldonado1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Reduction and transport of organically bound iron by <italic>Thalassiosira oceanica</italic> (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Grasshoff1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Grasshoff K, Kremling K, Ehrhardt M (1999) Methods of Seawater Analysis pp 600. Weinheim: Wiley-VCH.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Brewer1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Brewer PG, Bradshaw AL, Williams RT (1986) Measurement of total carbon dioxide and alkalinity in the North Atlantic ocean in 1981. In The Changing Carbon Cycle – A Global Analysis ed. JR Trabalka, DE Reichle, Heidelberg Berlin: Springer Verlag. 358–381 pp.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Stoll1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>MHC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nobbe</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haese</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Continous-Flow Analysis of Dissolved Inorganic Carbon Content in Seawater</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>4111</fpage>–<lpage>4116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hoppe1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>CJM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rokitta</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf-Gladrow</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Implications of observed inconsistencies in carbonate chemistry measurements for ocean acidification studies</article-title>. <source>Biogeosciences</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2401</fpage>–<lpage>2405</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Pierrot1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierrot</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DWR</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>MS Exel Program Developed for CO<sub>2</sub> System Calculations. ed. ORNL ORNL/CDIAC-105a Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Centre</article-title>. <source>US Department of Energy</source></mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Mehrbach1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrbach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Culberson</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pytkowicz</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Measurement of the apparent dissociation constants of carbonic acid in seawater at atmospheric pressure</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>907</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Dickson1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millero</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>A comparison of the equilibrium constants for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater media</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1733</fpage>–<lpage>1743</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Dickson2"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Standard potential of the reaction: AgCl(s)+½ H<sub>2</sub>(g) = Ag(s)+HCl(aq), and the standard acidity constant of the ion HSO<sub>4</sub><sup>−</sup> in synthetic seawater from 273.15 to 318.15 K</article-title>. <source>J Chem Thermodyn</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Croot1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croot</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Determination of Iron Speciation by Cathodic Stripping Voltammetry in Seawater Using the Competing Ligand 2-(2-Thiazolylazo)-p-cresol (TAC)</article-title>. <source>Electroanalysis</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Tomas1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Tomas CR, Hasle GR (1997) Identifying Marine Phytoplankton. Academic Press. 858 pp.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hillebrand1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillebrand</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dürselen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschtel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pollingher</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zohary</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Biovolume calculation for pelagic and benthic microalgae</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Leblanc1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leblanc</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arístegui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assmy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A global diatom database – abundance, biovolume and biomass in the world ocean</article-title>. <source>Earth Sys Sci Data</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Knap1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Knap A, Michaels A, Close AH, Dickson A. (1996) Protocols for the Joint Global Ocean Flux Study (JGOFS) Core Measurements. In JGOFS Report Nr. 19, UNESCO, pp. 170</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hassler2"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoemann</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>ECV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Saccharides enhance iron bioavailability to Southern Ocean phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>1076</fpage>–<lpage>8101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Gorbunov1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gorbunov M, Falkowski P (2004) Fluorescence Induction and Relaxation (FIRe) Technique and Instrumentation for Monitoring Photosynthetic Processes and Primary Production in Aquatic Ecosystems, Lawrence.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Genty1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Genty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence</article-title>. <source>BBA</source> <volume>990</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Bilger1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Björkman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Temperature dependence of violaxanthin de-epoxidation and non-photochemical fluorescence quenching in intact leaves of <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L. and <italic>Malva parviflora</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Planta</source> <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Johnson1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coale</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>What controls dissolved iron concentrations in the world ocean?</article-title> <source>Mar Chem</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Kolber1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolber</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coale</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzwateri</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Iron limitation of phytoplankton photosynthesis in the equatorial Pacific Ocean</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>371</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-vanOijen1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oijen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwe</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gieskes</surname><given-names>WWC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Baar</surname><given-names>HJW</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Effects of iron limitation on photosynthesis and carbohydrate metabolism in the Antarctic diatom <italic>Chaetoceros brevis</italic> (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Phycol</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Alderkamp1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alderkamp</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buma</surname><given-names>AGJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RJW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dijken</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The effect of iron limitation on the photophysiology of <italic>Phaeocystis antarctica</italic> (Prymnesiophyceae) and <italic>Fragilariopsis cylindrus</italic> (Bacillariophyceae) under dynamic irradiance</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Ihnken1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ihnken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beardall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Differential responses of growth and photosynthesis in the marine diatom <italic>Chaetoceros muelleri</italic> to CO<sub>2</sub> and light availability</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Tortell2"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tortell</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gueguen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strzepek</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Inorganic carbon uptake by Southern Ocean phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1266</fpage>–<lpage>1278</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Taylor1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chrachri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>A Voltage-Gated H+ Channel Underlying pH Homeostasis in Calcifying Coccolithophores</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source> <volume>9</volume>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Beardall1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beardall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The potential effects of global climate change on microalgal photosynthesis, growth and ecology</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Maldonado2"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Utilization of iron bound to strong organic ligands by plankton communities in the subarctic Pacific Ocean</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res Part 2 Top Stud Oceanogr</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>2447</fpage>–<lpage>2473</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Maldonado3"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strzepek</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Acquisition of iron bound to strong organic complexes, with different Fe binding groups and photochemical reactivities, by plankton communities in Fe-limited subantarctic waters</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cycles</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>GB4S23</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Sugie2"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Effects of pCO<sub>2</sub> and iron on the elemental composition and cell geometry of the marine diatom <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia pseudodelicatissima</italic> (Bacillariophyceae)</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Velasquez1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velasquez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibisanmi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goodlett</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Detection of hydroxamate siderophores in coastal and Sub-Antarctic waters off the South Eastern Coast of New Zealand</article-title>. <source>Mar Chem</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hassler3"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Hassler CS, Schoemann V, Boye M, Tagliabue A, Rozmarynowycz M, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2012) Iron Bioavailability in the Southern Ocean. In Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review, ed. A. R. Gibson RN, Gordon JDM, Hughes RN, 1–64. London: CRC Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Shaked1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaked</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Disassembling iron availability to phytoplankton</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Laglera1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laglera</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>CMG</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evidence for the geochemical control of iron by humic substances in seawater</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>610</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hassler4"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassler</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alasonati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mancuso Nichols</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slaveykova</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Exopolysaccharides produced by bacteria isolated from the pelagic Southern Ocean - Role in Fe binding, chemical reactivity, and bioavailability</article-title>. <source>Mar Chem</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Gledhill1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gledhill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The organic complexation of iron in the marine environment: A review</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Morel1"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>FMM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The Biogeochemical Cycles of Trace Metals in the Oceans</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>300</volume>: <fpage>944</fpage>–<lpage>947</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Marchetti1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Iron Requirements of the Pennate Diatom <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic>: Comparison of Oceanic (High-Nitrate, Low-Chlorophyll Waters) and Coastal Species</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>2092</fpage>–<lpage>2101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Coale1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coale</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buesseler</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Southern Ocean Iron Enrichment Experiment: Carbon Cycling in High- and Low-Si Waters</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>304</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Hasle1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasle</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medlin</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Syvertsen</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title><italic>Synedropsis</italic> gen. nov., a genus of araphid diatoms associated with sea ice</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Stickley1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stickley</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>St John</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koc</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Passchier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evidence for middle Eocene Arctic sea ice from diatoms and ice-rafted debris</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>460</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Sarthou1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarthou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Timmermans</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tréguer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Growth physiology and fate of diatoms in the ocean: a review</article-title>. <source>J Sea Res</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Marchetti2"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schruth</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kodner</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Comparative metatranscriptomics identifies molecular bases for the physiological responses of phytoplankton to varying iron availability</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Riebesell2"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riebesell</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bellerby</surname><given-names>RGJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Enhanced biological carbon consumption in a high CO<sub>2</sub> ocean</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>450</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Parsons1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dortch</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Sedimentological evidence of an increase in <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> (Bacillariophyceae) abundance in response to coastal eutrophication</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>–<lpage>558</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Almandoz1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almandoz</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreyra</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schloss</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dogliotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rupolo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Distribution and ecology of <italic>Pseudo-nitzschia</italic> species (Bacillariophyceae) in surface waters of the Weddell Sea (Antarctica)</article-title>. <source>Polar Biol</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>442</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Kang1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fryxell</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Phytoplankton in the Weddell Sea, Antarctica: composition, abundance and distribution in water-column assemblages of the marginal ice-edge zone during austral autumn</article-title>. <source>Mar Biol</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Garibotti1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garibotti</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vernet</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrario</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Interannual variability in the distribution of the phytoplankton standing stock across the seasonal sea-ice zone west of the Antarctic Peninsula</article-title>. <source>J Plankton Res</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>825</fpage>–<lpage>843</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Armand1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armand</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crosta</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The biogeography of major diatom taxa in Southern Ocean sediments: 1. Sea ice related species</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source> <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Crosta1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crosta</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armand</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The biogeography of major diatom taxa in Southern Ocean sediments: 2. Open ocean related species</article-title>. <source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source> <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Assmy1"><label>71</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Assmy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Henjes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smetacek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms determining species dominance in a phytoplankton bloom induced by the iron fertilization experiment EisenEx in the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>Deep-Sea Res Part 1 Oceanogr Res Pap</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Boyd1"><label>72</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellwood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The biogeochemical cycle of iron in the ocean</article-title>. <source>Nat Geosci</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0079890-Rokitta1"><label>73</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rokitta</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effects of CO<sub>2</sub> and their modulation by light in the life-cycle stages of the coccolithophore <italic>Emiliania huxleyi</italic></article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>618</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>