<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
<title>
Carbon, nitrogen and O<sub>2</sub> fluxes associated with the cyanobacterium <i>Nodularia spumigena</i> in the Baltic Sea
</title>
<description>
<p>Photosynthesis, respiration, N<span>2</span> fixation and ammonium release were studied directly in <i>Nodularia spumigena</i> during a bloom in the Baltic Sea using a combination of microsensors, stable isotope tracer experiments combined with nanoscale secondary ion mass spectrometry (nanoSIMS) and fluorometry. Cell-specific net C- and N<span>2</span>-fixation rates by <i>N. spumigena</i> were 81.6±6.7 and 11.4±0.9 fmol N per cell per h, respectively. During light, the net C:N fixation ratio was 8.0±0.8. During darkness, carbon fixation was not detectable, but N<span>2</span> fixation was 5.4±0.4 fmol N per cell per h. Net photosynthesis varied between 0.34 and 250 nmol O<span>2</span> h<sup>−1</sup> in colonies with diameters ranging between 0.13 and 5.0 mm, and it reached the theoretical upper limit set by diffusion of dissolved inorganic carbon to colonies (>1 mm). Dark respiration of the same colonies varied between 0.038 and 87 nmol O<span>2</span> h<sup>−1</sup>, and it reached the limit set by O<span>2</span> diffusion from the surrounding water to colonies (>1 mm). N<span>2</span> fixation associated with <i>N. spumigena</i> colonies (>1 mm) comprised on average 18% of the total N<span>2</span> fixation in the bulk water. Net NH<span>4</span><sup>+</sup> release in colonies equaled 8–33% of the estimated gross N<span>2</span> fixation during photosynthesis. NH<span>4</span><sup>+</sup> concentrations within light-exposed colonies, modeled from measured net NH<span>4</span><sup>+</sup> release rates, were 60-fold higher than that of the bulk. Hence, <i>N. spumigena</i> colonies comprise highly productive microenvironments and an attractive NH<span>4</span><sup>+</sup> microenvironment to be utilized by other (micro)organisms in the Baltic Sea where dissolved inorganic nitrogen is limiting growth.</p>
</description>
</abstract>
