<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
<title>
Genetic diversity of inorganic carbon uptake systems causes variation in CO<sub>2</sub> response of the cyanobacterium <i>Microcystis</i>
</title>
<description>
<p>Rising CO<span>2</span> levels may act as an important selective factor on the CO<span>2</span>-concentrating mechanism (CCM) of cyanobacteria. We investigated genetic diversity in the CCM of <i>Microcystis aeruginosa</i>, a species producing harmful cyanobacterial blooms in many lakes worldwide. All 20 investigated <i>Microcystis</i> strains contained complete genes for two CO<span>2</span> uptake systems, the ATP-dependent bicarbonate uptake system BCT1 and several carbonic anhydrases (CAs). However, 12 strains lacked either the high-flux bicarbonate transporter BicA or the high-affinity bicarbonate transporter SbtA. Both genes, <i>bicA</i> and <i>sbtA</i>, were located on the same operon, and the expression of this operon is most likely regulated by an additional LysR-type transcriptional regulator (CcmR2). Strains with only a small <i>bicA</i> fragment clustered together in the phylogenetic tree of <i>sbtAB</i>, and the <i>bicA</i> fragments were similar in strains isolated from different continents. This indicates that a common ancestor may first have lost most of its <i>bicA</i> gene and subsequently spread over the world. Growth experiments showed that strains with <i>sbtA</i> performed better at low inorganic carbon (C<span>i</span>) conditions, whereas strains with <i>bicA</i> performed better at high C<span>i</span> conditions. This offers an alternative explanation of previous competition experiments, as our results reveal that the competition at low CO<span>2</span> levels was won by a specialist with only <i>sbtA</i>, whereas a generalist with both <i>bicA</i> and <i>sbtA</i> won at high CO<span>2</span> levels. Hence, genetic and phenotypic variation in C<span>i</span> uptake systems provide <i>Microcystis</i> with the potential for microevolutionary adaptation to changing CO<span>2</span> conditions, with a selective advantage for <i>bicA</i>-containing strains in a high-CO<span>2</span> world.</p>
</description>
</abstract>
