<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
<title>
Gradients in microbial methanol uptake: productive coastal upwelling waters to oligotrophic gyres in the Atlantic Ocean
</title>
<description>
<p>Methanol biogeochemistry and its importance as a carbon source in seawater is relatively unexplored. We report the first microbial methanol carbon assimilation rates (<i>k</i>) in productive coastal upwelling waters of up to 0.117±0.002 d<sup>−1</sup> (∼10 nmol l<sup>−1 </sup>d<sup>−1</sup>). On average, coastal upwelling waters were 11 times greater than open ocean northern temperate (NT) waters, eight times greater than gyre waters and four times greater than equatorial upwelling (EU) waters; suggesting that all upwelling waters upon reaching the surface (20 m), contain a microbial population that uses a relatively high amount of carbon (0.3–10 nmol l<sup>−1 </sup>d<sup>−1</sup>), derived from methanol, to support their growth. In open ocean Atlantic regions, microbial uptake of methanol into biomass was significantly lower, ranging between 0.04–0.68 nmol l<sup>−1 </sup>d<sup>−1</sup>. Microbes in the Mauritanian coastal upwelling used up to 57% of the total methanol for assimilation of the carbon into cells, compared with an average of 12% in the EU, and 1% in NT and gyre waters. Several methylotrophic bacterial species were identified from open ocean Atlantic waters using PCR amplification of <i>mxaF</i> encoding methanol dehydrogenase, the key enzyme in bacterial methanol oxidation. These included <i>Methylophaga</i> sp., <i>Burkholderiales</i> sp., <i>Methylococcaceae</i> sp., <i>Ancylobacter aquaticus</i>, <i>Paracoccus denitrificans</i>, <i>Methylophilus methylotrophus</i>, <i>Methylobacterium oryzae</i>, <i>Hyphomicrobium</i> sp. and <i>Methylosulfonomonas methylovora</i>. Statistically significant correlations for upwelling waters between methanol uptake into cells and both chlorophyll a concentrations and methanol oxidation rates suggest that remotely sensed chlorophyll a images, in these productive areas, could be used to derive total methanol biological loss rates, a useful tool for atmospheric and marine climatically active gas modellers, and air–sea exchange scientists.</p>
</description>
</abstract>
