<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">iaa1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.145#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/iaa1/10.1038/ismej.2010.145</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{G_rdes_2010, title={Diatom-associated bacteria are required for aggregation of Thalassiosira weissflogii}, volume={5}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.145}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.145}, number={3}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Gärdes, Astrid and Iversen, Morten H and Grossart, Hans-Peter and Passow, Uta and Ullrich, Matthias S}, year={2010}, month={Sep}, pages={436–445}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Diatom-associated bacteria are required for aggregation of Thalassiosira weissflogii
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>85</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>85</offset>
        <text>Aggregation of algae, mainly diatoms, is an important process in marine systems leading to the settling of particulate organic carbon predominantly in the form of marine snow.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>261</offset>
        <text>Exudation products of phytoplankton form transparent exopolymer particles (TEP), which acts as the glue for particle aggregation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>391</offset>
        <text>Heterotrophic bacteria interacting with phytoplankton may influence TEP formation and phytoplankton aggregation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>504</offset>
        <text>This bacterial impact has not been explored in detail.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>559</offset>
        <text>We hypothesized that bacteria attaching to Thalassiosira weissflogii might interact in a yet-to-be determined manner, which could impact TEP formation and aggregate abundance.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>735</offset>
        <text>The role of individual T. weissflogii-attaching and free-living new bacterial isolates for TEP production and diatom aggregation was investigated in vitro.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>891</offset>
        <text>T. weissflogii did not aggregate in axenic culture, and striking differences in aggregation dynamics and TEP abundance were observed when diatom cultures were inoculated with either diatom-attaching or free-living bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1115</offset>
        <text>The data indicated that free-living bacteria might not influence aggregation whereas bacteria attaching to diatom cells may increase aggregate formation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1269</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, photosynthetically inactivated T. weissflogii cells did not aggregate regardless of the presence of bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1394</offset>
        <text>Comparison of aggregate formation, TEP production, aggregate sinking velocity and solid hydrated density revealed remarkable differences.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1532</offset>
        <text>Both, photosynthetically active T. weissflogii and specific diatom-attaching bacteria were required for aggregation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1649</offset>
        <text>It was concluded that interactions between heterotrophic bacteria and diatoms increased aggregate formation and particle sinking and thus may enhance the efficiency of the biological pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
