<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">iaa1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#31203#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/iaa1/10.1038/31203</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hutchins_1998, title={Iron-limited diatom growth and Si:N uptake ratios in a coastal upwelling regime}, volume={393}, ISSN={0028-0836}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/31203}, DOI={10.1038/31203}, number={6685}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Springer Nature}, author={Hutchins, David A. and Bruland, Kenneth W.}, year={1998}, month={Jun}, pages={561–564}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Iron-limited diatom growth and Si:N uptake ratios in a coastal upwelling regime
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>80</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>80</offset>
        <text>There is compelling evidence that phytoplankton growth is limited by iron availability in the subarctic Pacific, and equatorial Pacific and Southern oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>237</offset>
        <text>A lack of iron prevents the complete biological utilization of the ambient nitrate and influences phytoplankton species composition in these open-ocean 'high-nitrate, low-chlorophyll' (HNLC) regimes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>437</offset>
        <text>But the effects of iron availability on coastal primary productivity and nutrient biogeochemistry are unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>548</offset>
        <text>Here we present the results of shipboard seawater incubation experiments which demonstrate that phytoplankton are iron-limited in parts of the California coastal upwelling region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>728</offset>
        <text>As in offshore HNLC regimes, the addition of iron to these nearshore HNLC waters promotes blooms of large chain-forming diatoms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>857</offset>
        <text>The silicic acid:nitrate (Si:N) uptake ratios in control incubations are two to three times higher than those in iron incubations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>988</offset>
        <text>Diatoms stressed by a lack of iron should therefore deplete surface waters of silicic acid before nitrate, leading to a secondary silicic acid limitation of the phytoplankton community.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1174</offset>
        <text>Higher Si:cell, Si:C and Si:pigment ratios in diatoms in the control incubations suggest that iron limitation leads to more silicified, faster-sinking diatom biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1341</offset>
        <text>These results raise fundamental questions about the nature of nutrient-limitation interactions in marine ecosystems, palaeoproductivity estimates based on the sedimentary accumulation of biogenic opal, and the controls on carbon export from some of the world's most productive surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
