<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">iaa1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature05317#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/iaa1/10.1038/nature05317</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Behrenfeld_2006, title={Climate-driven trends in contemporary ocean productivity}, volume={444}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature05317}, DOI={10.1038/nature05317}, number={7120}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Springer Nature}, author={Behrenfeld, Michael J. and O’Malley, Robert T. and Siegel, David A. and McClain, Charles R. and Sarmiento, Jorge L. and Feldman, Gene C. and Milligan, Allen J. and Falkowski, Paul G. and Letelier, Ricardo M. and Boss, Emmanuel S.}, year={2006}, month={Dec}, pages={752–755}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Climate-driven trends in contemporary ocean productivity
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>57</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>57</offset>
        <text>Contributing roughly half of the biosphere's net primary production (NPP), photosynthesis by oceanic phytoplankton is a vital link in the cycling of carbon between living and inorganic stocks.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>250</offset>
        <text>Each day, more than a hundred million tons of carbon in the form of CO2 are fixed into organic material by these ubiquitous, microscopic plants of the upper ocean, and each day a similar amount of organic carbon is transferred into marine ecosystems by sinking and grazing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>524</offset>
        <text>The distribution of phytoplankton biomass and NPP is defined by the availability of light and nutrients (nitrogen, phosphate, iron).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>657</offset>
        <text>These growth-limiting factors are in turn regulated by physical processes of ocean circulation, mixed-layer dynamics, upwelling, atmospheric dust deposition, and the solar cycle.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>836</offset>
        <text>Satellite measurements of ocean colour provide a means of quantifying ocean productivity on a global scale and linking its variability to environmental factors.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>997</offset>
        <text>Here we describe global ocean NPP changes detected from space over the past decade.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1081</offset>
        <text>The period is dominated by an initial increase in NPP of 1,930 teragrams of carbon a year (Tg C yr-1), followed by a prolonged decrease averaging 190 Tg C yr-1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1242</offset>
        <text>These trends are driven by changes occurring in the expansive stratified low-latitude oceans and are tightly coupled to coincident climate variability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1394</offset>
        <text>This link between the physical environment and ocean biology functions through changes in upper-ocean temperature and stratification, which influence the availability of nutrients for phytoplankton growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1600</offset>
        <text>The observed reductions in ocean productivity during the recent post-1999 warming period provide insight on how future climate change can alter marine food webs.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
