<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">iaa1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1784#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Parmentier_2013, title={The impact of lower sea-ice extent on Arctic greenhouse-gas exchange}, volume={3}, ISSN={1758-6798}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1784}, DOI={10.1038/nclimate1784}, number={3}, journal={Nature Climate Change}, publisher={Springer Nature}, author={Parmentier, Frans-Jan W. and Christensen, Torben R. and Sørensen, Lise Lotte and Rysgaard, Søren and McGuire, A. David and Miller, Paul A. and Walker, Donald A.}, year={2013}, month={Feb}, pages={195–202}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/iaa1/10.1038/nclimate1784</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The impact of lower sea-ice extent on Arctic greenhouse-gas exchange
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>69</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>69</offset>
        <text>In September 2012, Arctic sea-ice extent plummeted to a new record low: two times lower than the 1979-2000 average.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>185</offset>
        <text>Often, record lows in sea-ice cover are hailed as an example of climate change impacts in the Arctic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>287</offset>
        <text>Less apparent, however, are the implications of reduced sea-ice cover in the Arctic Ocean for marine-atmosphere CO2 exchange.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>413</offset>
        <text>Sea-ice decline has been connected to increasing air temperatures at high latitudes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>498</offset>
        <text>Temperature is a key controlling factor in the terrestrial exchange of CO2 and methane, and therefore the greenhouse-gas balance of the Arctic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>642</offset>
        <text>Despite the large potential for feedbacks, many studies do not connect the diminishing sea-ice extent with changes in the interaction of the marine and terrestrial Arctic with the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>834</offset>
        <text>In this Review, we assess how current understanding of the Arctic Ocean and high-latitude ecosystems can be used to predict the impact of a lower sea-ice cover on Arctic greenhouse-gas exchange.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
