<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.142#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2009.142</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{G_mez_Pereira_2010, title={Distinct flavobacterial communities in contrasting water masses of the North Atlantic Ocean}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2009.142}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2009.142}, number={4}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Gómez-Pereira, Paola R and Fuchs, Bernhard M and Alonso, Cecilia and Oliver, Matthew J and van Beusekom, Justus E E and Amann, Rudolf}, year={2010}, month={Apr}, pages={472–487}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Distinct flavobacterial communities in contrasting water masses of the North Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>92</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>92</offset>
        <text>Members of the class Flavobacteria in the phylum Bacteroidetes are among the most abundant picoplankton in coastal and polar oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>225</offset>
        <text>Their diversity is high in marine waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>267</offset>
        <text>However, quantitative information about distribution patterns of flavobacterial clades is scarce.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>365</offset>
        <text>We analyzed the diversity and clade-specific abundances of individual Flavobacteria in different oceanic provinces in the North Atlantic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>509</offset>
        <text>Samples were taken along the 30degreesW meridian between the East Greenland current and the North Atlantic subtropical gyre.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>634</offset>
        <text>Comparative sequence analysis of 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) gene libraries revealed high diversity and significant spatial variability within the class Flavobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>799</offset>
        <text>Published and newly designed oligonucleotide probes were used to enumerate eleven flavobacterial clades by catalyzed reporter deposition fluorescence in situ hybridization (CARD-FISH).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>984</offset>
        <text>We found that different provinces harbor distinct flavobacterial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1062</offset>
        <text>Clade DE2 accounted for a substantial fraction of total Flavobacteria only in the Polar Biome (BPLR), whereas the VISION clades VIS1 and VIS4 significantly increased in the Arctic (ARCT) province.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1259</offset>
        <text>Members of the genus Polaribacter were the most abundant clade in all the water masses analyzed, with highest absolute numbers in BPLR and ARCT.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1404</offset>
        <text>We improved the CARD-FISH protocol to quantify the rare clades VIS2, VIS3, VIS5 and VIS6, which were present in abundances below 0.5%.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1539</offset>
        <text>They all showed pronounced regional distribution patterns.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">14</infon>
        <offset>1598</offset>
        <text>Microscopic analysis proved a specific enrichment of Flavobacteria in the phycosphere of nanophytoplankton of BPLR and ARCT.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">15</infon>
        <offset>1723</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that different marine flavobacterial clades have distinct niches and different life strategies.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
