<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep00030#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/srep00030</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Maldonado_2011, title={Silicon uptake by sponges: a twist to understanding nutrient cycling on continental margins}, volume={1}, ISSN={2045-2322}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep00030}, DOI={10.1038/srep00030}, journal={Sci. Rep.}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Maldonado, Manuel and Navarro, Laura and Grasa, Ana and Gonzalez, Alicia and Vaquerizo, Isabel}, year={2011}, month={Jul}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Silicon uptake by sponges: a twist to understanding nutrient cycling on continental margins
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>92</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>92</offset>
        <text>About 75% of extant sponge species use dissolved silicon (DSi) to build a siliceous skeleton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>186</offset>
        <text>We show that silicon (Si) uptake by sublittoral Axinella demosponges follows an enzymatic kinetics.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>286</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, maximum uptake efficiency occurs at experimental DSi concentrations two orders of magnitude higher than those in the sponge habitats, being unachievable in coastal waters of modern oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>490</offset>
        <text>Such uptake performance appears to be rooted in a former condition suitable to operate at the seemingly high DSi values characterizing the pre-Tertiary (&gt;65 mya) habitats where this sponge lineage diversified.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>700</offset>
        <text>Persistence of ancestral uptake systems causes sponges to be outcompeted by the more efficient uptake of diatoms at the low ambient DSi levels characterizing Recent oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>873</offset>
        <text>Yet, we show that sublittoral sponges consume substantial coastal DSi (0.01-0.90 mmol Si m-2 day-1) at the expenses of the primary-production circuit.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1024</offset>
        <text>Neglect of that consumption hampers accurate understanding of Si cycling on continental margins.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
