<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep02339#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/srep02339</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Shadwick_2013, title={Vulnerability of Polar Oceans to Anthropogenic Acidification: Comparison of Arctic and Antarctic Seasonal Cycles}, volume={3}, ISSN={2045-2322}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep02339}, DOI={10.1038/srep02339}, journal={Sci. Rep.}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Shadwick, E. H. and Trull, T. W. and Thomas, H. and Gibson, J. A. E.}, year={2013}, month={Aug}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Vulnerability of Polar Oceans to Anthropogenic Acidification: Comparison of Arctic and Antarctic Seasonal Cycles
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>113</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>113</offset>
        <text>Polar oceans are chemically sensitive to anthropogenic acidification due to their relatively low alkalinity and correspondingly weak carbonate buffering capacity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>276</offset>
        <text>Here, we compare unique CO2 system observations covering complete annual cycles at an Arctic (Amundsen Gulf) and Antarctic site (Prydz Bay).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>417</offset>
        <text>The Arctic site experiences greater seasonal warming (10 vs 3degreesC), and freshening (3 vs 2), has lower alkalinity (2220 vs 2320 mumol/kg), and lower summer pH (8.15 vs 8.5), than the Antarctic site.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>620</offset>
        <text>Despite a larger uptake of inorganic carbon by summer photosynthesis, the Arctic carbon system exhibits smaller seasonal changes than the more alkaline Antarctic system.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>790</offset>
        <text>In addition, the excess surface nutrients in the Antarctic may allow mitigation of acidification, via CO2 removal by enhanced summer production driven by iron inputs from glacial and sea-ice melting.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>990</offset>
        <text>These differences suggest that the Arctic system is more vulnerable to anthropogenic change due to lower alkalinity, enhanced warming, and nutrient limitation.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
