<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1265#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo1265</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Fawcett_2011, title={Assimilation of upwelled nitrate by small eukaryotes in the Sargasso Sea}, volume={4}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1265}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo1265}, number={10}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Fawcett, Sarah E. and Lomas, Michael W. and Casey, John R. and Ward, Bess B. and Sigman, Daniel M.}, year={2011}, month={Sep}, pages={717–722}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Assimilation of upwelled nitrate by small eukaryotes in the Sargasso Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>73</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>73</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton growth is potentially limited by the scarcity of biologically available forms of nitrogen such as nitrate and ammonium.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>207</offset>
        <text>In the subtropical ocean gyres, water column stratification impedes the upward flux of nitrate to surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton in these waters are assumed to rely largely on ammonium and other forms of nitrogen recycled during the breakdown of organic matter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>468</offset>
        <text>Here, we use flow cytometry to separate prokaryotic and eukaryotic phytoplankton collected from Sargasso Sea surface waters in the summers of 2008 and 2009, and to analyse their respective nitrogen isotope ratios.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>682</offset>
        <text>We show that prokaryotes have a uniformly low ratio of 15N to 14N, delta15N, consistent with their reliance on recycled nitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>812</offset>
        <text>In contrast, small eukaryotic phytoplankton, less than 30 mum in size, have a higher and more variable delta15N, with a mean value similar to that of nitrate in underlying Subtropical Mode Water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1008</offset>
        <text>For the summertime Sargasso Sea, we estimate that small eukaryotes obtain more than half of their nitrogen from upwelled nitrate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1138</offset>
        <text>In addition, our data support the view that sinking material derives largely from eukaryotic, not prokaryotic, phytoplankton biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
