<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature06267#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature06267</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Riebesell_2007, title={Enhanced biological carbon consumption in a high CO2 ocean}, volume={450}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06267}, DOI={10.1038/nature06267}, number={7169}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Riebesell, U. and Schulz, K. G. and Bellerby, R. G. J. and Botros, M. and Fritsche, P. and Meyerhöfer, M. and Neill, C. and Nondal, G. and Oschlies, A. and Wohlers, J. and et al.}, year={2007}, month={Nov}, pages={545–548}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Enhanced biological carbon consumption in a high CO2 ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>59</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>59</offset>
        <text>The oceans have absorbed nearly half of the fossil-fuel carbon dioxide (CO2) emitted into the atmosphere since pre-industrial times, causing a measurable reduction in seawater pH and carbonate saturation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>264</offset>
        <text>If CO2 emissions continue to rise at current rates, upper-ocean pH will decrease to levels lower than have existed for tens of millions of years and, critically, at a rate of change 100 times greater than at any time over this period.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>499</offset>
        <text>Recent studies have shown effects of ocean acidification on a variety of marine life forms, in particular calcifying organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>627</offset>
        <text>Consequences at the community to ecosystem level, in contrast, are largely unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>711</offset>
        <text>Here we show that dissolved inorganic carbon consumption of a natural plankton community maintained in mesocosm enclosures at initial CO2 partial pressures of 350, 700 and 1,050 muatm increases with rising CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>922</offset>
        <text>The community consumed up to 39% more dissolved inorganic carbon at increased CO2 partial pressures compared to present levels, whereas nutrient uptake remained the same.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1093</offset>
        <text>The stoichiometry of carbon to nitrogen drawdown increased from 6.0 at low CO2 to 8.0 at high CO2, thus exceeding the Redfield carbon:nitrogen ratio of 6.6 in today's ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1267</offset>
        <text>This excess carbon consumption was associated with higher loss of organic carbon from the upper layer of the stratified mesocosms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1398</offset>
        <text>If applicable to the natural environment, the observed responses have implications for a variety of marine biological and biogeochemical processes, and underscore the importance of biologically driven feedbacks in the ocean to global change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
