<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature06853#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature06853</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Merico_2008, title={Eocene/Oligocene ocean de-acidification linked to Antarctic glaciation by sea-level fall}, volume={452}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06853}, DOI={10.1038/nature06853}, number={7190}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Merico, Agostino and Tyrrell, Toby and Wilson, Paul A.}, year={2008}, month={Apr}, pages={979–982}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Eocene/Oligocene ocean de-acidification linked to Antarctic glaciation by sea-level fall
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>One of the most dramatic perturbations to the Earth system during the past 100 million years was the rapid onset of Antarctic glaciation near the Eocene/Oligocene epoch boundary (~34 million years ago).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>292</offset>
        <text>This climate transition was accompanied by a deepening of the calcite compensation depth--the ocean depth at which the rate of calcium carbonate input from surface waters equals the rate of dissolution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>495</offset>
        <text>Changes in the global carbon cycle, rather than changes in continental configuration, have recently been proposed as the most likely root cause of Antarctic glaciation, but the mechanism linking glaciation to the deepening of calcite compensation depth remains unclear.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>765</offset>
        <text>Here we use a global biogeochemical box model to test competing hypotheses put forward to explain the Eocene/Oligocene transition.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>896</offset>
        <text>We find that, of the candidate hypotheses, only shelf to deep sea carbonate partitioning is capable of explaining the observed changes in both carbon isotope composition and calcium carbonate accumulation at the sea floor.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1119</offset>
        <text>In our simulations, glacioeustatic sea-level fall associated with the growth of Antarctic ice sheets permanently reduces global calcium carbonate accumulation on the continental shelves, leading to an increase in pelagic burial via permanent deepening of the calcite compensation depth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1406</offset>
        <text>At the same time, fresh limestones are exposed to erosion, thus temporarily increasing global river inputs of dissolved carbonate and increasing seawater delta13C.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1570</offset>
        <text>Our work sheds new light on the mechanisms linking glaciation and ocean acidity change across arguably the most important climate transition of the Cenozoic era.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
