<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.21#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Peura_2012, title={Distinct and diverse anaerobic bacterial communities in boreal lakes dominated by candidate division OD1}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.21}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.21}, number={9}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Peura, Sari and Eiler, Alexander and Bertilsson, Stefan and Nykänen, Hannu and Tiirola, Marja and Jones, Roger I}, year={2012}, month={Mar}, pages={1640–1652}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.21</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Distinct and diverse anaerobic bacterial communities in boreal lakes dominated by candidate division OD1
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>105</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>105</offset>
        <text>Lakes have a central role in the carbon cycle of the boreal landscape.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>176</offset>
        <text>These systems typically stratify in summer and their hypolimnetic microbial communities influence burial of biogenic organic matter in sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>322</offset>
        <text>The composition of bacterial communities in these suboxic habitats was studied by pyrosequencing of 16S rRNA amplicons from five lakes with variable dissolved organic carbon (DOC) concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>518</offset>
        <text>Bacterioplankton communities in the hypolimnetic waters were clearly different from the surface layer with candidate division OD1, Chlorobi and Bacteroidetes as dominant community members.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>707</offset>
        <text>Several operational taxonomic units (OTUs) affiliated with candidate division OD1 were abundant and consistently present in the suboxic hypolimnion in these boreal lakes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>878</offset>
        <text>The overall representation of this group was positively correlated with DOC and methane concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>982</offset>
        <text>Network analysis of time-series data revealed contrasting temporal patterns but suggested similar ecological roles among the abundant OTUs affiliated with candidate division OD1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1161</offset>
        <text>Together, stable isotope data and taxonomic classification point to methane oxidation and autotrophic denitrification as important processes in the suboxic zone of boreal lakes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1339</offset>
        <text>Our data revealed that while hypolimnetic bacterial communities are less dynamic, they appear to be more diverse than communities from the oxic surface layer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1498</offset>
        <text>An appreciable proportion of the hypolimnetic bacteria belong to poorly described phyla.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
