<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.127#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.127</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Robidart_2011, title={Seasonal Synechococcus and Thaumarchaeal population dynamics examined with high resolution with remote in situ instrumentation}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.127}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.127}, number={3}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Robidart, Julie C and Preston, Christina M and Paerl, Ryan W and Turk, Kendra A and Mosier, Annika C and Francis, Christopher A and Scholin, Christopher A and Zehr, Jonathan P}, year={2011}, month={Oct}, pages={513–523}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Seasonal Synechococcus and Thaumarchaeal population dynamics examined with high resolution with remote in situ instrumentation
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>127</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>127</offset>
        <text>Monterey Bay, CA is an Eastern boundary upwelling system that is nitrogen limited much of the year.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>227</offset>
        <text>In order to resolve population dynamics of microorganisms important for nutrient cycling in this region, we deployed the Environmental Sample Processor with quantitative PCR assays targeting both ribosomal RNA genes and functional genes for subclades of cyanobacteria (Synechococcus) and ammonia-oxidizing Archaea (Thaumarchaeota) populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>571</offset>
        <text>Results showed a strong correlation between Thaumarchaea abundances and nitrate during the spring upwelling but not the fall sampling period.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>713</offset>
        <text>In relatively stratified fall waters, the Thaumarchaeota community reached higher numbers than in the spring, and an unexpected positive correlation with chlorophyll concentration was observed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>907</offset>
        <text>Further, we detected drops in Synechococcus abundance that occurred on short (that is, daily) time scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1014</offset>
        <text>Upwelling intensity and blooms of eukaryotic phytoplankton strongly influenced Synechococcus distributions in the spring and fall, revealing what appear to be the environmental limitations of Synechococcus populations in this region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1248</offset>
        <text>Each of these findings has implications for Monterey Bay biogeochemistry.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1322</offset>
        <text>High-resolution sampling provides a better-resolved framework within which to observe changes in the plankton community.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1443</offset>
        <text>We conclude that controls on these ecosystems change on smaller scales than are routinely assessed, and that more predictable trends will be uncovered if they are evaluated within seasonal (monthly), rather than on annual or interannual scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
