<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#416168a#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/416168a</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hoppe_2002, title={Bacterial growth and primary production along a north–south transect of the Atlantic Ocean}, volume={416}, ISSN={0028-0836}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/416168a}, DOI={10.1038/416168a}, number={6877}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hoppe, Hans-Georg and Gocke, Klaus and Koppe, Regine and Begler, Christian}, year={2002}, month={Mar}, pages={168–171}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Bacterial growth and primary production along a north-south transect of the Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>91</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>91</offset>
        <text>The oceanic carbon cycle is mainly determined by the combined activities of bacteria and phytoplankton, but the interdependence of climate, the carbon cycle and the microbes is not well understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>289</offset>
        <text>To elucidate this interdependence, we performed high-frequency sampling of sea water along a north-south transect of the Atlantic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>426</offset>
        <text>Here we report that the interaction of bacteria and phytoplankton is closely related to the meridional profile of water temperature, a variable directly dependent on climate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>601</offset>
        <text>Water temperature was positively correlated with the ratio of bacterial production to primary production, and, more strongly, with the ratio of bacterial carbon demand to primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>792</offset>
        <text>In warm latitudes (25degrees N to 30degrees S), we observed alternating patches of predominantly heterotrophic and autotrophic community metabolism.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>941</offset>
        <text>The calculated regression lines (for data north and south of the Equator) between temperature and the ratio of bacterial production to primary production give a maximum value for this ratio of 40% in the oligotrophic equatorial regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1178</offset>
        <text>Taking into account a bacterial growth efficiency of 30%, the resulting area of net heterotrophy (where the bacterial carbon demand for growth plus respiration exceeds phytoplankton carbon fixation) expands from 8degrees N (27 degreesC) to 20degrees S (23 degreesC).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1445</offset>
        <text>This suggests an output of CO2 from parts of the ocean to the atmosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
