<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.28#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.28</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Williams_2012, title={A metaproteomic assessment of winter and summer bacterioplankton from Antarctic Peninsula coastal surface waters}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.28}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.28}, number={10}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Williams, Timothy J and Long, Emilie and Evans, Flavia and DeMaere, Mathew Z and Lauro, Federico M and Raftery, Mark J and Ducklow, Hugh and Grzymski, Joseph J and Murray, Alison E and Cavicchioli, Ricardo}, year={2012}, month={Apr}, pages={1883–1900}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A metaproteomic assessment of winter and summer bacterioplankton from Antarctic Peninsula coastal surface waters
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>113</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>113</offset>
        <text>A metaproteomic survey of surface coastal waters near Palmer Station on the Antarctic Peninsula, West Antarctica, was performed, revealing marked differences in the functional capacity of summer and winter communities of bacterioplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>352</offset>
        <text>Proteins from Flavobacteria were more abundant in the summer metaproteome, whereas winter was characterized by proteins from ammonia-oxidizing Marine Group I Crenarchaeota.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>525</offset>
        <text>Proteins prevalent in both seasons were from SAR11 and Rhodobacterales clades of Alphaproteobacteria, as well as many lineages of Gammaproteobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>676</offset>
        <text>The metaproteome data were used to elucidate the main metabolic and energy generation pathways and transport processes occurring at the microbial level in each season.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>844</offset>
        <text>In summer, autotrophic carbon assimilation appears to be driven by oxygenic photoautotrophy, consistent with high light availability and intensity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>992</offset>
        <text>In contrast, during the dark polar winter, the metaproteome supported the occurrence of chemolithoautotrophy via the 3-hydroxypropionate/4-hydroxybutyrate cycle and the reverse tricarboxylic acid cycle of ammonia-oxidizing archaea and nitrite-oxidizing bacteria, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1269</offset>
        <text>Proteins involved in nitrification were also detected in the metaproteome.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1344</offset>
        <text>Taurine appears to be an important source of carbon and nitrogen for heterotrophs (especially SAR11), with transporters and enzymes for taurine uptake and degradation abundant in the metaproteome.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1541</offset>
        <text>Divergent heterotrophic strategies for Alphaproteobacteria and Flavobacteria were indicated by the metaproteome data, with Alphaproteobacteria capturing (by high-affinity transport) and processing labile solutes, and Flavobacteria expressing outer membrane receptors for particle adhesion to facilitate the exploitation of non-labile substrates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1887</offset>
        <text>TonB-dependent receptors from Gammaproteobacteria and Flavobacteria (particularly in summer) were abundant, indicating that scavenging of substrates was likely an important strategy for these clades of Southern Ocean bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>2114</offset>
        <text>This study provides the first insight into differences in functional processes occurring between summer and winter microbial communities in coastal Antarctic waters, and particularly highlights the important role that 'dark' carbon fixation has in winter.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
