<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.69#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.69</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Yau_2013, title={Metagenomic insights into strategies of carbon conservation and unusual sulfur biogeochemistry in a hypersaline Antarctic lake}, volume={7}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.69}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.69}, number={10}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Yau, Sheree and Lauro, Federico M and Williams, Timothy J and DeMaere, Matthew Z and Brown, Mark V and Rich, John and Gibson, John AE and Cavicchioli, Ricardo}, year={2013}, month={Apr}, pages={1944–1961}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Metagenomic insights into strategies of carbon conservation and unusual sulfur biogeochemistry in a hypersaline Antarctic lake
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>127</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>127</offset>
        <text>Organic Lake is a shallow, marine-derived hypersaline lake in the Vestfold Hills, Antarctica that has the highest reported concentration of dimethylsulfide (DMS) in a natural body of water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>317</offset>
        <text>To determine the composition and functional potential of the microbial community and learn about the unusual sulfur chemistry in Organic Lake, shotgun metagenomics was performed on size-fractionated samples collected along a depth profile.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>557</offset>
        <text>Eucaryal phytoflagellates were the main photosynthetic organisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>623</offset>
        <text>Bacteria were dominated by the globally distributed heterotrophic taxa Marinobacter, Roseovarius and Psychroflexus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>739</offset>
        <text>The dominance of heterotrophic degradation, coupled with low fixation potential, indicates possible net carbon loss.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>856</offset>
        <text>However, abundant marker genes for aerobic anoxygenic phototrophy, sulfur oxidation, rhodopsins and CO oxidation were also linked to the dominant heterotrophic bacteria, and indicate the use of photo- and lithoheterotrophy as mechanisms for conserving organic carbon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1124</offset>
        <text>Similarly, a high genetic potential for the recycling of nitrogen compounds likely functions to retain fixed nitrogen in the lake.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1255</offset>
        <text>Dimethylsulfoniopropionate (DMSP) lyase genes were abundant, indicating that DMSP is a significant carbon and energy source.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1380</offset>
        <text>Unlike marine environments, DMSP demethylases were less abundant, indicating that DMSP cleavage is the likely source of high DMS concentration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1524</offset>
        <text>DMSP cleavage, carbon mixotrophy (photoheterotrophy and lithoheterotrophy) and nitrogen remineralization by dominant Organic Lake bacteria are potentially important adaptations to nutrient constraints.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1726</offset>
        <text>In particular, carbon mixotrophy relieves the extent of carbon oxidation for energy production, allowing more carbon to be used for biosynthetic processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1882</offset>
        <text>The study sheds light on how the microbial community has adapted to this unique Antarctic lake environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
