<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms4107#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ncomms4107</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hendry_2014, title={Silicon isotopes indicate enhanced carbon export efficiency in the North Atlantic during deglaciation}, volume={5}, ISSN={2041-1723}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms4107}, DOI={10.1038/ncomms4107}, journal={Nature Communications}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hendry, Katharine R. and Robinson, Laura F. and McManus, Jerry F. and Hays, James D.}, year={2014}, month={Jan}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Silicon isotopes indicate enhanced carbon export efficiency in the North Atlantic during deglaciation
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>102</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>102</offset>
        <text>Today's Sargasso Sea is nutrient starved, except for episodic upwelling events caused by wind-driven winter mixing and eddies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>229</offset>
        <text>Enhanced diatom opal burial in Sargasso Sea sediments indicates that silicic acid, a limiting nutrient today, may have been more available in subsurface waters during Heinrich Stadials, millennial-scale climate perturbations of the last glacial and deglaciation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>492</offset>
        <text>Here we use the geochemistry of opal-forming organisms from different water depths to demonstrate changes in silicic acid supply and utilization during the most recent Heinrich Stadial.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>678</offset>
        <text>We suggest that during the early phase (17.5-18 ka), wind-driven upwelling replenished silicic acid to the subsurface, resulting in low Si utilization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>830</offset>
        <text>By 17 ka, stratification reduced the surface silicic acid supply leading to increased Si utilization efficiency.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>943</offset>
        <text>This abrupt shift in Si cycling would have contributed to high regional carbon export efficiency during the recent Heinrich Stadial, despite being a period of increasing atmospheric CO2.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
