<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.87#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.87</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Giebel_2010, title={Distribution of Roseobacter RCA and SAR11 lineages in the North Sea and characteristics of an abundant RCA isolate}, volume={5}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.87}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.87}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Giebel, Helge-Ansgar and Kalhoefer, Daniela and Lemke, Andreas and Thole, Sebastian and Gahl-Janssen, Renate and Simon, Meinhard and Brinkhoff, Thorsten}, year={2010}, month={Jul}, pages={8–19}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Distribution of Roseobacter RCA and SAR11 lineages in the North Sea and characteristics of an abundant RCA isolate
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>115</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>115</offset>
        <text>The Roseobacter group and SAR11 clade constitute high proportions of the marine bacterioplankton, but only scarce information exists on the abundance of distinct populations of either lineage.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>308</offset>
        <text>Therefore, we quantified the abundance of the largest cluster of the Roseobacter group, the RCA (Roseobacter clade affiliated) cluster together with the SAR11 clade by quantitative PCR in the southern and eastern North Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>532</offset>
        <text>The RCA cluster constituted up to 15 and 21% of total bacterial 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) genes in September 2005 and May 2006, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>673</offset>
        <text>At a few stations, the RCA cluster exceeded the SAR11 clade, whereas at most stations, SAR11 constituted higher fractions with maxima of 37%.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>815</offset>
        <text>In most samples, only one RCA ribotype was detected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>868</offset>
        <text>RCA abundance was positively correlated with phaeopigments, chlorophyll, dissolved and particulate organic carbon (POC), turnover rates of dissolved free amino acids (DFAAs), temperature, and negatively correlated with salinity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1097</offset>
        <text>The SAR11 clade was only correlated with POC (negatively, May) and with DFAA turnover rates (positively, September).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1214</offset>
        <text>An abundant RCA strain, 'Candidatus Planktomarina temperata', was isolated from the southern North Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1318</offset>
        <text>This strain has an identical 16S rRNA gene sequence to the dominant RCA ribotype.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1400</offset>
        <text>Detection of the pufM gene, coding for a subunit of the reaction center of bacteriochlorophyll a, indicates the potential of the isolate for aerobic anoxygenic photosynthesis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1576</offset>
        <text>Our study shows that a distinct population of the RCA cluster constitutes an abundant bacterioplankton group in a neritic sea of the temperate zone and indicates that this population has an important role during decaying phytoplankton blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
