<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2009.29#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2009.29</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{B_er_2009, title={Time- and sediment depth-related variations in bacterial diversity and community structure in subtidal sands}, volume={3}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2009.29}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2009.29}, number={7}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Böer, Simone I and Hedtkamp, Stefanie I C and van Beusekom, Justus E E and Fuhrman, Jed A and Boetius, Antje and Ramette, Alban}, year={2009}, month={Apr}, pages={780–791}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Time- and sediment depth-related variations in bacterial diversity and community structure in subtidal sands
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>109</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>109</offset>
        <text>Bacterial community structure and microbial activity were determined together with a large number of contextual environmental parameters over 2 years in subtidal sands of the German Wadden Sea in order to identify the main factors shaping microbial community structure and activity in this habitat.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>408</offset>
        <text>Seasonal changes in temperature were directly reflected in bacterial activities and total community respiration, but could not explain variations in the community structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>582</offset>
        <text>Strong sediment depth-related patterns were observed for bacterial abundances, carbon production rates and extracellular enzymatic activities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>725</offset>
        <text>Bacterial community structure also showed a clear vertical variation with higher operational taxonomic unit (OTU) numbers at 10-15 cm depth than in the top 10 cm, probably because of the decreasing disturbance by hydrodynamic forces with sediment depth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>979</offset>
        <text>The depth-related variations in bacterial community structure could be attributed to vertical changes in bacterial abundances, chlorophyll a and NO3-, indicating that spatial patterns of microbes are partially environmentally controlled.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1217</offset>
        <text>Time was the most important single factor affecting microbial community structure with an OTU replacement of up to 47% over 2 years and a contribution of 34% to the total variation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1399</offset>
        <text>A large part of this variation was not related to any environmental parameters, suggesting that temporal variations in bacterial community structure are caused by yet unknown environmental drivers and/or by stochastic events in coastal sand habitats.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1650</offset>
        <text>Principal ecosystem functions such as benthic oxygen consumption and extracellular hydrolysis of organic matter were, however, at a high level at all times, indicating functional redundancy in the microbial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
