<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.31#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.31</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Grzymski_2012, title={A metagenomic assessment of winter and summer bacterioplankton from Antarctica Peninsula coastal surface waters}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.31}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.31}, number={10}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Grzymski, Joseph J and Riesenfeld, Christian S and Williams, Timothy J and Dussaq, Alex M and Ducklow, Hugh and Erickson, Matthew and Cavicchioli, Ricardo and Murray, Alison E}, year={2012}, month={Apr}, pages={1901–1915}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A metagenomic assessment of winter and summer bacterioplankton from Antarctica Peninsula coastal surface waters
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>112</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>112</offset>
        <text>Antarctic surface oceans are well-studied during summer when irradiance levels are high, sea ice is melting and primary productivity is at a maximum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>262</offset>
        <text>Coincident with this timing, the bacterioplankton respond with significant increases in secondary productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>374</offset>
        <text>Little is known about bacterioplankton in winter when darkness and sea-ice cover inhibit photoautotrophic primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>500</offset>
        <text>We report here an environmental genomic and small subunit ribosomal RNA (SSU rRNA) analysis of winter and summer Antarctic Peninsula coastal seawater bacterioplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>668</offset>
        <text>Intense inter-seasonal differences were reflected through shifts in community composition and functional capacities encoded in winter and summer environmental genomes with significantly higher phylogenetic and functional diversity in winter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>910</offset>
        <text>In general, inferred metabolisms of summer bacterioplankton were characterized by chemoheterotrophy, photoheterotrophy and aerobic anoxygenic photosynthesis while the winter community included the capacity for bacterial and archaeal chemolithoautotrophy.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1165</offset>
        <text>Chemolithoautotrophic pathways were dominant in winter and were similar to those recently reported in global 'dark ocean' mesopelagic waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1307</offset>
        <text>If chemolithoautotrophy is widespread in the Southern Ocean in winter, this process may be a previously unaccounted carbon sink and may help account for the unexplained anomalies in surface inorganic nitrogen content.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
