<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.175#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Mayali_2011, title={High-throughput isotopic analysis of RNA microarrays to quantify microbial resource use}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.175}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.175}, number={6}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Mayali, Xavier and Weber, Peter K and Brodie, Eoin L and Mabery, Shalini and Hoeprich, Paul D and Pett-Ridge, Jennifer}, year={2011}, month={Dec}, pages={1210–1221}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.175</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>High-throughput isotopic analysis of RNA microarrays to quantify microbial resource use
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>88</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>88</offset>
        <text>Most microorganisms remain uncultivated, and typically their ecological roles must be inferred from diversity and genomic studies.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>219</offset>
        <text>To directly measure functional roles of uncultivated microbes, we developed Chip-stable isotope probing (SIP), a high-sensitivity, high-throughput SIP method performed on a phylogenetic microarray (chip).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>424</offset>
        <text>This approach consists of microbial community incubations with isotopically labeled substrates, hybridization of the extracted community rRNA to a microarray and measurement of isotope incorporation--and therefore substrate use--by secondary ion mass spectrometer imaging (NanoSIMS).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>708</offset>
        <text>Laboratory experiments demonstrated that Chip-SIP can detect isotopic enrichment of 0.5 atom % 13C and 0.1 atom % 15N, thus permitting experiments with short incubation times and low substrate concentrations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>917</offset>
        <text>We applied Chip-SIP analysis to a natural estuarine community and quantified amino acid, nucleic acid or fatty acid incorporation by 81 distinct microbial taxa, thus demonstrating that resource partitioning occurs with relatively simple organic substrates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1174</offset>
        <text>The Chip-SIP approach expands the repertoire of stable isotope-enabled methods available to microbial ecologists and provides a means to test genomics-generated hypotheses about biogeochemical function in any natural environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
