<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.69#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.69</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Alonso_S_ez_2010, title={High bicarbonate assimilation in the dark by Arctic bacteria}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.69}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.69}, number={12}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Alonso-Sáez, Laura and Galand, Pierre E and Casamayor, Emilio O and Pedrós-Alió, Carlos and Bertilsson, Stefan}, year={2010}, month={Dec}, pages={1581–1590}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>High bicarbonate assimilation in the dark by Arctic bacteria
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>61</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>61</offset>
        <text>Although both autotrophic and heterotrophic microorganisms incorporate CO2 in the dark through different metabolic pathways, this process has usually been disregarded in oxic marine environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>257</offset>
        <text>We studied the significance and mediators of dark bicarbonate assimilation in dilution cultures inoculated with winter Arctic seawater.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>393</offset>
        <text>At stationary phase, bicarbonate incorporation rates were high (0.5-2.5 mug C L-1 d-1) and correlated with rates of bacterial heterotrophic production, suggesting that most of the incorporation was due to heterotrophs.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>612</offset>
        <text>Accordingly, very few typically chemoautotrophic bacteria were detected by 16S rRNA gene cloning.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>710</offset>
        <text>The genetic analysis of the biotin carboxylase gene accC putatively involved in archaeal CO2 fixation did not yield any archaeal sequence, but amplified a variety of bacterial carboxylases involved in fatty acids biosynthesis, anaplerotic pathways and leucine catabolism.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>982</offset>
        <text>Gammaproteobacteria dominated the seawater cultures (40-70% of cell counts), followed by Betaproteobacteria and Flavobacteria as shown by catalyzed reporter deposition fluorescence in situ hybridization (CARDFISH).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1197</offset>
        <text>Both Beta- and Gammaproteobacteria were active in leucine and bicarbonate uptake, while Flavobacteria did not take up bicarbonate, as measured by microautoradiography combined with CARDFISH.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1388</offset>
        <text>Within Gammaproteobacteria, Pseudoalteromonas-Colwellia and Oleispira were very active in bicarbonate uptake (ca. 30 and 70% of active cells, respectively), while the group Arctic96B-16 did not take up bicarbonate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1603</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that, potentially, the incorporation of CO2 can be relevant for the metabolism of specific Arctic heterotrophic phylotypes, promoting the maintenance of their cell activity and/or longer survival under resource depleted conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
