<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.133#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.133</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Cavalcanti_2014, title={Physiologic and metagenomic attributes of the rhodoliths forming the largest CaCO3 bed in the South Atlantic Ocean}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.133}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.133}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Cavalcanti, Giselle S and Gregoracci, Gustavo B and dos Santos, Eidy O and Silveira, Cynthia B and Meirelles, Pedro M and Longo, Leila and Gotoh, Kazuyoshi and Nakamura, Shota and Iida, Tetsuya and Sawabe, Tomoo and et al.}, year={2014}, month={Jan}, pages={52–62}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Physiologic and metagenomic attributes of the rhodoliths forming the largest CaCO3 bed in the South Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>115</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>115</offset>
        <text>Rhodoliths are free-living coralline algae (Rhodophyta, Corallinales) that are ecologically important for the functioning of marine environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>261</offset>
        <text>They form extensive beds distributed worldwide, providing a habitat and nursery for benthic organisms and space for fisheries, and are an important source of calcium carbonate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>438</offset>
        <text>The Abrolhos Bank, off eastern Brazil, harbors the world's largest continuous rhodolith bed (of ~21 000 km2) and has one of the largest marine CaCO3 deposits (producing 25 megatons of CaCO3 per year).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>639</offset>
        <text>Nevertheless, there is a lack of information about the microbial diversity, photosynthetic potential and ecological interactions within the rhodolith holobiont.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>800</offset>
        <text>Herein, we performed an ecophysiologic and metagenomic analysis of the Abrolhos rhodoliths to understand their microbial composition and functional components.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>960</offset>
        <text>Rhodoliths contained a specific microbiome that displayed a significant enrichment in aerobic ammonia-oxidizing betaproteobacteria and dissimilative sulfate-reducing deltaproteobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1147</offset>
        <text>We also observed a significant contribution of bacterial guilds (that is, photolithoautotrophs, anaerobic heterotrophs, sulfide oxidizers, anoxygenic phototrophs and methanogens) in the rhodolith metagenome, suggested to have important roles in biomineralization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1411</offset>
        <text>The increased hits in aromatic compounds, fatty acid and secondary metabolism subsystems hint at an important chemically mediated interaction in which a functional job partition among eukaryal, archaeal and bacterial groups allows the rhodolith holobiont to thrive in the global ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1697</offset>
        <text>High rates of photosynthesis were measured for Abrolhos rhodoliths (52.16 mumol carbon m-2 s-1), allowing the entire Abrolhos rhodolith bed to produce 5.65 x 105 tons C per day.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1875</offset>
        <text>This estimate illustrates the great importance of the Abrolhos rhodolith beds for dissolved carbon production in the South Atlantic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
