<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2008.125#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Haaber_2009, title={Viral lysis of Phaeocystis pouchetii: Implications for algal population dynamics and heterotrophic C, N and P cycling}, volume={3}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2008.125}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2008.125}, number={4}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Haaber, Jakob and Middelboe, Mathias}, year={2009}, month={Apr}, pages={430–441}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2008.125</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Viral lysis of Phaeocystis pouchetii: Implications for algal population dynamics and heterotrophic C, N and P cycling
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>118</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>118</offset>
        <text>A model ecosystem with two autotrophic flagellates, Phaeocystis pouchetii and Rhodomonas salina, a virus specific to P. pouchetii (PpV) and bacteria and heterotrophic nanoflagellates was used to investigate effects of viral lysis on algal population dynamics and heterotrophic nitrogen and phosphorus mineralization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>435</offset>
        <text>Lysis of P. pouchetii by PpV had strong positive effects on bacterial and HNF abundance, and the mass balance of C, N and P suggested an efficient transfer of organic material from P. pouchetii to bacterial and HNF biomass through viral lysis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>679</offset>
        <text>At the same time, the degradation of P. pouchetii lysates was associated with significant regeneration of inorganic N and P resulting in 148 mug N l-1 and 7 mug P l-1, corresponding to 78% and 26% of lysate N and P being mineralized to NH4+ and PO43-, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>945</offset>
        <text>These results showed that the turnover of viral lysates in the microbial food web was associated with significant N and P mineralization, supporting the current view that viral lysates can be an important source of inorganic nutrients in marine systems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1199</offset>
        <text>In the presence of R. salina, the generated NH4+ supported 11% of the observed R. salina growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1296</offset>
        <text>Regrowth of virus-resistant P. pouchetii following cell lysis was observed in long-term incubations (150 days), and possibly influenced by nutrient availability and competition from R. salina.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1489</offset>
        <text>The observed impact of viral activity on autotrophic and heterotrophic processes provides direct experimental evidence for virus-driven nutrient generation and emphasizes the potential importance of the viral activity in supporting marine primary production.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
