<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.113#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.113</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Eiler_2011, title={Coherent dynamics and association networks among lake bacterioplankton taxa}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.113}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.113}, number={2}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Eiler, Alexander and Heinrich, Friederike and Bertilsson, Stefan}, year={2011}, month={Sep}, pages={330–342}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Coherent dynamics and association networks among lake bacterioplankton taxa
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>76</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>76</offset>
        <text>Bacteria have important roles in freshwater food webs and in the cycling of elements in the ecosystem.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>179</offset>
        <text>Yet specific ecological features of individual phylogenetic groups and interactions among these are largely unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>296</offset>
        <text>We used 454 pyrosequencing of 16S rRNA genes to study associations of different bacterioplankton groups to environmental characteristics and their co-occurrence patterns over an annual cycle in a dimictic lake.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>507</offset>
        <text>Clear seasonal succession of the bacterioplankton community was observed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>581</offset>
        <text>After binning of sequences into previously described and highly resolved phylogenetic groups (tribes), their temporal dynamics revealed extensive synchrony and associations with seasonal events such as ice coverage, ice-off, mixing and phytoplankton blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>839</offset>
        <text>Coupling between closely and distantly related tribes was resolved by time-dependent rank correlations, suggesting ecological coherence that was often dependent on taxonomic relatedness.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1026</offset>
        <text>Association networks with the abundant freshwater Actinobacteria and Proteobacteria in focus revealed complex interdependencies within bacterioplankton communities and contrasting linkages to environmental conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1244</offset>
        <text>Accordingly, unique ecological features can be inferred for each tribe and reveal the natural history of abundant cultured and uncultured freshwater bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
