<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.213#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.213</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Balzano_2012, title={Composition of the summer photosynthetic pico and nanoplankton communities in the Beaufort Sea assessed by T-RFLP and sequences of the 18S rRNA gene from flow cytometry sorted samples}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.213}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.213}, number={8}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Balzano, Sergio and Marie, Dominique and Gourvil, Priscillia and Vaulot, Daniel}, year={2012}, month={Jan}, pages={1480–1498}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Composition of the summer photosynthetic pico and nanoplankton communities in the Beaufort Sea assessed by T-RFLP and sequences of the 18S rRNA gene from flow cytometry sorted samples
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>184</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>184</offset>
        <text>The composition of photosynthetic pico and nanoeukaryotes was investigated in the North East Pacific and the Arctic Ocean with special emphasis on the Beaufort Sea during the MALINA cruise in summer 2009.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>389</offset>
        <text>Photosynthetic populations were sorted using flow cytometry based on their size and pigment fluorescence.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>495</offset>
        <text>Diversity of the sorted photosynthetic eukaryotes was determined using terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism analysis and cloning/sequencing of the 18S ribosomal RNA gene.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>679</offset>
        <text>Picoplankton was dominated by Mamiellophyceae, a class of small green algae previously included in the prasinophytes: in the North East Pacific, the contribution of an Arctic Micromonas ecotype increased steadily northward becoming the only taxon occurring at most stations throughout the Beaufort Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>982</offset>
        <text>In contrast, nanoplankton was more diverse: North Pacific stations were dominated by Pseudo-nitzschia sp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1088</offset>
        <text>whereas those in the Beaufort Sea were dominated by two distinct Chaetoceros species as well as by Chrysophyceae, Pelagophyceae and Chrysochromulina spp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1242</offset>
        <text>.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1244</offset>
        <text>This study confirms the importance of Arctic Micromonas within picoplankton throughout the Beaufort Sea and demonstrates that the photosynthetic picoeukaryote community in the Arctic is much less diverse than at lower latitudes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1473</offset>
        <text>Moreover, in contrast to what occurs in warmer waters, most of the key pico- and nanoplankton species found in the Beaufort Sea could be successfully established in culture.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
