<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.44#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.44</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hunter_2012, title={Macrofauna regulate heterotrophic bacterial carbon and nitrogen incorporation in low-oxygen sediments}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.44}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.44}, number={11}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hunter, William R and Veuger, Bart and Witte, Ursula}, year={2012}, month={May}, pages={2140–2151}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Macrofauna regulate heterotrophic bacterial carbon and nitrogen incorporation in low-oxygen sediments
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>102</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>102</offset>
        <text>Oxygen minimum zones (OMZs) currently impinge upon &gt;1 million km2 of sea floor and are predicted to expand with climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>230</offset>
        <text>We investigated how changes in oxygen availability, macrofaunal biomass and retention of labile organic matter (OM) regulate heterotrophic bacterial C and N incorporation in the sediments of the OMZ-impacted Indian continental margin (540-1100 m; [O2]=0.35-15 mumol l-1).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>502</offset>
        <text>In situ pulse-chase experiments traced 13C:15N-labelled phytodetritus into bulk sediment OM and hydrolysable amino acids, including the bacterial biomarker D-alanine.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>669</offset>
        <text>Where oxygen availability was lowest ([O2]=0.35 mumol l-1), metazoan macrofauna were absent and bacteria assimilated 30-90% of the labelled phytodetritus within the sediment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>844</offset>
        <text>At higher oxygen levels ([O2]=2-15 mumol l-1) the macrofaunal presence and lower phytodetritus retention with the sediment occur concomitantly, and bacterial phytodetrital incorporation was reduced and retarded.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1056</offset>
        <text>Bacterial C and N incorporation exhibited a significant negative relationship with macrofaunal biomass across the OMZ.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1175</offset>
        <text>We hypothesise that fauna-bacterial interactions significantly influence OM recycling in low-oxygen sediments and need to be considered when assessing the consequences of global change on biogeochemical cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
