<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.244#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.244</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Robidart_2014, title={Ecogenomic sensor reveals controls on N2-fixing microorganisms in the North Pacific Ocean}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.244}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.244}, number={6}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Robidart, Julie C and Church, Matthew J and Ryan, John P and Ascani, François and Wilson, Samuel T and Bombar, Deniz and Marin, Roman and Richards, Kelvin J and Karl, David M and Scholin, Christopher A and et al.}, year={2014}, month={Jun}, pages={1175–1185}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Ecogenomic sensor reveals controls on N2-fixing microorganisms in the North Pacific Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen-fixing microorganisms (diazotrophs) are keystone species that reduce atmospheric dinitrogen (N2) gas to fixed nitrogen (N), thereby accounting for much of N-based new production annually in the oligotrophic North Pacific.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>However, current approaches to study N2 fixation provide relatively limited spatiotemporal sampling resolution; hence, little is known about the ecological controls on these microorganisms or the scales over which they change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>548</offset>
        <text>In the present study, we used a drifting robotic gene sensor to obtain high-resolution data on the distributions and abundances of N2-fixing populations over small spatiotemporal scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>735</offset>
        <text>The resulting measurements demonstrate that concentrations of N2 fixers can be highly variable, changing in abundance by nearly three orders of magnitude in less than 2 days and 30 km.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>920</offset>
        <text>Concurrent shipboard measurements and long-term time-series sampling uncovered a striking and previously unrecognized correlation between phosphate, which is undergoing long-term change in the region, and N2-fixing cyanobacterial abundances.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1162</offset>
        <text>These results underscore the value of high-resolution sampling and its applications for modeling the effects of global change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
