<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.135#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Sheik_2014, title={Responses of the coastal bacterial community to viral infection of the algae Phaeocystis globosa}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.135}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.135}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Sheik, Abdul R and Brussaard, Corina P D and Lavik, Gaute and Lam, Phyllis and Musat, Niculina and Krupke, Andreas and Littmann, Sten and Strous, Marc and Kuypers, Marcel M M}, year={2014}, month={Jan}, pages={212–225}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.135</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Responses of the coastal bacterial community to viral infection of the algae Phaeocystis globosa
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>97</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>97</offset>
        <text>The release of organic material upon algal cell lyses has a key role in structuring bacterial communities and affects the cycling of biolimiting elements in the marine environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>278</offset>
        <text>Here we show that already before cell lysis the leakage or excretion of organic matter by infected yet intact algal cells shaped North Sea bacterial community composition and enhanced bacterial substrate assimilation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>496</offset>
        <text>Infected algal cultures of Phaeocystis globosa grown in coastal North Sea water contained gamma- and alphaproteobacterial phylotypes that were distinct from those in the non-infected control cultures 5 h after infection.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>717</offset>
        <text>The gammaproteobacterial population at this time mainly consisted of Alteromonas sp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>802</offset>
        <text>cells that were attached to the infected but still intact host cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>872</offset>
        <text>Nano-scale secondary-ion mass spectrometry (nanoSIMS) showed ~20% transfer of organic matter derived from the infected 13C- and 15N-labelled P. globosa cells to Alteromonas sp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1049</offset>
        <text>cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1056</offset>
        <text>Subsequent, viral lysis of P. globosa resulted in the formation of aggregates that were densely colonised by bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1175</offset>
        <text>Aggregate dissolution was observed after 2 days, which we attribute to bacteriophage-induced lysis of the attached bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1300</offset>
        <text>Isotope mass spectrometry analysis showed that 40% of the particulate 13C-organic carbon from the infected P. globosa culture was remineralized to dissolved inorganic carbon after 7 days.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1488</offset>
        <text>These findings reveal a novel role of viruses in the leakage or excretion of algal biomass upon infection, which provides an additional ecological niche for specific bacterial populations and potentially redirects carbon availability.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
