<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.161#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.161</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Nelson_2013, title={Coral and macroalgal exudates vary in neutral sugar composition and differentially enrich reef bacterioplankton lineages}, volume={7}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.161}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.161}, number={5}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Nelson, Craig E and Goldberg, Stuart J and Wegley Kelly, Linda and Haas, Andreas F and Smith, Jennifer E and Rohwer, Forest and Carlson, Craig A}, year={2013}, month={May}, pages={962–979}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Coral and macroalgal exudates vary in neutral sugar composition and differentially enrich reef bacterioplankton lineages
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>121</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>121</offset>
        <text>Increasing algal cover on tropical reefs worldwide may be maintained through feedbacks whereby algae outcompete coral by altering microbial activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>271</offset>
        <text>We hypothesized that algae and coral release compositionally distinct exudates that differentially alter bacterioplankton growth and community structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>425</offset>
        <text>We collected exudates from the dominant hermatypic coral holobiont Porites spp.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>505</offset>
        <text>and three dominant macroalgae (one each Ochrophyta, Rhodophyta and Chlorophyta) from reefs of Mo'orea, French Polynesia.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>626</offset>
        <text>We characterized exudates by measuring dissolved organic carbon (DOC) and fractional dissolved combined neutral sugars (DCNSs) and subsequently tracked bacterioplankton responses to each exudate over 48 h, assessing cellular growth, DOC/DCNS utilization and changes in taxonomic composition (via 16S rRNA amplicon pyrosequencing).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>957</offset>
        <text>Fleshy macroalgal exudates were enriched in the DCNS components fucose (Ochrophyta) and galactose (Rhodophyta); coral and calcareous algal exudates were enriched in total DCNS but in the same component proportions as ambient seawater.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1192</offset>
        <text>Rates of bacterioplankton growth and DOC utilization were significantly higher in algal exudate treatments than in coral exudate and control incubations with each community selectively removing different DCNS components.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1413</offset>
        <text>Coral exudates engendered the smallest shift in overall bacterioplankton community structure, maintained high diversity and enriched taxa from Alphaproteobacteria lineages containing cultured representatives with relatively few virulence factors (VFs) (Hyphomonadaceae and Erythrobacteraceae).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1707</offset>
        <text>In contrast, macroalgal exudates selected for less diverse communities heavily enriched in copiotrophic Gammaproteobacteria lineages containing cultured pathogens with increased VFs (Vibrionaceae and Pseudoalteromonadaceae).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1932</offset>
        <text>Our results demonstrate that algal exudates are enriched in DCNS components, foster rapid growth of bacterioplankton and select for bacterial populations with more potential VFs than coral exudates.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
