<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1916#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Capone_2013, title={Microbial biogeochemistry of coastal upwelling regimes in a changing ocean}, volume={6}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1916}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo1916}, number={9}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Capone, Douglas G. and Hutchins, David A.}, year={2013}, month={Aug}, pages={711–717}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo1916</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Microbial biogeochemistry of coastal upwelling regimes in a changing ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>75</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>75</offset>
        <text>Coastal upwelling regimes associated with eastern boundary currents are the most biologically productive ecosystems in the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>205</offset>
        <text>As a result, they play a disproportionately important role in the microbially mediated cycling of marine nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>These systems are characterized by strong natural variations in carbon dioxide concentrations, pH, nutrient levels and sea surface temperatures on both seasonal and interannual timescales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>510</offset>
        <text>Despite this natural variability, changes resulting from human activities are starting to emerge.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>608</offset>
        <text>Carbon dioxide derived from fossil fuel combustion is adding to the acidity of upwelled low-pH waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>711</offset>
        <text>Low-oxygen waters associated with coastal upwelling systems are growing in their extent and intensity as a result of a rise in upper ocean temperatures and productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>881</offset>
        <text>And nutrient inputs to the coastal ocean continue to grow.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>940</offset>
        <text>Coastal upwelling systems may prove more resilient to changes resulting from human activities than other ocean ecosystems because of their ability to function under extremely variable conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1136</offset>
        <text>Nevertheless, shifts in primary production, fish yields, nitrogen gain and loss, and the flux of climate-relevant gases could result from the perturbation of these highly productive and dynamic ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
