<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nrmicro2831#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Pointing_2012, title={Microbial colonization and controls in dryland systems}, volume={10}, ISSN={1740-1534}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrmicro2831}, DOI={10.1038/nrmicro2831}, number={8}, journal={Nature Reviews Microbiology}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Pointing, Stephen B. and Belnap, Jayne}, year={2012}, month={Jul}, pages={551–562}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nrmicro2831</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Microbial colonization and controls in dryland systems
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>55</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>55</offset>
        <text>Drylands constitute the most extensive terrestrial biome, covering more than one-third of the Earth's continental surface.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>178</offset>
        <text>In these environments, stress limits animal and plant life, so life forms that can survive desiccation and then resume growth following subsequent wetting assume the foremost role in ecosystem processes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>382</offset>
        <text>In this Review, we describe how these organisms assemble in unique soil- and rock-surface communities to form a thin veneer of mostly microbial biomass across hot and cold deserts.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>563</offset>
        <text>These communities mediate inputs and outputs of gases, nutrients and water from desert surfaces, as well as regulating weathering, soil stability, and hydrological and nutrient cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>748</offset>
        <text>The magnitude of regional and global desert-related environmental impacts is affected by these surface communities; here, we also discuss the challenges for incorporating the consideration of these communities and their effects into the management of dryland resources.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
