<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.50#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.50</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Ward_2011, title={Linking phytoplankton community composition to seasonal changes in f-ratio}, volume={5}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.50}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.50}, number={11}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Ward, Bess B and Rees, Andrew P and Somerfield, Paul J and Joint, Ian}, year={2011}, month={May}, pages={1759–1770}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Linking phytoplankton community composition to seasonal changes in f-ratio
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>75</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>75</offset>
        <text>Seasonal changes in nitrogen assimilation have been studied in the western English Channel by sampling at approximately weekly intervals for 12 months.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>227</offset>
        <text>Nitrate concentrations showed strong seasonal variations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>285</offset>
        <text>Available nitrogen in the winter was dominated by nitrate but this was close to limit of detection from May to September, after the spring phytoplankton bloom.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>445</offset>
        <text>The 15N uptake experiments showed that nitrate was the nitrogen source for the spring phytoplankton bloom but regenerated nitrogen supported phytoplankton productivity throughout the summer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>636</offset>
        <text>The average annual f-ratio was 0.35, which demonstrated the importance of ammonia regeneration in this dynamic temperate region.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>765</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen uptake rate measurements were related to the phytoplankton responsible by assessing the relative abundance of nitrate reductase (NR) genes and the expression of NR among eukaryotic phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>970</offset>
        <text>Strong signals were detected from NR sequences that are not associated with known phylotypes or cultures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1076</offset>
        <text>NR sequences from the diatom Phaeodactylum tricornutum were highly represented in gene abundance and expression, and were significantly correlated with f-ratio.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1237</offset>
        <text>The results demonstrate that analysis of functional genes provides additional information, and may be able to give better indications of which phytoplankton species are responsible for the observed seasonal changes in f-ratio than microscopic phytoplankton identification.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
