<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.107#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.107</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Gilbert_2011, title={Defining seasonal marine microbial community dynamics}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.107}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.107}, number={2}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Gilbert, Jack A and Steele, Joshua A and Caporaso, J Gregory and Steinbrück, Lars and Reeder, Jens and Temperton, Ben and Huse, Susan and McHardy, Alice C and Knight, Rob and Joint, Ian and et al.}, year={2011}, month={Aug}, pages={298–308}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Defining seasonal marine microbial community dynamics
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>54</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>54</offset>
        <text>Here we describe, the longest microbial time-series analyzed to date using high-resolution 16S rRNA tag pyrosequencing of samples taken monthly over 6 years at a temperate marine coastal site off Plymouth, UK.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>264</offset>
        <text>Data treatment effected the estimation of community richness over a 6-year period, whereby 8794 operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were identified using single-linkage preclustering and 21 130 OTUs were identified by denoising the data.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>501</offset>
        <text>The Alphaproteobacteria were the most abundant Class, and the most frequently recorded OTUs were members of the Rickettsiales (SAR 11) and Rhodobacteriales.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>658</offset>
        <text>This near-surface ocean bacterial community showed strong repeatable seasonal patterns, which were defined by winter peaks in diversity across all years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>812</offset>
        <text>Environmental variables explained far more variation in seasonally predictable bacteria than did data on protists or metazoan biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>947</offset>
        <text>Change in day length alone explains &gt;65% of the variance in community diversity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1028</offset>
        <text>The results suggested that seasonal changes in environmental variables are more important than trophic interactions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1145</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, microbial association network analysis showed that correlations in abundance were stronger within bacterial taxa rather than between bacteria and eukaryotes, or between bacteria and environmental variables.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
