<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.182#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Halm_2011, title={Heterotrophic organisms dominate nitrogen fixation in the South Pacific Gyre}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.182}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.182}, number={6}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Halm, Hannah and Lam, Phyllis and Ferdelman, Timothy G and Lavik, Gaute and Dittmar, Thorsten and LaRoche, Julie and D’Hondt, Steven and Kuypers, Marcel MM}, year={2011}, month={Dec}, pages={1238–1249}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.182</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Heterotrophic organisms dominate nitrogen fixation in the South Pacific Gyre
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>77</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>77</offset>
        <text>Oceanic subtropical gyres are considered biological deserts because of the extremely low availability of nutrients and thus minimum productivities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>225</offset>
        <text>The major source of nutrient nitrogen in these ecosystems is N2-fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>299</offset>
        <text>The South Pacific Gyre (SPG) is the largest ocean gyre in the world, but measurements of N2-fixation therein, or identification of microorganisms involved, are scarce.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>467</offset>
        <text>In the 2006/2007 austral summer, we investigated nitrogen and carbon assimilation at 11 stations throughout the SPG.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>584</offset>
        <text>In the ultra-oligotrophic waters of the SPG, the chlorophyll maxima reached as deep as 200 m. Surface primary production seemed limited by nitrogen, as dissolved inorganic carbon uptake was stimulated upon additions of 15N-labeled ammonium and leucine in our incubation experiments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>867</offset>
        <text>N2-fixation was detectable throughout the upper 200 m at most stations, with rates ranging from 0.001 to 0.19 nM N h-1.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>987</offset>
        <text>N2-fixation in the SPG may account for the production of 8-20% of global oceanic new nitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1082</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, comparable 15N2-fixation rates were measured under light and dark conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1175</offset>
        <text>Meanwhile, phylogenetic analyses for the functional gene biomarker nifH and its transcripts could not detect any common photoautotrophic diazotrophs, such as, Trichodesmium, but a prevalence of gamma-proteobacteria and the unicellular photoheterotrophic Group A cyanobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1452</offset>
        <text>The dominance of these likely heterotrophic diazotrophs was further verified by quantitative PCR.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1550</offset>
        <text>Hence, our combined results show that the ultra-oligotrophic SPG harbors a hitherto unknown heterotrophic diazotrophic community, clearly distinct from other oceanic gyres previously visited.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
