<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.201#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.201</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Allen_2012, title={Influence of nutrients and currents on the genomic composition of microbes across an upwelling mosaic}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.201}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.201}, number={7}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Allen, Lisa Zeigler and Allen, Eric E and Badger, Jonathan H and McCrow, John P and Paulsen, Ian T and Elbourne, Liam DH and Thiagarajan, Mathangi and Rusch, Doug B and Nealson, Kenneth H and Williamson, Shannon J and et al.}, year={2012}, month={Jan}, pages={1403–1414}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Influence of nutrients and currents on the genomic composition of microbes across an upwelling mosaic
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>102</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>102</offset>
        <text>Metagenomic data sets were generated from samples collected along a coastal to open ocean transect between Southern California Bight and California Current waters during a seasonal upwelling event, providing an opportunity to examine the impact of episodic pulses of cold nutrient-rich water into surface ocean microbial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>436</offset>
        <text>The data set consists of ~5.8 million predicted proteins across seven sites, from three different size classes: 0.1-0.8, 0.8-3.0 and 3.0-200.0 mum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>584</offset>
        <text>Taxonomic and metabolic analyses suggest that sequences from the 0.1-0.8 mum size class correlated with their position along the upwelling mosaic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>731</offset>
        <text>However, taxonomic profiles of bacteria from the larger size classes (0.8-200 mum) were less constrained by habitat and characterized by an increase in Cyanobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Flavobacteria and double-stranded DNA viral sequences.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>968</offset>
        <text>Functional annotation of transmembrane proteins indicate that sites comprised of organisms with small genomes have an enrichment of transporters with substrate specificities for amino acids, iron and cadmium, whereas organisms with larger genomes have a higher percentage of transporters for ammonium and potassium.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1284</offset>
        <text>Eukaryotic-type glutamine synthetase (GS) II proteins were identified and taxonomically classified as viral, most closely related to the GSII in Mimivirus, suggesting that marine Mimivirus-like particles may have played a role in the transfer of GSII gene functions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1551</offset>
        <text>Additionally, a Planctomycete bloom was sampled from one upwelling site providing a rare opportunity to assess the genomic composition of a marine Planctomycete population.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1724</offset>
        <text>The significant correlations observed between genomic properties, community structure and nutrient availability provide insights into habitat-driven dynamics among oligotrophic versus upwelled marine waters adjoining each other spatially.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
