<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.79#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.79</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Joint_2010, title={Will ocean acidification affect marine microbes?}, volume={5}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.79}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.79}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Joint, Ian and Doney, Scott C and Karl, David M}, year={2010}, month={Jun}, pages={1–7}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Will ocean acidification affect marine microbes?
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>49</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>49</offset>
        <text>The pH of the surface ocean is changing as a result of increases in atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2), and there are concerns about potential impacts of lower pH and associated alterations in seawater carbonate chemistry on the biogeochemical processes in the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>315</offset>
        <text>However, it is important to place these changes within the context of pH in the present-day ocean, which is not constant; it varies systematically with season, depth and along productivity gradients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>515</offset>
        <text>Yet this natural variability in pH has rarely been considered in assessments of the effect of ocean acidification on marine microbes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>649</offset>
        <text>Surface pH can change as a consequence of microbial utilization and production of carbon dioxide, and to a lesser extent other microbially mediated processes such as nitrification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>830</offset>
        <text>Useful comparisons can be made with microbes in other aquatic environments that readily accommodate very large and rapid pH change.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>962</offset>
        <text>For example, in many freshwater lakes, pH changes that are orders of magnitude greater than those projected for the twenty second century oceans can occur over periods of hours.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1140</offset>
        <text>Marine and freshwater assemblages have always experienced variable pH conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1222</offset>
        <text>Therefore, an appropriate null hypothesis may be, until evidence is obtained to the contrary, that major biogeochemical processes in the oceans other than calcification will not be fundamentally different under future higher CO2/lower pH conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
