<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo2139#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo2139</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Ma_2014, title={Carbon sequestration during the Palaeocene–Eocene Thermal Maximum by an efficient biological pump}, volume={7}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo2139}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo2139}, number={5}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Ma, Zhongwu and Gray, Ellen and Thomas, Ellen and Murphy, Brandon and Zachos, James and Paytan, Adina}, year={2014}, month={Apr}, pages={382–388}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Carbon sequestration during the Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum by an efficient biological pump
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>98</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>98</offset>
        <text>A perturbation of the carbon cycle and biosphere, linked to globally increased temperatures about 55.9 million years ago, characterized the Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>273</offset>
        <text>Its effect on global oceanic productivity is controversial.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>333</offset>
        <text>Here we present records of marine barite accumulation rates that show distinct peaks during this time interval, suggesting a general increase in export productivity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>499</offset>
        <text>We propose that changes in marine ecosystems, resulting from high atmospheric partial pressure of CO2 and ocean acidification, led to enhanced carbon export from the photic zone to depth, thereby increasing the efficiency of the biological pump.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>745</offset>
        <text>Higher seawater temperatures at that time increased bacterial activity and organic matter regeneration.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>849</offset>
        <text>Through this process much of the sinking particulate organic matter was probably converted to dissolved inorganic and organic carbon.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>983</offset>
        <text>We estimate that an annual carbon export flux out of the euphotic zone and into the deep ocean waters could have amounted to about 15 Gt during the Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1166</offset>
        <text>About 0.4% of this carbon is expected to have entered the refractory dissolved organic pool, where it could be sequestered from the atmosphere for tens of thousands of years.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1341</offset>
        <text>Our estimates are consistent with the amount of carbon redistribution expected for the recovery from the Palaeocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
