<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#24352#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/24352</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Price_1998, volume={396}, ISSN={0028-0836}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/24352}, DOI={10.1038/24352}, number={6708}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Price, N. M. and Maranger, R. and Bird, D. F.}, year={1998}, month={Nov}, pages={248–251}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Iron acquisition by photosynthetic marine phytoplankton from ingested bacteria
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>79</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>79</offset>
        <text>Iron is unique among biologically essential trace metals in having a higher particulate than dissolved concentration in ocean surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>221</offset>
        <text>Uptake of dissolved iron is generally considered to be the norm for phytoplankton, as even the smallest iron-bearing particles are unavailable for transport into cells,.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>391</offset>
        <text>But the oceanic dissolved fraction is so small, and the particulate fraction so inert, that phytoplankton production is limited by a dearth of available iron in some regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>566</offset>
        <text>Here we use incubation experiments to show that Ochromonas sp., a common photosynthetic flagellate from the Pacific Ocean, can obtain iron directly in particulate form, by ingesting bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>758</offset>
        <text>Iron acquisition is highly efficient; Ochromonas assimilates 30% of the ingested ration, acquiring a high intracellular iron concentration and maintaining a significantly faster growth rate than when iron is provided in the dissolved phase.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>999</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton capable of such phagotrophy (so-called mixotrophic species) may thus be able to assimilate iron in both particulate and dissolved forms in the ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1163</offset>
        <text>Moreover, when iron availability is limited, the iron 'cost' of growth is diminished because Ochromonas derives a greater fraction of its energy from the bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1327</offset>
        <text>Analysis of standing stocks and clearance rates of plankton in the equatorial Pacific shows that the iron flux through mixotrophic flagellates can amount to 35-58% of the total Fe uptake by the entire autotrophic community.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1551</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that the phagotrophic ingestion of bacteria may be an effective adaptive strategy for photosynthetic organisms to obtain iron for growth in iron-limited regions of the sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
