<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature07268#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature07268</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Danovaro_2008, title={Major viral impact on the functioning of benthic deep-sea ecosystems}, volume={454}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature07268}, DOI={10.1038/nature07268}, number={7208}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Danovaro, Roberto and Dell’Anno, Antonio and Corinaldesi, Cinzia and Magagnini, Mirko and Noble, Rachel and Tamburini, Christian and Weinbauer, Markus}, year={2008}, month={Aug}, pages={1084–1087}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Major viral impact on the functioning of benthic deep-sea ecosystems
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>69</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>69</offset>
        <text>Viruses are the most abundant biological organisms of the world's oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>143</offset>
        <text>Viral infections are a substantial source of mortality in a range of organisms--including autotrophic and heterotrophic plankton--but their impact on the deep ocean and benthic biosphere is completely unknown.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>353</offset>
        <text>Here we report that viral production in deep-sea benthic ecosystems worldwide is extremely high, and that viral infections are responsible for the abatement of 80% of prokaryotic heterotrophic production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>558</offset>
        <text>Virus-induced prokaryotic mortality increases with increasing water depth, and beneath a depth of 1,000 m nearly all of the prokaryotic heterotrophic production is transformed into organic detritus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>757</offset>
        <text>The viral shunt, releasing on a global scale ~0.37-0.63 gigatonnes of carbon per year, is an essential source of labile organic detritus in the deep-sea ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>922</offset>
        <text>This process sustains a high prokaryotic biomass and provides an important contribution to prokaryotic metabolism, allowing the system to cope with the severe organic resource limitation of deep-sea ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1133</offset>
        <text>Our results indicate that viruses have an important role in global biogeochemical cycles, in deep-sea metabolism and the overall functioning of the largest ecosystem of our biosphere.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
