<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo101#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Battin_2008, title={Biophysical controls on organic carbon fluxes in fluvial networks}, volume={1}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo101}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo101}, number={2}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Battin, Tom J. and Kaplan, Louis A. and Findlay, Stuart and Hopkinson, Charles S. and Marti, Eugenia and Packman, Aaron I. and Newbold, J. Denis and Sabater, Francesc}, year={2008}, month={Jan}, pages={95–100}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo101</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Biophysical controls on organic carbon fluxes in fluvial networks
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>66</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>66</offset>
        <text>Metabolism of terrestrial organic carbon in freshwater ecosystems is responsible for a large amount of carbon dioxide outgassing to the atmosphere, in contradiction to the conventional wisdom that terrestrial organic carbon is recalcitrant and contributes little to the support of aquatic metabolism.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>367</offset>
        <text>Here, we combine recent findings from geophysics, microbial ecology and organic geochemistry to show geophysical opportunity and microbial capacity to enhance the net heterotrophy in streams, rivers and estuaries.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>581</offset>
        <text>We identify hydrological storage and retention zones that extend the residence time of organic carbon during downstream transport as geophysical opportunities for microorganisms to develop as attached biofilms or suspended aggregates, and to metabolize organic carbon for energy and growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>872</offset>
        <text>We consider fluvial networks as meta-ecosystems to include the acclimation of microbial communities in downstream ecosystems that enable them to exploit energy that escapes from upstream ecosystems, thereby increasing the overall energy utilization at the network level.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
