<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.56#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.56</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hartmann_2014, title={Efficient CO2 fixation by surface Prochlorococcus in the Atlantic Ocean}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.56}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.56}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hartmann, Manuela and Gomez-Pereira, Paola and Grob, Carolina and Ostrowski, Martin and Scanlan, David J and Zubkov, Mikhail V}, year={2014}, month={Apr}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Efficient CO2 fixation by surface Prochlorococcus in the Atlantic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>72</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>72</offset>
        <text>Nearly half of the Earth's surface is covered by the ocean populated by the most abundant photosynthetic organisms on the planet--Prochlorococcus cyanobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>233</offset>
        <text>However, in the oligotrophic open ocean, the majority of their cells in the top half of the photic layer have levels of photosynthetic pigmentation barely detectable by flow cytometry, suggesting low efficiency of CO2 fixation compared with other phytoplankton living in the same waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>521</offset>
        <text>To test the latter assumption, CO2 fixation rates of flow cytometrically sorted 14C-labelled phytoplankton cells were directly compared in surface waters of the open Atlantic Ocean (30degreesS to 30degreesN).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>730</offset>
        <text>CO2 fixation rates of Prochlorococcus are at least 1.5-2.0 times higher than CO2 fixation rates of the smallest plastidic protists and Synechococcus cyanobacteria when normalised to photosynthetic pigmentation assessed using cellular red autofluorescence.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>986</offset>
        <text>Therefore, our data indicate that in oligotrophic oceanic surface waters, pigment minimisation allows Prochlorococcus cells to harvest plentiful sunlight more effectively than other phytoplankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1183</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 24 April 2014; doi:10.1038/ismej.2014.56
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
