<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep01292#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Lee_2013, title={Utilizing the algicidal activity of aminoclay as a practical treatment for toxic red tides}, volume={3}, ISSN={2045-2322}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep01292}, DOI={10.1038/srep01292}, journal={Sci. Rep.}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Lee, Young-Chul and Jin, EonSeon and Jung, Seung Won and Kim, Yeon-Mi and Chang, Kwang Suk and Yang, Ji-Won and Kim, Si-Wouk and Kim, Young-Ok and Shin, Hyun-Jae}, year={2013}, month={Feb}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/srep01292</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Utilizing the algicidal activity of aminoclay as a practical treatment for toxic red tides
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>91</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>91</offset>
        <text>In recent decades, harmful algal blooms (HABs) - commonly known as red tides - have increasingly impacted human health, caused significant economic losses to fisheries and damaged coastal environments and ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>308</offset>
        <text>Here, we demonstrate a method to control and suppress HABs through selective algal lysis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>398</offset>
        <text>The approach harnesses the algicidal effects of aminoclays, which are comprised of a high density of primary amine groups covalently bonded by metal cation backbones.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>565</offset>
        <text>Positively charged colloidals of aminoclays induce cell lysis in HABs within several minutes exposure but have negligible impact on non-harmful phytoplankton, zooplankton and farmed fish.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>753</offset>
        <text>This selective lysis is due to the ammonium characteristics of the aminoclay and the electrostatic attraction between the clay nanoparticles and the algal cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>915</offset>
        <text>In contrast, yellow loess clay, a recognized treatment for HABs, causes algal flocs with little cell lysis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1023</offset>
        <text>Thus, the aminoclay loading can be effective for the mitigation of HABs.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
