<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.234#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Georges_2014, title={Metaproteomic analysis of a winter to spring succession in coastal northwest Atlantic Ocean microbial plankton}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.234}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.234}, number={6}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Georges, Anna A and El-Swais, Heba and Craig, Susanne E and Li, William KW and Walsh, David A}, year={2014}, month={Jun}, pages={1301–1313}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.234</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Metaproteomic analysis of a winter to spring succession in coastal northwest Atlantic Ocean microbial plankton
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>111</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>111</offset>
        <text>In this study, we used comparative metaproteomics to investigate the metabolic activity of microbial plankton inhabiting a seasonally hypoxic basin in the Northwest Atlantic Ocean (Bedford Basin).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>308</offset>
        <text>From winter to spring, we observed a seasonal increase in high-affinity membrane transport proteins involved in scavenging of organic substrates; Rhodobacterales transporters were strongly associated with the spring phytoplankton bloom, whereas SAR11 transporters were abundant in the underlying waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>612</offset>
        <text>A diverse array of transporters for organic compounds were similar to the SAR324 clade, revealing an active heterotrophic lifestyle in coastal waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>763</offset>
        <text>Proteins involved in methanol oxidation (from the OM43 clade) and carbon monoxide (from a wide variety of bacteria) were identified throughout Bedford Basin.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>921</offset>
        <text>Metabolic niche partitioning between the SUP05 and ARCTIC96BD-19 clades, which together comprise the Gamma-proteobacterial sulfur oxidizers group was apparent.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1081</offset>
        <text>ARCTIC96BD-19 proteins involved in the transport of organic compounds indicated that in productive coastal waters this lineage tends toward a heterotrophic metabolism.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1249</offset>
        <text>In contrast, the identification of sulfur oxidation proteins from SUP05 indicated the use of reduced sulfur as an energy source in hypoxic bottom water.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1402</offset>
        <text>We identified an abundance of Marine Group I Thaumarchaeota proteins in the hypoxic deep layer, including proteins for nitrification and carbon fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1556</offset>
        <text>No transporters for organic compounds were detected among the thaumarchaeal proteins, suggesting a reliance on autotrophic carbon assimilation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1700</offset>
        <text>In summary, our analyses revealed the spatiotemporal structure of numerous metabolic activities in the coastal ocean that are central to carbon, nitrogen and sulfur cycling in the sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
