<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ncomms4271#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ncomms4271</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Irigoien_2014, title={Large mesopelagic fishes biomass and trophic efficiency in the open ocean}, volume={5}, ISSN={2041-1723}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncomms4271}, DOI={10.1038/ncomms4271}, journal={Nature Communications}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Irigoien, Xabier and Klevjer, T. A. and Røstad, A. and Martinez, U. and Boyra, G. and Acuña, J. L. and Bode, A. and Echevarria, F. and Gonzalez-Gordillo, J. I. and Hernandez-Leon, S. and et al.}, year={2014}, month={Feb}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Large mesopelagic fishes biomass and trophic efficiency in the open ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>74</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>74</offset>
        <text>With a current estimate of ~1,000 million tons, mesopelagic fishes likely dominate the world total fishes biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>189</offset>
        <text>However, recent acoustic observations show that mesopelagic fishes biomass could be significantly larger than the current estimate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>Here we combine modelling and a sensitivity analysis of the acoustic observations from the Malaspina 2010 Circumnavigation Expedition to show that the previous estimate needs to be revised to at least one order of magnitude higher.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>553</offset>
        <text>We show that there is a close relationship between the open ocean fishes biomass and primary production, and that the energy transfer efficiency from phytoplankton to mesopelagic fishes in the open ocean is higher than what is typically assumed.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>799</offset>
        <text>Our results indicate that the role of mesopelagic fishes in oceanic ecosystems and global ocean biogeochemical cycles needs to be revised as they may be respiring ~10% of the primary production in deep waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
