<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature10285#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature10285</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Frank_2011, title={Transient dynamics of an altered large marine ecosystem}, volume={477}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature10285}, DOI={10.1038/nature10285}, number={7362}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Frank, Kenneth T. and Petrie, Brian and Fisher, Jonathan A. D. and Leggett, William C.}, year={2011}, month={Jul}, pages={86–89}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Transient dynamics of an altered large marine ecosystem
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>56</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>56</offset>
        <text>Overfishing of large-bodied benthic fishes and their subsequent population collapses on the Scotian Shelf of Canada's east coast and elsewhere resulted in restructuring of entire food webs now dominated by planktivorous, forage fish species and macroinvertebrates.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>321</offset>
        <text>Despite the imposition of strict management measures in force since the early 1990s, the Scotian Shelf ecosystem has not reverted back to its former structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>481</offset>
        <text>Here we provide evidence of the transient nature of this ecosystem and its current return path towards benthic fish species domination.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>617</offset>
        <text>The prolonged duration of the altered food web, and its current recovery, was and is being governed by the oscillatory, runaway consumption dynamics of the forage fish complex.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>794</offset>
        <text>These erupting forage species, which reached biomass levels 900% greater than those prevalent during the pre-collapse years of large benthic predators, are now in decline, having outstripped their zooplankton food supply.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1016</offset>
        <text>This dampening, and the associated reduction in the intensity of predation, was accompanied by lagged increases in species abundances at both lower and higher trophic levels, first witnessed in zooplankton and then in large-bodied predators, all consistent with a return towards the earlier ecosystem structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1328</offset>
        <text>We conclude that the reversibility of perturbed ecosystems can occur and that this bodes well for other collapsed fisheries.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
