<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo234#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo234</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Karl_2008, title={Aerobic production of methane in the sea}, volume={1}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo234}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo234}, number={7}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Karl, David M. and Beversdorf, Lucas and Björkman, Karin M. and Church, Matthew J. and Martinez, Asuncion and Delong, Edward F.}, year={2008}, month={Jun}, pages={473–478}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Aerobic production of methane in the sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>41</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>41</offset>
        <text>Methane is a potent greenhouse gas that has contributed approximately 20% to the Earth's warming since pre-industrial times.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>166</offset>
        <text>The world's oceans are an important source of methane, comprising 1-4% of annual global emissions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>265</offset>
        <text>But despite its global significance, oceanic methane production is poorly understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>351</offset>
        <text>In particular, methane concentrations in the surface waters of most of the world's oceans are supersaturated with respect to atmospheric concentrations, but the origin of this methane, which has been thought to be produced exclusively in anaerobic environments, is not known.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>627</offset>
        <text>Here, we measure methane production in seawater samples amended with methylphosphonate, an organic, phosphorus-containing compound.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>759</offset>
        <text>We show that methane is produced aerobically as a by-product of methylphosphonate decomposition in phosphate-stressed waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>885</offset>
        <text>Methylphosphonate decomposition, and thus methane production, may be enhanced by the activity of nitrogen-fixing microorganisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1014</offset>
        <text>We suggest that aerobic marine methane production will be sensitive to the changes in water-column stratification and nutrient limitation that are likely to result from greenhouse-gas-induced ocean warming.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
