<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.1#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Shilova_2014, title={A microarray for assessing transcription from pelagic marine microbial taxa}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.1}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.1}, number={7}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Shilova, Irina N and Robidart, Julie C and James Tripp, H and Turk-Kubo, Kendra and Wawrik, Boris and Post, Anton F and Thompson, Anne W and Ward, Bess and Hollibaugh, James T and Millard, Andy and et al.}, year={2014}, month={Jan}, pages={1476–1491}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.1</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A microarray for assessing transcription from pelagic marine microbial taxa
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>76</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>76</offset>
        <text>Metagenomic approaches have revealed unprecedented genetic diversity within microbial communities across vast expanses of the world's oceans.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>218</offset>
        <text>Linking this genetic diversity with key metabolic and cellular activities of microbial assemblages is a fundamental challenge.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>345</offset>
        <text>Here we report on a collaborative effort to design MicroTOOLs (Microbiological Targets for Ocean Observing Laboratories), a high-density oligonucleotide microarray that targets functional genes of diverse taxa in pelagic and coastal marine microbial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>608</offset>
        <text>MicroTOOLs integrates nucleotide sequence information from disparate data types: genomes, PCR-amplicons, metagenomes, and metatranscriptomes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>750</offset>
        <text>It targets 19 400 unique sequences over 145 different genes that are relevant to stress responses and microbial metabolism across the three domains of life and viruses.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>919</offset>
        <text>MicroTOOLs was used in a proof-of-concept experiment that compared the functional responses of microbial communities following Fe and P enrichments of surface water samples from the North Pacific Subtropical Gyre.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1133</offset>
        <text>We detected transcription of 68% of the gene targets across major taxonomic groups, and the pattern of transcription indicated relief from Fe limitation and transition to N limitation in some taxa.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1331</offset>
        <text>Prochlorococcus (eHLI), Synechococcus (sub-cluster 5.3) and Alphaproteobacteria SAR11 clade (HIMB59) showed the strongest responses to the Fe enrichment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1485</offset>
        <text>In addition, members of uncharacterized lineages also responded.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1550</offset>
        <text>The MicroTOOLs microarray provides a robust tool for comprehensive characterization of major functional groups of microbes in the open ocean, and the design can be easily amended for specific environments and research questions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1779</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 30 January 2014; doi:10.1038/ismej.2014.1
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
