<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.118#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Tseng_2013, title={Microbial and viral metagenomes of a subtropical freshwater reservoir subject to climatic disturbances}, volume={7}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.118}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.118}, number={12}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Tseng, Ching-Hung and Chiang, Pei-Wen and Shiah, Fuh-Kwo and Chen, Yi-Lung and Liou, Jia-Rong and Hsu, Ting-Chang and Maheswararajah, Suhinthan and Saeed, Isaam and Halgamuge, Saman and Tang, Sen-Lin}, year={2013}, month={Jul}, pages={2374–2386}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.118</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Microbial and viral metagenomes of a subtropical freshwater reservoir subject to climatic disturbances
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>103</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>103</offset>
        <text>Extreme climatic activities, such as typhoons, are widely known to disrupt our natural environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>203</offset>
        <text>In particular, studies have revealed that typhoon-induced perturbations can result in several long-term effects on various ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>338</offset>
        <text>In this study, we have conducted a 2-year metagenomic survey to investigate the microbial and viral community dynamics associated with environmental changes and seasonal variations in an enclosed freshwater reservoir subject to episodic typhoons.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>585</offset>
        <text>We found that the microbial community structure and the associated metagenomes continuously changed, where microbial richness increased after typhoon events and decreased during winter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>771</offset>
        <text>Among the environmental factors that influenced changes in the microbial community, precipitation was considered to be the most significant.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>912</offset>
        <text>Similarly, the viral community regularly showed higher relative abundances and diversity during summer in comparison to winter, with major variations happening in several viral families including Siphoviridae, Myoviridae, Podoviridae and Microviridae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1164</offset>
        <text>Interestingly, we also found that the precipitation level was associated with the terrestrial viral abundance in the reservoir.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1292</offset>
        <text>In contrast to the dynamic microbial community (L-divergence 0.73+/-0.25), we found that microbial metabolic profiles were relatively less divergent (L-divergence 0.24+/-0.04) at the finest metabolic resolution.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1504</offset>
        <text>This study provides for the first time a glimpse at the microbial and viral community dynamics of a subtropical freshwater ecosystem, adding a comprehensive set of new knowledge to aquatic environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
