<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2012.166#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2012.166</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Kirkham_2013, title={A global perspective on marine photosynthetic picoeukaryote community structure}, volume={7}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2012.166}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2012.166}, number={5}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Kirkham, Amy R and Lepère, Cécile and Jardillier, Ludwig E and Not, Fabrice and Bouman, Heather and Mead, Andrew and Scanlan, David J}, year={2013}, month={May}, pages={922–936}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>A global perspective on marine photosynthetic picoeukaryote community structure
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>80</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>80</offset>
        <text>A central goal in ecology is to understand the factors affecting the temporal dynamics and spatial distribution of microorganisms and the underlying processes causing differences in community structure and composition.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>299</offset>
        <text>However, little is known in this respect for photosynthetic picoeukaryotes (PPEs), algae that are now recognised as major players in marine CO2 fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>453</offset>
        <text>Here, we analysed dot blot hybridisation and cloning-sequencing data, using the plastid-encoded 16S rRNA gene, from seven research cruises that encompassed all four ocean biomes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>632</offset>
        <text>We provide insights into global abundance, alpha- and beta-diversity distribution and the environmental factors shaping PPE community structure and composition.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>793</offset>
        <text>At the class level, the most commonly encountered PPEs were Prymnesiophyceae and Chrysophyceae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>889</offset>
        <text>These taxa displayed complementary distribution patterns, with peak abundances of Prymnesiophyceae and Chrysophyceae in waters of high (25:1) or low (12:1) nitrogen:phosphorus (N:P) ratio, respectively.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1092</offset>
        <text>Significant differences in phylogenetic composition of PPEs were demonstrated for higher taxonomic levels between ocean basins, using Unifrac analyses of clone library sequence data.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1275</offset>
        <text>Differences in composition were generally greater between basins (interbasins) than within a basin (intrabasin).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1388</offset>
        <text>These differences were primarily linked to taxonomic variation in the composition of Prymnesiophyceae and Prasinophyceae whereas Chrysophyceae were phylogenetically similar in all libraries.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1579</offset>
        <text>These data provide better knowledge of PPE community structure across the world ocean and are crucial in assessing their evolution and contribution to CO2 fixation, especially in the context of global climate change.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
