<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.28#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.28</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Van_de_Waal_2011, title={Reversal in competitive dominance of a toxic versus non-toxic cyanobacterium in response to rising CO2}, volume={5}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.28}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.28}, number={9}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Van de Waal, Dedmer B and Verspagen, Jolanda MH and Finke, Jan F and Vournazou, Vasiliki and Immers, Anne K and Kardinaal, W Edwin A and Tonk, Linda and Becker, Sven and Van Donk, Ellen and Visser, Petra M and et al.}, year={2011}, month={Mar}, pages={1438–1450}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Reversal in competitive dominance of a toxic versus non-toxic cyanobacterium in response to rising CO2
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>103</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>103</offset>
        <text>Climate change scenarios predict a doubling of the atmospheric CO2 concentration by the end of this century.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>212</offset>
        <text>Yet, how rising CO2 will affect the species composition of aquatic microbial communities is still largely an open question.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>336</offset>
        <text>In this study, we develop a resource competition model to investigate competition for dissolved inorganic carbon in dense algal blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>472</offset>
        <text>The model predicts how dynamic changes in carbon chemistry, pH and light conditions during bloom development feed back on competing phytoplankton species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>627</offset>
        <text>We test the model predictions in chemostat experiments with monocultures and mixtures of a toxic and non-toxic strain of the freshwater cyanobacterium Microcystis aeruginosa.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>802</offset>
        <text>The toxic strain was able to reduce dissolved CO2 to lower concentrations than the non-toxic strain, and became dominant in competition at low CO2 levels.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>957</offset>
        <text>Conversely, the non-toxic strain could grow at lower light levels, and became dominant in competition at high CO2 levels but low light availability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1106</offset>
        <text>The model captured the observed reversal in competitive dominance, and was quantitatively in good agreement with the results of the competition experiments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1263</offset>
        <text>To assess whether microcystins might have a role in this reversal of competitive dominance, we performed further competition experiments with the wild-type strain M. aeruginosa PCC 7806 and its mcyB mutant impaired in microcystin production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1505</offset>
        <text>The microcystin-producing wild type had a strong selective advantage at low CO2 levels but not at high CO2 levels.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1620</offset>
        <text>Our results thus demonstrate both in theory and experiment that rising CO2 levels can alter the community composition and toxicity of harmful algal blooms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
