<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.28#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.28</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Ng_2010, title={Metaproteogenomic analysis of a dominant green sulfur bacterium from Ace Lake, Antarctica}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.28}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.28}, number={8}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Ng, Charmaine and DeMaere, Matthew Z and Williams, Timothy J and Lauro, Federico M and Raftery, Mark and Gibson, John AE and Andrews-Pfannkoch, Cynthia and Lewis, Matt and Hoffman, Jeffrey M and Thomas, Torsten and et al.}, year={2010}, month={Aug}, pages={1002–1019}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Metaproteogenomic analysis of a dominant green sulfur bacterium from Ace Lake, Antarctica
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Green sulfur bacteria (GSB) (Chlorobiaceae) are primary producers that are important in global carbon and sulfur cycling in natural environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>236</offset>
        <text>An almost complete genome sequence for a single, dominant GSB species ('C-Ace') was assembled from shotgun sequence data of an environmental sample taken from the O2-H2S interface of the water column of Ace Lake, Antarctica.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>461</offset>
        <text>Approximately 34 Mb of DNA sequence data were assembled into nine scaffolds totaling 1.79 Mb, representing approximately 19-fold coverage for the C-Ace composite genome.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>631</offset>
        <text>A high level (~31%) of metaproteomic coverage was achieved using matched biomass.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>713</offset>
        <text>The metaproteogenomic approach provided unique insight into the protein complement required for dominating the microbial community under cold, nutrient-limited, oxygen-limited and extremely varied annual light conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>935</offset>
        <text>C-Ace shows physiological traits that promote its ability to compete very effectively with other GSB and gain dominance (for example, specific bacteriochlorophylls, mechanisms of cold adaptation) as well as a syntrophic relationship with sulfate-reducing bacteria that provides a mechanism for the exchange of sulfur compounds.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1263</offset>
        <text>As a result we are able to propose an explanation of the active biological processes promoted by cold-adapted GSB and the adaptive strategies they use to thrive under the severe physiochemical conditions prevailing in polar environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
