<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1489#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nclimate1489</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Flynn_2012, title={Changes in pH at the exterior surface of plankton with ocean acidification}, ISSN={1758-6798}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1489}, DOI={10.1038/nclimate1489}, journal={Nature Climate Change}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Flynn, Kevin J. and Blackford, Jerry C. and Baird, Mark E. and Raven, John A. and Clark, Darren R. and Beardall, John and Brownlee, Colin and Fabian, Heiner and Wheeler, Glen L.}, year={2012}, month={Apr}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Changes in pH at the exterior surface of plankton with ocean acidification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>75</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>75</offset>
        <text>Anthropogenically released CO2 is dissolving in the ocean, causing a decrease in bulk-seawater pH (ocean acidification).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>196</offset>
        <text>Projections indicate that the pH will drop 0.3 units from its present value by 2100 (ref. )
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>288</offset>
        <text>.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>290</offset>
        <text>However, it is unclear how the growth of plankton is likely to respond.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>362</offset>
        <text>Using simulations we demonstrate how pH and carbonate chemistry at the exterior surface of marine organisms deviates increasingly from those of the bulk sea water as organism metabolic activity and size increases.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>576</offset>
        <text>These deviations will increase in the future as the buffering capacity of sea water decreases with decreased pH and as metabolic activity increases with raised seawater temperatures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>759</offset>
        <text>We show that many marine plankton will experience pH conditions completely outside their recent historical range.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>873</offset>
        <text>However, ocean acidification is likely to have differing impacts on plankton physiology as taxon-specific differences in organism size, metabolic activity and growth rates during blooms result in very different microenvironments around the organism.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1123</offset>
        <text>This is an important consideration for future studies in ocean acidification as the carbonate chemistry experienced by most planktonic organisms will probably be considerably different from that measured in bulk-seawater samples.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1353</offset>
        <text>An understanding of these deviations will assist interpretation of the impacts of ocean acidification on plankton of different size and metabolic activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
