<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature12784#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Sherwood_2013, title={Increasing subtropical North Pacific Ocean nitrogen fixation since the Little Ice Age}, volume={505}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature12784}, DOI={10.1038/nature12784}, number={7481}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Sherwood, Owen A. and Guilderson, Thomas P. and Batista, Fabian C. and Schiff, John T. and McCarthy, Matthew D.}, year={2013}, month={Dec}, pages={78–81}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature12784</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Increasing subtropical North Pacific Ocean nitrogen fixation since the Little Ice Age
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>The North Pacific subtropical gyre (NPSG) plays a major part in the export of carbon and other nutrients to the deep ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>210</offset>
        <text>Primary production in the NPSG has increased in recent decades despite a reduction in nutrient supply to surface waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>331</offset>
        <text>It is thought that this apparent paradox can be explained by a shift in plankton community structure from mostly eukaryotes to mostly nitrogen-fixing prokaryotes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>494</offset>
        <text>It remains uncertain, however, whether the plankton community domain shift can be linked to cyclical climate variability or a long-term global warming trend.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>652</offset>
        <text>Here we analyse records of bulk and amino-acid-specific 15N/14N isotopic ratios (delta15N) preserved in the skeletons of long-lived deep-sea proteinaceous corals collected from the Hawaiian archipelago; these isotopic records serve as a proxy for the source of nitrogen-supported export production through time.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>964</offset>
        <text>We find that the recent increase in nitrogen fixation is the continuation of a much larger, centennial-scale trend.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1080</offset>
        <text>After a millennium of relatively minor fluctuation, delta15N decreases between 1850 and the present.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1181</offset>
        <text>The total shift in delta15N of -2 per mil over this period is comparable to the total change in global mean sedimentary delta15N across the Pleistocene-Holocene transition, but it is happening an order of magnitude faster.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1404</offset>
        <text>We use a steady-state model and find that the isotopic mass balance between nitrate and nitrogen fixation implies a 17 to 27 per cent increase in nitrogen fixation over this time period.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1591</offset>
        <text>A comparison with independent records suggests that the increase in nitrogen fixation might be linked to Northern Hemisphere climate change since the end of the Little Ice Age.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
