<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2010.63#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2010.63</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{N_slund_2010, title={Meiofauna reduces bacterial mineralization of naphthalene in marine sediment}, volume={4}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2010.63}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2010.63}, number={11}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Näslund, Johan and Nascimento, Francisco JA and Gunnarsson, Jonas S}, year={2010}, month={May}, pages={1421–1430}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Meiofauna reduces bacterial mineralization of naphthalene in marine sediment
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>77</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>77</offset>
        <text>The role of sediment-living meiofauna, benthic invertebrates smaller than 1000 mum such as nematodes and ostracods, on the mineralization of naphthalene, a common polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) in marine sediments, was studied in microcosms using radiorespirometry.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>350</offset>
        <text>A method to extract live meiofauna was developed and used in order to experimentally manipulate meiofauna abundance and group diversity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>487</offset>
        <text>Higher abundances of meiofauna were found to significantly decrease naphthalene mineralization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>583</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, a change in the bacterial community composition (studied using terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism) was also observed in presence of higher meiofauna abundance, as well as a lower number of cultivable naphthalene-degrading bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>843</offset>
        <text>The reduced mineralization of naphthalene and the altered bacterial community composition in the presence of increased meiofauna abundance is likely the result of top-down control by meiofauna.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1037</offset>
        <text>This study shows that higher abundances of meiofauna can significantly decrease the microbial mineralization of PAHs such as naphthalene and also significantly modify the bacterial community composition in natural marine sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
