<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2007.5#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2007.5</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hewson_2007, title={Diazotrophic bacterioplankton in a coral reef lagoon: phylogeny, diel nitrogenase expression and response to phosphate enrichment}, volume={1}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2007.5}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2007.5}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hewson, Ian and Moisander, Pia H and Morrison, Amanda E and Zehr, Jonathan P}, year={2007}, month={May}, pages={78–91}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Diazotrophic bacterioplankton in a coral reef lagoon: phylogeny, diel nitrogenase expression and response to phosphate enrichment
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>130</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>130</offset>
        <text>We investigated diazotrophic bacterioplankton assemblage composition in the Heron Reef lagoon (Great Barrier Reef, Australia) using culture-independent techniques targeting the nifH fragment of the nitrogenase gene.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>346</offset>
        <text>Seawater was collected at 3 h intervals over a period of 72 h (i.e. over diel as well as tidal cycles).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>450</offset>
        <text>An incubation experiment was also conducted to assess the impact of phosphate (PO43-) availability on nifH expression patterns.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>578</offset>
        <text>DNA-based nifH libraries contained primarily sequences that were most similar to nifH from sediment, microbial mat and surface-associated microorganisms, with a few sequences that clustered with typical open ocean phylotypes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>804</offset>
        <text>In contrast to genomic DNA sequences, libraries prepared from gene transcripts (mRNA amplified by reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction) were entirely cyanobacterial and contained phylotypes similar to those observed in open ocean plankton.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1055</offset>
        <text>The abundance of Trichodesmium and two uncultured cyanobacterial phylotypes from previous studies (group A and group B) were studied by quantitative-polymerase chain reaction in the lagoon samples.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1253</offset>
        <text>These were detected as transcripts, but were not detected in genomic DNA.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1327</offset>
        <text>The gene transcript abundance of these phylotypes demonstrated variability over several diel cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1428</offset>
        <text>The PO43- enrichment experiment had a clearer pattern of gene expression over diel cycles than the lagoon sampling, however PO43- additions did not result in enhanced transcript abundance relative to control incubations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1649</offset>
        <text>The results suggest that a number of diazotrophs in bacterioplankton of the reef lagoon may originate from sediment, coral or beachrock surfaces, sloughing into plankton with the flooding tide.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1843</offset>
        <text>The presence of typical open ocean phylotype transcripts in lagoon bacterioplankton may indicate that they are an important component of the N cycle of the coral reef.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
