<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.16#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.16</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{McKie_Krisberg_2014, title={Phagotrophy by the picoeukaryotic green alga Micromonas: implications for Arctic Oceans}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.16}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.16}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={McKie-Krisberg, Zaid M and Sanders, Robert W}, year={2014}, month={Feb}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Phagotrophy by the picoeukaryotic green alga Micromonas: implications for Arctic Oceans
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>88</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>88</offset>
        <text>Photosynthetic picoeukaryotes (PPE) are recognized as major primary producers and contributors to phytoplankton biomass in oceanic and coastal environments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>245</offset>
        <text>Molecular surveys indicate a large phylogenetic diversity in the picoeukaryotes, with members of the Prymnesiophyceae and Chrysophyseae tending to be more common in open ocean waters and Prasinophyceae dominating coastal and Arctic waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>485</offset>
        <text>In addition to their role as primary producers, PPE have been identified in several studies as mixotrophic and major predators of prokaryotes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>628</offset>
        <text>Mixotrophy, the combination of photosynthesis and phagotrophy in a single organism, is well established for most photosynthetic lineages.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>766</offset>
        <text>However, green algae, including prasinophytes, were widely considered as a purely photosynthetic group.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>870</offset>
        <text>The prasinophyte Micromonas is perhaps the most common picoeukaryote in coastal and Arctic waters and is one of the relatively few cultured representatives of the picoeukaryotes available for physiological investigations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1092</offset>
        <text>In this study, we demonstrate phagotrophy by a strain of Micromonas (CCMP2099) isolated from Arctic waters and show that environmental factors (light and nutrient concentration) affect ingestion rates in this mixotroph.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1312</offset>
        <text>In addition, we show size-selective feeding with a preference for smaller particles, and determine P vs I (photosynthesis vs irradiance) responses in different nutrient conditions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1493</offset>
        <text>If other strains have mixotrophic abilities similar to Micromonas CCMP2099, the widespread distribution and frequently high abundances of Micromonas suggest that these green algae may have significant impact on prokaryote populations in several oceanic regimes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1755</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 20 February 2014; doi:10.1038/ismej.2014.16
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
