<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature11229#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature11229</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Smetacek_2012, title={Deep carbon export from a Southern Ocean iron-fertilized diatom bloom}, volume={487}, ISSN={1476-4687}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature11229}, DOI={10.1038/nature11229}, number={7407}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Smetacek, Victor and Klaas, Christine and Strass, Volker H. and Assmy, Philipp and Montresor, Marina and Cisewski, Boris and Savoye, Nicolas and Webb, Adrian and d’ Ovidio, Francesco and Arrieta, Jesús M. and et al.}, year={2012}, month={Jul}, pages={313–319}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Deep carbon export from a Southern Ocean iron-fertilized diatom bloom
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>70</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>70</offset>
        <text>Fertilization of the ocean by adding iron compounds has induced diatom-dominated phytoplankton blooms accompanied by considerable carbon dioxide drawdown in the ocean surface layer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>252</offset>
        <text>However, because the fate of bloom biomass could not be adequately resolved in these experiments, the timescales of carbon sequestration from the atmosphere are uncertain.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>424</offset>
        <text>Here we report the results of a five-week experiment carried out in the closed core of a vertically coherent, mesoscale eddy of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current, during which we tracked sinking particles from the surface to the deep-sea floor.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>669</offset>
        <text>A large diatom bloom peaked in the fourth week after fertilization.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>737</offset>
        <text>This was followed by mass mortality of several diatom species that formed rapidly sinking, mucilaginous aggregates of entangled cells and chains.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>883</offset>
        <text>Taken together, multiple lines of evidence--although each with important uncertainties--lead us to conclude that at least half the bloom biomass sank far below a depth of 1,000 metres and that a substantial portion is likely to have reached the sea floor.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1139</offset>
        <text>Thus, iron-fertilized diatom blooms may sequester carbon for timescales of centuries in ocean bottom water and for longer in the sediments.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
