<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.140#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.140</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Bienhold_2011, title={The energy–diversity relationship of complex bacterial communities in Arctic deep-sea sediments}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.140}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.140}, number={4}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Bienhold, Christina and Boetius, Antje and Ramette, Alban}, year={2011}, month={Nov}, pages={724–732}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>The energy-diversity relationship of complex bacterial communities in Arctic deep-sea sediments
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>96</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>96</offset>
        <text>The availability of nutrients and energy is a main driver of biodiversity for plant and animal communities in terrestrial and marine ecosystems, but we are only beginning to understand whether and how energy-diversity relationships may be extended to complex natural bacterial communities.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>386</offset>
        <text>Here, we analyzed the link between phytodetritus input, diversity and activity of bacterial communities of the Siberian continental margin (37-3427 m water depth).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>550</offset>
        <text>Community structure and functions, such as enzymatic activity, oxygen consumption and carbon remineralization rates, were highly related to each other, and with energy availability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>732</offset>
        <text>Bacterial richness substantially increased with increasing sediment pigment content, suggesting a positive energy-diversity relationship in oligotrophic regions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>894</offset>
        <text>Richness leveled off, forming a plateau, when mesotrophic sites were included, suggesting that bacterial communities and other benthic fauna may be structured by similar mechanisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1076</offset>
        <text>Dominant bacterial taxa showed strong positive or negative relationships with phytodetritus input and allowed us to identify candidate bioindicator taxa.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1230</offset>
        <text>Contrasting responses of individual taxa to changes in phytodetritus input also suggest varying ecological strategies among bacterial groups along the energy gradient.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1398</offset>
        <text>Our results imply that environmental changes affecting primary productivity and particle export from the surface ocean will not only affect bacterial community structure but also bacterial functions in Arctic deep-sea sediment, and that sediment bacterial communities can record shifts in the whole ocean ecosystem functioning.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
