<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.144#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Ganesh_2014, title={Metagenomic analysis of size-fractionated picoplankton in a marine oxygen minimum zone}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.144}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.144}, number={1}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Ganesh, Sangita and Parris, Darren J and DeLong, Edward F and Stewart, Frank J}, year={2014}, month={Jan}, pages={187–211}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.144</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Metagenomic analysis of size-fractionated picoplankton in a marine oxygen minimum zone
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>87</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>87</offset>
        <text>Marine oxygen minimum zones (OMZs) support diverse microbial communities with roles in major elemental cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>198</offset>
        <text>It is unclear how the taxonomic composition and metabolism of OMZ microorganisms vary between particle-associated and free-living size fractions.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>344</offset>
        <text>We used amplicon (16S rRNA gene) and shotgun metagenome sequencing to compare microbial communities from large (&gt;1.6 mum) and small (0.2-1.6 mum) filter size fractions along a depth gradient in the OMZ off Chile.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>557</offset>
        <text>Despite steep vertical redox gradients, size fraction was a significantly stronger predictor of community composition compared to depth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>694</offset>
        <text>Phylogenetic diversity showed contrasting patterns, decreasing towards the anoxic OMZ core in the small size fraction, but exhibiting maximal values at these depths within the larger size fraction.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>892</offset>
        <text>Fraction-specific distributions were evident for key OMZ taxa, including anammox planctomycetes, whose coding sequences were enriched up to threefold in the 0.2-1.6 mum community.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1072</offset>
        <text>Functional gene composition also differed between fractions, with the &gt;1.6 mum community significantly enriched in genes mediating social interactions, including motility, adhesion, cell-to-cell transfer, antibiotic resistance and mobile element activity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1328</offset>
        <text>Prokaryotic transposase genes were three to six fold more abundant in this fraction, comprising up to 2% of protein-coding sequences, suggesting that particle surfaces may act as hotbeds for transposition-based genome changes in marine microbes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1574</offset>
        <text>Genes for nitric and nitrous oxide reduction were also more abundant (three to seven fold) in the larger size fraction, suggesting microniche partitioning of key denitrification steps.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1759</offset>
        <text>These results highlight an important role for surface attachment in shaping community metabolic potential and genome content in OMZ microorganisms.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
