<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ngeo1739#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Kalvelage_2013, title={Nitrogen cycling driven by organic matter export in the South Pacific oxygen minimum zone}, volume={6}, ISSN={1752-0908}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ngeo1739}, DOI={10.1038/ngeo1739}, number={3}, journal={Nature Geoscience}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Kalvelage, Tim and Lavik, Gaute and Lam, Phyllis and Contreras, Sergio and Arteaga, Lionel and Löscher, Carolin R. and Oschlies, Andreas and Paulmier, Aurélien and Stramma, Lothar and Kuypers, Marcel M. M.}, year={2013}, month={Feb}, pages={228–234}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ngeo1739</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen cycling driven by organic matter export in the South Pacific oxygen minimum zone
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>Oxygen minimum zones are expanding globally, and at present account for around 20-40% of oceanic nitrogen loss.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>202</offset>
        <text>Heterotrophic denitrification and anammox--anaerobic ammonium oxidation with nitrite--are responsible for most nitrogen loss in these low-oxygen waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>355</offset>
        <text>Anammox is particularly significant in the eastern tropical South Pacific, one of the largest oxygen minimum zones globally.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>480</offset>
        <text>However, the factors that regulate anammox-driven nitrogen loss have remained unclear.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>567</offset>
        <text>Here, we present a comprehensive nitrogen budget for the eastern tropical South Pacific oxygen minimum zone, using measurements of nutrient concentrations, experimentally determined rates of nitrogen transformation and a numerical model of export production.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>826</offset>
        <text>Anammox was the dominant mode of nitrogen loss at the time of sampling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>898</offset>
        <text>Rates of anammox, and related nitrogen transformations, were greatest in the productive shelf waters, and tailed off with distance from the coast.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1045</offset>
        <text>Within the shelf region, anammox activity peaked in both upper and bottom waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1127</offset>
        <text>Overall, rates of nitrogen transformation, including anammox, were strongly correlated with the export of organic matter.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1249</offset>
        <text>We suggest that the sinking of organic matter, and thus the release of ammonium into the water column, together with benthic ammonium release, fuel nitrogen loss from oxygen minimum zones.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
