<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#31674#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Takeda_1998, volume={393}, ISSN={0028-0836}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/31674}, DOI={10.1038/31674}, number={6687}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Takeda, Shigenobu}, year={1998}, month={Jun}, pages={774–777}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/31674</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Influence of iron availability on nutrient consumption ratio of diatoms in oceanic waters
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>90</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>90</offset>
        <text>The major nutrients (nitrate, phosphate and silicate) needed for phytoplankton growth are abundant in the surface waters of the subarctic Pacific, equatorial Pacific and Southern oceans, but this growth is limited by the availability of iron.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>333</offset>
        <text>Under iron-deficient conditions, phytoplankton exhibit reduced uptake of nitrate and lower cellular levels of carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>476</offset>
        <text>Here I describe seawater and culture experiments which show that iron limitation can also affect the ratio of consumed silicate to nitrate and phosphate.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>630</offset>
        <text>In iron-limited waters from all three of the aforementioned environments, addition of iron to phytoplankton assemblages in incubation bottles halved the silicate:nitrate and silicate:phosphate consumption ratios, in spite of the preferential growth of diatoms (silica-shelled phytoplankton).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>922</offset>
        <text>The nutrient consumption ratios of the phytoplankton assemblage from the Southern Ocean were similar to those of an iron-deficient laboratory culture of Antarctic diatoms, which exhibit increased cellular silicon or decreased cellular nitrogen and phosphorus in response to iron limitation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1213</offset>
        <text>Iron limitation therefore increases the export of biogenic silicon, relative to nitrogen and phosphorus, from the surface to deeper waters.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1353</offset>
        <text>These findings suggest how the sedimentary records of carbon and silicon deposition in the glacial Southern Ocean can be consistent with the idea that changes in productivity, and thus in drawdown of atmospheric CO2, during the last glaciation were stimulated by changes in iron inputs from atmospheric dust.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
