<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nclimate1774#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nclimate1774</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Schaum_2012, title={Variation in plastic responses of a globally distributed picoplankton species to ocean acidification}, volume={3}, ISSN={1758-6798}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nclimate1774}, DOI={10.1038/nclimate1774}, number={3}, journal={Nature Climate Change}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Schaum, Elisa and Rost, Björn and Millar, Andrew J. and Collins, Sinéad}, year={2012}, month={Dec}, pages={298–302}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Variation in plastic responses of a globally distributed picoplankton species to ocean acidification
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>101</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>101</offset>
        <text>Phytoplankton are the basis of marine food webs, and affect biogeochemical cycles.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>184</offset>
        <text>As CO2 levels increase, shifts in the frequencies and physiology of ecotypes within phytoplankton groups will affect their nutritional value and biogeochemical function.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>354</offset>
        <text>However, studies so far are based on a few representative genotypes from key species.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>440</offset>
        <text>Here, we measure changes in cellular function and growth rate at atmospheric CO2 concentrations predicted for the year 2100 in 16 ecotypes of the marine picoplankton Ostreococcus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>620</offset>
        <text>We find that variation in plastic responses among ecotypes is on par with published between-genera variation, so the responses of one or a few ecotypes cannot estimate changes to the physiology or composition of a species under CO2 enrichment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>864</offset>
        <text>We show that ecotypes best at taking advantage of CO2 enrichment by changing their photosynthesis rates most should increase in relative fitness, and so in frequency in a high-CO2 environment.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1057</offset>
        <text>Finally, information on sampling location, and not phylogenetic relatedness, is a good predictor of ecotypes likely to increase in frequency in this system.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
