<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.59#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.59</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Hingamp_2013, title={Exploring nucleo-cytoplasmic large DNA viruses in Tara Oceans microbial metagenomes}, volume={7}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.59}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.59}, number={9}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Hingamp, Pascal and Grimsley, Nigel and Acinas, Silvia G and Clerissi, Camille and Subirana, Lucie and Poulain, Julie and Ferrera, Isabel and Sarmento, Hugo and Villar, Emilie and Lima-Mendez, Gipsi and et al.}, year={2013}, month={Apr}, pages={1678–1695}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Exploring nucleo-cytoplasmic large DNA viruses in Tara Oceans microbial metagenomes
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>84</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>84</offset>
        <text>Nucleo-cytoplasmic large DNA viruses (NCLDVs) constitute a group of eukaryotic viruses that can have crucial ecological roles in the sea by accelerating the turnover of their unicellular hosts or by causing diseases in animals.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>312</offset>
        <text>To better characterize the diversity, abundance and biogeography of marine NCLDVs, we analyzed 17 metagenomes derived from microbial samples (0.2-1.6 mum size range) collected during the Tara Oceans Expedition.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>523</offset>
        <text>The sample set includes ecosystems under-represented in previous studies, such as the Arabian Sea oxygen minimum zone (OMZ) and Indian Ocean lagoons.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>673</offset>
        <text>By combining computationally derived relative abundance and direct prokaryote cell counts, the abundance of NCLDVs was found to be in the order of 104-105 genomes ml-1 for the samples from the photic zone and 102-103 genomes ml-1 for the OMZ.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>916</offset>
        <text>The Megaviridae and Phycodnaviridae dominated the NCLDV populations in the metagenomes, although most of the reads classified in these families showed large divergence from known viral genomes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1110</offset>
        <text>Our taxon co-occurrence analysis revealed a potential association between viruses of the Megaviridae family and eukaryotes related to oomycetes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1255</offset>
        <text>In support of this predicted association, we identified six cases of lateral gene transfer between Megaviridae and oomycetes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1381</offset>
        <text>Our results suggest that marine NCLDVs probably outnumber eukaryotic organisms in the photic layer (per given water mass) and that metagenomic sequence analyses promise to shed new light on the biodiversity of marine viruses and their interactions with potential hosts.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
