<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature02550#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature02550</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Mills_2004, title={Iron and phosphorus co-limit nitrogen fixation in the eastern tropical North Atlantic}, volume={429}, ISSN={1476-4679}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature02550}, DOI={10.1038/nature02550}, number={6989}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Mills, Matthew M. and Ridame, Celine and Davey, Margaret and La Roche, Julie and Geider, Richard J.}, year={2004}, month={May}, pages={292–294}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Iron and phosphorus co-limit nitrogen fixation in the eastern tropical North Atlantic
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>86</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>86</offset>
        <text>The role of iron in enhancing phytoplankton productivity in high nutrient, low chlorophyll oceanic regions was demonstrated first through iron-addition bioassay experiments and subsequently confirmed by large-scale iron fertilization experiments.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>333</offset>
        <text>Iron supply has been hypothesized to limit nitrogen fixation and hence oceanic primary productivity on geological timescales, providing an alternative to phosphorus as the ultimate limiting nutrient.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>533</offset>
        <text>Oceanographic observations have been interpreted both to confirm and refute this hypothesis, but direct experimental evidence is lacking.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>671</offset>
        <text>We conducted experiments to test this hypothesis during the Meteor 55 cruise to the tropical North Atlantic.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>780</offset>
        <text>This region is rich in diazotrophs and strongly impacted by Saharan dust input.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>860</offset>
        <text>Here we show that community primary productivity was nitrogen-limited, and that nitrogen fixation was co-limited by iron and phosphorus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>997</offset>
        <text>Saharan dust addition stimulated nitrogen fixation, presumably by supplying both iron and phosphorus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1099</offset>
        <text>Our results support the hypothesis that aeolian mineral dust deposition promotes nitrogen fixation in the eastern tropical North Atlantic.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
