<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.60#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Giovannoni_2014, title={Implications of streamlining theory for microbial ecology}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.60}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.60}, number={8}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Giovannoni, Stephen J and Cameron Thrash, J and Temperton, Ben}, year={2014}, month={Apr}, pages={1553–1565}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.60</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Implications of streamlining theory for microbial ecology
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>58</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>58</offset>
        <text>Whether a small cell, a small genome or a minimal set of chemical reactions with self-replicating properties, simplicity is beguiling.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>193</offset>
        <text>As Leonardo da Vinci reportedly said, 'simplicity is the ultimate sophistication'.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>276</offset>
        <text>Two diverging views of simplicity have emerged in accounts of symbiotic and commensal bacteria and cosmopolitan free-living bacteria with small genomes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>429</offset>
        <text>The small genomes of obligate insect endosymbionts have been attributed to genetic drift caused by small effective population sizes (Ne).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>567</offset>
        <text>In contrast, streamlining theory attributes small cells and genomes to selection for efficient use of nutrients in populations where Ne is large and nutrients limit growth.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>740</offset>
        <text>Regardless of the cause of genome reduction, lost coding potential eventually dictates loss of function.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>845</offset>
        <text>Consequences of reductive evolution in streamlined organisms include atypical patterns of prototrophy and the absence of common regulatory systems, which have been linked to difficulty in culturing these cells.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1056</offset>
        <text>Recent evidence from metagenomics suggests that streamlining is commonplace, may broadly explain the phenomenon of the uncultured microbial majority, and might also explain the highly interdependent (connected) behavior of many microbial ecosystems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1306</offset>
        <text>Streamlining theory is belied by the observation that many successful bacteria are large cells with complex genomes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1423</offset>
        <text>To fully appreciate streamlining, we must look to the life histories and adaptive strategies of cells, which impose minimum requirements for complexity that vary with niche.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1597</offset>
        <text>The ISME Journal advance online publication, 17 April 2014; doi:10.1038/ismej.2014.60
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
