<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#nature02210#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/nature02210</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{M_ller_Navarra_2004, title={Unsaturated fatty acid content in seston and tropho-dynamic coupling in lakes}, volume={427}, ISSN={1476-4679}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature02210}, DOI={10.1038/nature02210}, number={6969}, journal={Nature}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Müller-Navarra, Dörthe C. and Brett, Michael T. and Park, Sangkyu and Chandra, Sudeep and Ballantyne, Ashley P. and Zorita, Eduardo and Goldman, Charles R.}, year={2004}, month={Jan}, pages={69–72}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Unsaturated fatty acid content in seston and tropho-dynamic coupling in lakes
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>78</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>78</offset>
        <text>Determining the factors that control food web interactions is a key issue in ecology.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>164</offset>
        <text>The empirical relationship between nutrient loading (total phosphorus) and phytoplankton standing stock (chlorophyll a) in lakes was described about 30 years ago and is central for managing surface water quality.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>377</offset>
        <text>The efficiency with which biomass and energy are transferred through the food web and sustain the production of higher trophic levels (such as fish) declines with nutrient loading and system productivity, but the underlying mechanisms are poorly understood.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>635</offset>
        <text>Here we show that in seston (fine particles in water) during summer, specific omega3-polyunsaturated fatty acids (omega3-PUFAs), which are important for zooplankton, are significantly correlated to the trophic status of the lake.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>865</offset>
        <text>The omega3-PUFAs octadecatetraenoic acid, eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid, but not alpha-linolenic acid, decrease on a double-logarithmic scale with increasing total phosphorus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1064</offset>
        <text>By combining the empirical relationship between EPA-to-carbon content and total phosphorus with functional models relating EPA-to-carbon content to the growth and egg production of daphnids, we predict secondary production for this key consumer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1310</offset>
        <text>Thus, the decreasing efficiency in energy transfer with increasing lake productivity can be explained by differences in omega3-PUFA-associated food quality at the plant-animal interface.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
