<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2014.71#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Loescher_2014, title={Facets of diazotrophy in the oxygen minimum zone waters off Peru}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2014.71}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2014.71}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Loescher, Carolin R and Großkopf, Tobias and Desai, Falguni D and Gill, Diana and Schunck, Harald and Croot, Peter L and Schlosser, Christian and Neulinger, Sven C and Pinnow, Nicole and Lavik, Gaute and et al.}, year={2014}, month={May}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2014.71</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Facets of diazotrophy in the oxygen minimum zone waters off Peru
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>65</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>65</offset>
        <text>Nitrogen fixation, the biological reduction of dinitrogen gas (N2) to ammonium (NH4+), is quantitatively the most important external source of new nitrogen (N) to the open ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>244</offset>
        <text>Classically, the ecological niche of oceanic N2 fixers (diazotrophs) is ascribed to tropical oligotrophic surface waters, often depleted in fixed N, with a diazotrophic community dominated by cyanobacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>451</offset>
        <text>Although this applies for large areas of the ocean, biogeochemical models and phylogenetic studies suggest that the oceanic diazotrophic niche may be much broader than previously considered, resulting in major implications for the global N-budget.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>699</offset>
        <text>Here, we report on the composition, distribution and abundance of nifH, the functional gene marker for N2 fixation.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>815</offset>
        <text>Our results show the presence of eight clades of diazotrophs in the oxygen minimum zone (OMZ) off Peru.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>919</offset>
        <text>Although proteobacterial clades dominated overall, two clusters affiliated to spirochaeta and archaea were identified.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1038</offset>
        <text>N2 fixation was detected within OMZ waters and was stimulated by the addition of organic carbon sources supporting the view that non-phototrophic diazotrophs were actively fixing dinitrogen.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1229</offset>
        <text>The observed co-occurrence of key functional genes for N2 fixation, nitrification, anammox and denitrification suggests that a close spatial coupling of N-input and N-loss processes exists in the OMZ off Peru.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1439</offset>
        <text>The wide distribution of diazotrophs throughout the water column adds to the emerging view that the habitat of marine diazotrophs can be extended to low oxygen/high nitrate areas.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1619</offset>
        <text>Furthermore, our statistical analysis suggests that NO2- and PO43- are the major factors affecting diazotrophic distribution throughout the OMZ.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1764</offset>
        <text>In view of the predicted increase in ocean deoxygenation resulting from global warming, our findings indicate that the importance of OMZs as niches for N2 fixation may increase in the future.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
