<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2008.117#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2008.117</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Carlson_2008, title={Seasonal dynamics of SAR11 populations in the euphotic and mesopelagic zones of the northwestern Sargasso Sea}, volume={3}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2008.117}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2008.117}, number={3}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Carlson, Craig A and Morris, Robert and Parsons, Rachel and Treusch, Alexander H and Giovannoni, Stephen J and Vergin, Kevin}, year={2008}, month={Dec}, pages={283–295}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Seasonal dynamics of SAR11 populations in the euphotic and mesopelagic zones of the northwestern Sargasso Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>110</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>110</offset>
        <text>Bacterioplankton belonging to the SAR11 clade of a-proteobacteria were counted by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) over eight depths in the surface 300 m at the Bermuda Atlantic Time-series Study (BATS) site from 2003 to 2005.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>346</offset>
        <text>SAR11 are dominant heterotrophs in oligotrophic systems; thus, resolving their temporal dynamics can provide important insights to the cycling of organic and inorganic nutrients.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>525</offset>
        <text>This quantitative time-series data revealed distinct annual distribution patterns of SAR11 abundance in the euphotic (0-120) and upper mesopelagic (160-300 m) zones that were reproducibly correlated with seasonal mixing and stratification of the water column.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>785</offset>
        <text>Terminal restriction fragment length polymorphism (T-RFLP) data generated from a decade of samples collected at BATS were combined with the FISH data to model the annual dynamics of SAR11 subclade populations.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>995</offset>
        <text>16S rRNA gene clone libraries were constructed to verify the correlation of the T-RFLP data with SAR11 clade structure.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1115</offset>
        <text>Clear vertical and temporal transitions were observed in the dominance of three SAR11 ecotypes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1211</offset>
        <text>The mechanisms that lead to shifts between the different SAR11 populations are not well understood, but are probably a consequence of finely tuned physiological adaptations that partition the populations along physical and chemical gradients in the ecosystem.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1471</offset>
        <text>The correlation between evolutionary descent and temporal/spatial patterns we describe, confirmed that a minimum of three SAR11 ecotypes occupy the Sargasso Sea surface layer, and revealed new details of their population dynamics.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
