<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep04661#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/srep04661</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Pedneault_2014, title={Archaeal amoA and ureC genes and their transcriptional activity in the Arctic Ocean}, volume={4}, ISSN={2045-2322}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep04661}, DOI={10.1038/srep04661}, journal={Sci. Rep.}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Pedneault, Estelle and Galand, Pierre E. and Potvin, Marianne and Tremblay, Jean-Éric and Lovejoy, Connie}, year={2014}, month={Apr}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Archaeal amoA and ureC genes and their transcriptional activity in the Arctic Ocean
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>84</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>84</offset>
        <text>Thaumarchaeota and the gene encoding for a subunit of ammonia monooxygenase (amoA) are ubiquitous in Polar Seas, and some Thaumarchaeota also have a gene coding for ureC, diagnostic for urease.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>278</offset>
        <text>Using quantitative PCR we investigated the occurrence of genes and transcripts of ureC and amoA in Arctic samples from winter, spring and summer.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>424</offset>
        <text>AmoA genes, ureC genes and amoA transcripts were always present, but ureC transcripts were rarely detected.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>532</offset>
        <text>Over a 48 h light manipulation experiment amoA transcripts persisted under light and dark conditions, but not ureC transcripts.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>660</offset>
        <text>In addition, maxima for amoA transcript were nearer the surface compared to amoA genes.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>748</offset>
        <text>Clone libraries using DNA template recovered shallow and deep amoA clades but only the shallow clade was recovered from cDNA (from RNA).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>885</offset>
        <text>These results imply environmental control of amoA expression with direct or indirect light effects, and rare ureC expression despite its widespread occurrence in the Arctic Ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
