<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-14</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.101#abs#sent#bioc</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.101</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Parsons_2011, title={Ocean time-series reveals recurring seasonal patterns of virioplankton dynamics in the northwestern Sargasso Sea}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.101}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.101}, number={2}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Parsons, Rachel J and Breitbart, Mya and Lomas, Michael W and Carlson, Craig A}, year={2011}, month={Aug}, pages={273–284}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Ocean time-series reveals recurring seasonal patterns of virioplankton dynamics in the northwestern Sargasso Sea
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>113</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>113</offset>
        <text>There are an estimated 1030 virioplankton in the world oceans, the majority of which are phages (viruses that infect bacteria).
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>241</offset>
        <text>Marine phages encompass enormous genetic diversity, affect biogeochemical cycling of elements, and partially control aspects of prokaryotic production and diversity.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>407</offset>
        <text>Despite their importance, there is a paucity of data describing virioplankton distributions over time and depth in oceanic systems.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>539</offset>
        <text>A decade of high-resolution time-series data collected from the upper 300 m in the northwestern Sargasso Sea revealed recurring temporal and vertical patterns of virioplankton abundance in unprecedented detail.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>750</offset>
        <text>An annual virioplankton maximum developed between 60 and 100 m during periods of summer stratification and eroded during winter convective mixing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>897</offset>
        <text>The timing and vertical positioning of this seasonal pattern was related to variability in water column stability and the dynamics of specific picophytoplankton and heterotrophic bacterioplankton lineages.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1103</offset>
        <text>Between 60 and 100 m, virioplankton abundance was negatively correlated to the dominant heterotrophic bacterioplankton lineage SAR11, as well as the less abundant picophytoplankton, Synechococcus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1300</offset>
        <text>In contrast, virioplankton abundance was positively correlated to the dominant picophytoplankton lineage Prochlorococcus, and the less abundant alpha-proteobacteria, Rhodobacteraceae.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1484</offset>
        <text>Seasonally, virioplankton abundances were highly synchronous with Prochlorococcus distributions and the virioplankton to Prochlorococcus ratio remained remarkably constant during periods of water column stratification.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1703</offset>
        <text>The data suggest that a significant fraction of viruses in the mid-euphotic zone of the subtropical gyres may be cyanophages and patterns in their abundance are largely determined by Prochlorococcus dynamics in response to water column stability.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1950</offset>
        <text>This high-resolution, decadal survey of virioplankton abundance provides insight into the possible controls of virioplankton dynamics in the open ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
