<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-10</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2011.118#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2011.118</infon>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Ruiz_Gonz_lez_2011, title={Sunlight modulates the relative importance of heterotrophic bacteria and picophytoplankton in DMSP-sulphur uptake}, volume={6}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2011.118}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2011.118}, number={3}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Ruiz-González, Clara and Simó, Rafel and Vila-Costa, Maria and Sommaruga, Ruben and Gasol, Josep M}, year={2011}, month={Sep}, pages={650–659}}
</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Sunlight modulates the relative importance of heterotrophic bacteria and picophytoplankton in DMSP-sulphur uptake
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>114</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>114</offset>
        <text>There is a large body of evidence supporting a major role of heterotrophic bacteria in dimethylsulphoniopropionate (DMSP) utilisation as a source of reduced sulphur.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>280</offset>
        <text>However, a role for phototrophic microorganisms has been only recently described and little is known about their contribution to DMSP consumption and the potential modulating effects of sunlight.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>476</offset>
        <text>In an attempt to ascertain the relative quantitative roles of heterotrophic bacteria and picophytoplankton in the osmoheterotrophic uptake of DMSP-sulphur upon exposure to natural sunlight conditions, we incubated northwestern Mediterranean waters under various optical filters and used an array of bulk and single-cell activity methods to trace the fate of added 35S-DMSP.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>850</offset>
        <text>Flow cytometry cell sorting confirmed dark 35S uptake by Prochlorococcus, Synechococcus and heterotrophic bacteria, the latter being the most efficient in terms of uptake on a cell volume basis.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>1045</offset>
        <text>Under exposure to full sunlight, however, the relative contribution of Synechococcus was significantly enhanced, mainly because of the inhibition of heterotrophic bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>1218</offset>
        <text>Microautoradiography showed a strong increase in the proportion of Synechococcus cells actively taking up 35S-DMSP, which, after full sunlight exposure, made up to 15% of total active Bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1412</offset>
        <text>Parallel incubations with 3H-leucine generally showed no clear responses to light.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1495</offset>
        <text>Finally, size-fractionated assimilation experiments showed greater relative cyanobacterial assimilation during the day than at night compared with that of heterotrophic bacteria.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1674</offset>
        <text>Our results show for the first time a major influence of sunlight in regulating the competition among autotrophic and heterotrophic picoplankton for DMSP uptake at both the daily and seasonal time scales.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
