<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#ismej.2013.228#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Pittera_2014, title={Connecting thermal physiology and latitudinal niche partitioning in marine Synechococcus}, volume={8}, ISSN={1751-7370}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.228}, DOI={10.1038/ismej.2013.228}, number={6}, journal={ISME J}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Pittera, Justine and Humily, Florian and Thorel, Maxine and Grulois, Daphné and Garczarek, Laurence and Six, Christophe}, year={2014}, month={Jun}, pages={1221–1236}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/ismej.2013.228</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Connecting thermal physiology and latitudinal niche partitioning in marine Synechococcus
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>89</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>89</offset>
        <text>Marine Synechococcus cyanobacteria constitute a monophyletic group that displays a wide latitudinal distribution, ranging from the equator to the polar fronts.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>249</offset>
        <text>Whether these organisms are all physiologically adapted to stand a large temperature gradient or stenotherms with narrow growth temperature ranges has so far remained unexplored.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>428</offset>
        <text>We submitted a panel of six strains, isolated along a gradient of latitude in the North Atlantic Ocean, to long- and short-term variations of temperature.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>583</offset>
        <text>Upon a downward shift of temperature, the strains showed strikingly distinct resistance, seemingly related to their latitude of isolation, with tropical strains collapsing while northern strains were capable of growing.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>803</offset>
        <text>This behaviour was associated to differential photosynthetic performances.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">7</infon>
        <offset>878</offset>
        <text>In the tropical strains, the rapid photosystem II inactivation and the decrease of the antioxydant beta-carotene relative to chl a suggested a strong induction of oxidative stress.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">8</infon>
        <offset>1059</offset>
        <text>These different responses were related to the thermal preferenda of the strains.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">9</infon>
        <offset>1140</offset>
        <text>The northern strains could grow at 10 degreesC while the other strains preferred higher temperatures.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">10</infon>
        <offset>1242</offset>
        <text>In addition, we pointed out a correspondence between strain isolation temperature and phylogeny.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">11</infon>
        <offset>1339</offset>
        <text>In particular, clades I and IV laboratory strains were all collected in the coldest waters of the distribution area of marine Synechococus.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">12</infon>
        <offset>1479</offset>
        <text>We, however, show that clade I Synechococcus exhibit different levels of adaptation, which apparently reflect their location on the latitudinal temperature gradient.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">13</infon>
        <offset>1645</offset>
        <text>This study reveals the existence of lineages of marine Synechococcus physiologically specialised in different thermal niches, therefore suggesting the existence of temperature ecotypes within the marine Synechococcus radiation.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
