<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<collection>
  <source>Ocean-Certain Corpus</source>
  <date>2017-03-13</date>
  <key></key>
  <infon key="part">abs1</infon>
  <document>
    <id>10.1038#srep00582#abs#sent</id>
    <infon key="bibtex">
 @article{Giosan_2012, title={Early Anthropogenic Transformation of the Danube-Black Sea System}, volume={2}, ISSN={2045-2322}, url={http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/srep00582}, DOI={10.1038/srep00582}, journal={Sci. Rep.}, publisher={Nature Publishing Group}, author={Giosan, Liviu and Coolen, Marco J. L. and Kaplan, Jed O. and Constantinescu, Stefan and Filip, Florin and Filipova-Marinova, Mariana and Kettner, Albert J. and Thom, Nick}, year={2012}, month={Aug}}
</infon>
    <infon key="source">http://dx.doi.org/data/brat/abs1/10.1038/srep00582</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <infon key="type">title</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">1</infon>
        <offset>0</offset>
        <text>Early Anthropogenic Transformation of the Danube-Black Sea System
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>66</offset>
      <infon key="type">body</infon>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">2</infon>
        <offset>66</offset>
        <text>Over the last century humans have altered the export of fluvial materials leading to significant changes in morphology, chemistry, and biology of the coastal ocean.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">3</infon>
        <offset>231</offset>
        <text>Here we present sedimentary, paleoenvironmental and paleogenetic evidence to show that the Black Sea, a nearly enclosed marine basin, was affected by land use long before the changes of the Industrial Era.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">4</infon>
        <offset>437</offset>
        <text>Although watershed hydroclimate was spatially and temporally variable over the last ~3000 years, surface salinity dropped systematically in the Black Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">5</infon>
        <offset>592</offset>
        <text>Sediment loads delivered by Danube River, the main tributary of the Black Sea, significantly increased as land use intensified in the last two millennia, which led to a rapid expansion of its delta.
</text>
      </sentence>
      <sentence>
        <infon key="n">6</infon>
        <offset>791</offset>
        <text>Lastly, proliferation of diatoms and dinoflagellates over the last five to six centuries, when intensive deforestation occurred in Eastern Europe, points to an anthropogenic pulse of river-borne nutrients that radically transformed the food web structure in the Black Sea.
</text>
      </sentence>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
